Ecclesiastes

The Book of

Ecclesiastes

I

^1The words of the Preacher, the son of David, king in Jerusalem. ^2Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher, vanity of vanities; all is vanity. ^3What profit hath a man of all his labour which he taketh under the sun? ^4One generation passeth away, and another generation cometh: but the earth abideth for ever. ^5The sun also ariseth, and the sun goeth down, and hasteth to his place where he arose. ^6The wind goeth toward the south, and turneth about unto the north; it whirleth about continually, and the wind returneth again according to his circuits. ^7All the rivers run into the sea; yet the sea is not full; unto the place from whence the rivers come, thither they return again. ^8All things are full of labour; man cannot utter it: the eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing. ^9The thing that hath been, it is that which shall be; and that which is done is that which shall be done: and there is no new thing under the sun. ^10Is there any thing whereof it may be said, See, this is new? it hath been already of old time, which was before us. ^11There is no remembrance of former things; neither shall there be any remembrance of things that are to come with those that shall come after.

^12I the Preacher was king over Israel in Jerusalem. ^13And I gave my heart to seek and search out by wisdom concerning all things that are done under heaven: this sore travail hath God given to the sons of man to be exercised therewith. ^14I have seen all the works that are done under the sun; and, behold, all is vanity and vexation of spirit. ^15That which is crooked cannot be made straight: and that which is wanting cannot be numbered. ^16I communed with mine own heart, saying, Lo, I am come to great estate, and have gotten more wisdom than all they that have been before me in Jerusalem: yea, my heart had great experience of wisdom and knowledge. ^17And I gave my heart to know wisdom, and to know madness and folly: I perceived that this also is vexation of spirit. ^18For in much wisdom is much grief: and he that increaseth knowledge increaseth sorrow.

II

^1I said in mine heart, Go to now, I will prove thee with mirth, therefore enjoy pleasure: and, behold, this also is vanity. ^2I said of laughter, It is mad: and of mirth, What doeth it? ^3I sought in mine heart to give myself unto wine, yet acquainting mine heart with wisdom; and to lay hold on folly, till I might see what was that good for the sons of men, which they should do under the heaven all the days of their life. ^4I made me great works; I builded me houses; I planted me vineyards: ^5I made me gardens and orchards, and I planted trees in them of all kind of fruits: ^6I made me pools of water, to water therewith the wood that bringeth forth trees: ^7I got me servants and maidens, and had servants born in my house; also I had great possessions of great and small cattle above all that were in Jerusalem before me: ^8I gathered me also silver and gold, and the peculiar treasure of kings and of the provinces: I gat me men singers and women singers, and the delights of the sons of men, as musical instruments, and that of all sorts. ^9So I was great, and increased more than all that were before me in Jerusalem: also my wisdom remained with me. ^10And whatsoever mine eyes desired I kept not from them, I withheld not my heart from any joy; for my heart rejoiced in all my labour: and this was my portion of all my labour. ^11Then I looked on all the works that my hands had wrought, and on the labour that I had laboured to do: and, behold, all was vanity and vexation of spirit, and there was no profit under the sun.

^12And I turned myself to behold wisdom, and madness, and folly: for what can the man do that cometh after the king? even that which hath been already done. ^13Then I saw that wisdom excelleth folly, as far as light excelleth darkness. ^14The wise man’s eyes are in his head; but the fool walketh in darkness: and I myself perceived also that one event happeneth to them all. ^15Then said I in my heart, As it happeneth to the fool, so it happeneth even to me; and why was I then more wise? Then I said in my heart, that this also is vanity. ^16For there is no remembrance of the wise more than of the fool for ever; seeing that which now is in the days to come shall all be forgotten. And how dieth the wise man? as the fool.

^17Therefore I hated life; because the work that is wrought under the sun is grievous unto me: for all is vanity and vexation of spirit.

^18Yea, I hated all my labour which I had taken under the sun: because I should leave it unto the man that shall be after me. ^19And who knoweth whether he shall be a wise man or a fool? yet shall he have rule over all my labour wherein I have laboured, and wherein I have shewed myself wise under the sun. This is also vanity. ^20Therefore I went about to cause my heart to despair of all the labour which I took under the sun. ^21For there is a man whose labour is in wisdom, and in knowledge, and in equity; yet to a man that hath not laboured therein shall he leave it for his portion. This also is vanity and a great evil. ^22For what hath man of all his labour, and of the vexation of his heart, wherein he hath laboured under the sun? ^23For all his days are sorrows, and his travail grief; yea, his heart taketh not rest in the night. This is also vanity.

^24There is nothing better for a man, than that he should eat and drink, and that he should make his soul enjoy good in his labour. This also I saw, that it was from the hand of God. ^25For who can eat, or who else can hasten hereunto, more than I? ^26For God giveth to a man that is good in his sight wisdom, and knowledge, and joy: but to the sinner he giveth travail, to gather and to heap up, that he may give to him that is good before God. This also is vanity and vexation of spirit.

III

^1To every thing there is a season, and a time to every purpose under the heaven:

^2A time to be born, and a time to die;
A time to plant, and a time to pluck up that which is planted;
^3A time to kill, and a time to heal;
A time to break down, and a time to build up;
^4A time to weep, and a time to laugh;
A time to mourn, and a time to dance;
^5A time to cast away stones, and a time to gather stones together;
A time to embrace, and a time to refrain from embracing;
^6A time to get, and a time to lose;
A time to keep, and a time to cast away;
^7A time to rend, and a time to sew;
A time to keep silence, and a time to speak;
^8A time to love, and a time to hate;
A time of war, and a time of peace.

^9What profit hath he that worketh in that wherein he laboureth? ^10I have seen the travail, which God hath given to the sons of men to be exercised in it. ^11He hath made every thing beautiful in his time: also he hath set the world in their heart, so that no man can find out the work that God maketh from the beginning to the end. ^12I know that there is no good in them, but for a man to rejoice, and to do good in his life. ^13And also that every man should eat and drink, and enjoy the good of all his labour, it is the gift of God. ^14I know that, whatsoever God doeth, it shall be for ever: nothing can be put to it, nor any thing taken from it: and God doeth it, that men should fear before him. ^15That which hath been is now; and that which is to be hath already been; and God requireth that which is past.

^16And moreover I saw under the sun the place of judgment, that wickedness was there; and the place of righteousness, that iniquity was there. ^17I said in mine heart, God shall judge the righteous and the wicked: for there is a time there for every purpose and for every work. ^18I said in mine heart concerning the estate of the sons of men, that God might manifest them, and that they might see that they themselves are beasts. ^19For that which befalleth the sons of men befalleth beasts; even one thing befalleth them: as the one dieth, so dieth the other; yea, they have all one breath; so that a man hath no preeminence above a beast: for all is vanity. ^20All go unto one place; all are of the dust, and all turn to dust again. ^21Who knoweth the spirit of man that goeth upward, and the spirit of the beast that goeth downward to the earth? ^22Wherefore I perceive that there is nothing better, than that a man should rejoice in his own works; for that is his portion: for who shall bring him to see what shall be after him?

IV

^1So I returned, and considered all the oppressions that are done under the sun: and behold the tears of such as were oppressed, and they had no comforter; and on the side of their oppressors there was power; but they had no comforter. ^2Wherefore I praised the dead which are already dead more than the living which are yet alive. ^3Yea, better is he than both they, which hath not yet been, who hath not seen the evil work that is done under the sun.

^4Again, I considered all travail, and every right work, that for this a man is envied of his neighbour. This is also vanity and vexation of spirit. ^5The fool foldeth his hands together, and eateth his own flesh. ^6Better is an handful with quietness, than both the hands full with travail and vexation of spirit.

^7Then I returned, and I saw vanity under the sun. ^8There is one alone, and there is not a second; yea, he hath neither child nor brother: yet is there no end of all his labour; neither is his eye satisfied with riches; neither saith he, For whom do I labour, and bereave my soul of good? This is also vanity, yea, it is a sore travail. ^9Two are better than one; because they have a good reward for their labour. ^10For if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow: but woe to him that is alone when he falleth; for he hath not another to help him up. ^11Again, if two lie together, then they have heat: but how can one be warm alone? ^12And if one prevail against him, two shall withstand him; and a threefold cord is not quickly broken.

^13Better is a poor and a wise child than an old and foolish king, who will no more be admonished. ^14For out of prison he cometh to reign; whereas also he that is born in his kingdom becometh poor. ^15I considered all the living which walk under the sun, with the second child that shall stand up in his stead. ^16There is no end of all the people, even of all that have been before them: they also that come after shall not rejoice in him. Surely this also is vanity and vexation of spirit.

V

^1Keep thy foot when thou goest to the house of God, and be more ready to hear, than to give the sacrifice of fools: for they consider not that they do evil. ^2Be not rash with thy mouth, and let not thine heart be hasty to utter any thing before God: for God is in heaven, and thou upon earth: therefore let thy words be few. ^3For a dream cometh through the multitude of business; and a fool’s voice is known by multitude of words. ^4When thou vowest a vow unto God, defer not to pay it; for he hath no pleasure in fools: pay that which thou hast vowed. ^5Better is it that thou shouldest not vow, than that thou shouldest vow and not pay. ^6Suffer not thy mouth to cause thy flesh to sin; neither say thou before the angel, that it was an error: wherefore should God be angry at thy voice, and destroy the work of thine hands? ^7For in the multitude of dreams and many words there are also divers vanities: but fear thou God.

^8If thou seest the oppression of the poor, and violent perverting of judgment and justice in a province, marvel not at the matter: for he that is higher than the highest regardeth; and there be higher than they. ^9Moreover the profit of the earth is for all: the king himself is served by the field.

^10He that loveth silver shall not be satisfied with silver; nor he that loveth abundance with increase: this is also vanity. ^11When goods increase, they are increased that eat them: and what good is there to the owners thereof, saving the beholding of them with their eyes? ^12The sleep of a labouring man is sweet, whether he eat little or much: but the abundance of the rich will not suffer him to sleep.

^13There is a sore evil which I have seen under the sun, namely, riches kept for the owners thereof to their hurt. ^14But those riches perish by evil travail: and he begetteth a son, and there is nothing in his hand. ^15As he came forth of his mother’s womb, naked shall he return to go as he came, and shall take nothing of his labour, which he may carry away in his hand. ^16And this also is a sore evil, that in all points as he came, so shall he go: and what profit hath he that hath laboured for the wind? ^17All his days also he eateth in darkness, and he hath much sorrow and wrath with his sickness.

^18Behold that which I have seen: it is good and comely for one to eat and to drink, and to enjoy the good of all his labour that he taketh under the sun all the days of his life, which God giveth him: for it is his portion. ^19Every man also to whom God hath given riches and wealth, and hath given him power to eat thereof, and to take his portion, and to rejoice in his labour; this is the gift of God. ^20For he shall not much remember the days of his life; because God answereth him in the joy of his heart.

VI

^1There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, and it is common among men: ^2a man to whom God hath given riches, wealth, and honour, so that he wanteth nothing for his soul of all that he desireth, yet God giveth him not power to eat thereof, but a stranger eateth it: this is vanity, and it is an evil disease. ^3If a man beget an hundred children, and live many years, so that the days of his years be many, and his soul be not filled with good, and also that he have no burial; I say, that an untimely birth is better than he. ^4For he cometh in with vanity, and departeth in darkness, and his name shall be covered with darkness. ^5Moreover he hath not seen the sun, nor known any thing: this hath more rest than the other. ^6Yea, though he live a thousand years twice told, yet hath he seen no good: do not all go to one place?

^7All the labour of man is for his mouth, and yet the appetite is not filled. ^8For what hath the wise more than the fool? what hath the poor, that knoweth to walk before the living? ^9Better is the sight of the eyes than the wandering of the desire: this is also vanity and vexation of spirit.

^10That which hath been is named already, and it is known that it is man: neither may he contend with him that is mightier than he. ^11Seeing there be many things that increase vanity, what is man the better? ^12For who knoweth what is good for man in this life, all the days of his vain life which he spendeth as a shadow? for who can tell a man what shall be after him under the sun?

VII

^1A good name is better than precious ointment; and the day of death than the day of one’s birth. ^2It is better to go to the house of mourning, than to go to the house of feasting: for that is the end of all men; and the living will lay it to his heart. ^3Sorrow is better than laughter: for by the sadness of the countenance the heart is made better. ^4The heart of the wise is in the house of mourning; but the heart of fools is in the house of mirth.

^5It is better to hear the rebuke of the wise, than for a man to hear the song of fools. ^6For as the crackling of thorns under a pot, so is the laughter of the fool: this also is vanity. ^7Surely oppression maketh a wise man mad; and a gift destroyeth the heart.

^8Better is the end of a thing than the beginning thereof: and the patient in spirit is better than the proud in spirit. ^9Be not hasty in thy spirit to be angry: for anger resteth in the bosom of fools. ^10Say not thou, What is the cause that the former days were better than these? for thou dost not enquire wisely concerning this.

^11Wisdom is good with an inheritance: and by it there is profit to them that see the sun. ^12For wisdom is a defence, and money is a defence: but the excellency of knowledge is, that wisdom giveth life to them that have it. ^13Consider the work of God: for who can make that straight, which he hath made crooked? ^14In the day of prosperity be joyful, but in the day of adversity consider: God also hath set the one over against the other, to the end that man should find nothing after him.

^15All things have I seen in the days of my vanity: there is a just man that perisheth in his righteousness, and there is a wicked man that prolongeth his life in his wickedness. ^16Be not righteous over much; neither make thyself over wise: why shouldest thou destroy thyself? ^17Be not over much wicked, neither be thou foolish: why shouldest thou die before thy time? ^18It is good that thou shouldest take hold of this; yea, also from this withdraw not thine hand: for he that feareth God shall come forth of them all.

^19Wisdom strengtheneth the wise more than ten mighty men which are in the city. ^20For there is not a just man upon earth, that doeth good, and sinneth not. ^21Also take no heed unto all words that are spoken; lest thou hear thy servant curse thee: ^22for oftentimes also thine own heart knoweth that thou thyself likewise hast cursed others.

^23All this have I proved by wisdom: I said, I will be wise; but it was far from me. ^24That which is far off, and exceeding deep, who can find it out? ^25I applied mine heart to know, and to search, and to seek out wisdom, and the reason of things, and to know the wickedness of folly, even of foolishness and madness: ^26and I find more bitter than death the woman, whose heart is snares and nets, and her hands as bands: whoso pleaseth God shall escape from her; but the sinner shall be taken by her. ^27Behold, this have I found, saith the preacher, counting one by one, to find out the account: ^28which yet my soul seeketh, but I find not: one man among a thousand have I found; but a woman among all those have I not found. ^29Lo, this only have I found, that God hath made man upright; but they have sought out many inventions.

VIII

^1Who is as the wise man? and who knoweth the interpretation of a thing? a man’s wisdom maketh his face to shine, and the boldness of his face shall be changed. ^2I counsel thee to keep the king’s commandment, and that in regard of the oath of God. ^3Be not hasty to go out of his sight: stand not in an evil thing; for he doeth whatsoever pleaseth him. ^4Where the word of a king is, there is power: and who may say unto him, What doest thou? ^5Whoso keepeth the commandment shall feel no evil thing: and a wise man’s heart discerneth both time and judgment. ^6Because to every purpose there is time and judgment, therefore the misery of man is great upon him. ^7For he knoweth not that which shall be: for who can tell him when it shall be? ^8There is no man that hath power over the spirit to retain the spirit; neither hath he power in the day of death: and there is no discharge in that war; neither shall wickedness deliver those that are given to it.

^9All this have I seen, and applied my heart unto every work that is done under the sun: there is a time wherein one man ruleth over another to his own hurt. ^10And so I saw the wicked buried, who had come and gone from the place of the holy, and they were forgotten in the city where they had so done: this is also vanity. ^11Because sentence against an evil work is not executed speedily, therefore the heart of the sons of men is fully set in them to do evil. ^12Though a sinner do evil an hundred times, and his days be prolonged, yet surely I know that it shall be well with them that fear God, which fear before him: ^13but it shall not be well with the wicked, neither shall he prolong his days, which are as a shadow; because he feareth not before God.

^14There is a vanity which is done upon the earth; that there be just men, unto whom it happeneth according to the work of the wicked; again, there be wicked men, to whom it happeneth according to the work of the righteous: I said that this also is vanity. ^15Then I commended mirth, because a man hath no better thing under the sun, than to eat, and to drink, and to be merry: for that shall abide with him of his labour the days of his life, which God giveth him under the sun.

^16When I applied mine heart to know wisdom, and to see the business that is done upon the earth: (for also there is that neither day nor night seeth sleep with his eyes:) ^17then I beheld all the work of God, that a man cannot find out the work that is done under the sun: because though a man labour to seek it out, yet he shall not find it; yea farther; though a wise man think to know it, yet shall he not be able to find it.

IX

^1For all this I considered in my heart even to declare all this, that the righteous, and the wise, and their works, are in the hand of God: no man knoweth either love or hatred by all that is before them.

^2All things come alike to all: there is one event to the righteous, and to the wicked; to the good and to the clean, and to the unclean; to him that sacrificeth, and to him that sacrificeth not: as is the good, so is the sinner; and he that sweareth, as he that feareth an oath. ^3This is an evil among all things that are done under the sun, that there is one event unto all: yea, also the heart of the sons of men is full of evil, and madness is in their heart while they live, and after that they go to the dead.

^4For to him that is joined to all the living there is hope: for a living dog is better than a dead lion. ^5For the living know that they shall die: but the dead know not any thing, neither have they any more a reward; for the memory of them is forgotten. ^6Also their love, and their hatred, and their envy, is now perished; neither have they any more a portion for ever in any thing that is done under the sun.

^7Go thy way, eat thy bread with joy, and drink thy wine with a merry heart; for God now accepteth thy works. ^8Let thy garments be always white; and let thy head lack no ointment. ^9Live joyfully with the wife whom thou lovest all the days of the life of thy vanity, which he hath given thee under the sun, all the days of thy vanity: for that is thy portion in this life, and in thy labour which thou takest under the sun. ^10Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with thy might; for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in the grave, whither thou goest.

^11I returned, and saw under the sun, that the race is not to the swift, nor the battle to the strong, neither yet bread to the wise, nor yet riches to men of understanding, nor yet favour to men of skill; but time and chance happeneth to them all. ^12For man also knoweth not his time: as the fishes that are taken in an evil net, and as the birds that are caught in the snare; so are the sons of men snared in an evil time, when it falleth suddenly upon them.

^13This wisdom have I seen also under the sun, and it seemed great unto me: ^14there was a little city, and few men within it; and there came a great king against it, and besieged it, and built great bulwarks against it: ^15now there was found in it a poor wise man, and he by his wisdom delivered the city; yet no man remembered that same poor man. ^16Then said I, Wisdom is better than strength: nevertheless the poor man’s wisdom is despised, and his words are not heard. ^17The words of wise men are heard in quiet more than the cry of him that ruleth among fools. ^18Wisdom is better than weapons of war: but one sinner destroyeth much good.

X

^1Dead flies cause the ointment of the apothecary to send forth a stinking savour: so doth a little folly him that is in reputation for wisdom and honour. ^2A wise man’s heart is at his right hand; but a fool’s heart at his left. ^3Yea also, when he that is a fool walketh by the way, his wisdom faileth him, and he saith to every one that he is a fool. ^4If the spirit of the ruler rise up against thee, leave not thy place; for yielding pacifieth great offences. ^5There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, as an error which proceedeth from the ruler: ^6folly is set in great dignity, and the rich sit in low place. ^7I have seen servants upon horses, and princes walking as servants upon the earth.

^8He that diggeth a pit shall fall into it; and whoso breaketh an hedge, a serpent shall bite him. ^9Whoso removeth stones shall be hurt therewith; and he that cleaveth wood shall be endangered thereby. ^10If the iron be blunt, and he do not whet the edge, then must he put to more strength: but wisdom is profitable to direct. ^11Surely the serpent will bite without enchantment; and a babbler is no better.

^12The words of a wise man’s mouth are gracious; but the lips of a fool will swallow up himself. ^13The beginning of the words of his mouth is foolishness: and the end of his talk is mischievous madness. ^14A fool also is full of words: a man cannot tell what shall be; and what shall be after him, who can tell him? ^15The labour of the foolish wearieth every one of them, because he knoweth not how to go to the city.

^16Woe to thee, O land, when thy king is a child, and thy princes eat in the morning! ^17Blessed art thou, O land, when thy king is the son of nobles, and thy princes eat in due season, for strength, and not for drunkenness! ^18By much slothfulness the building decayeth; and through idleness of the hands the house droppeth through. ^19A feast is made for laughter, and wine maketh merry: but money answereth all things. ^20Curse not the king, no not in thy thought; and curse not the rich in thy bedchamber: for a bird of the air shall carry the voice, and that which hath wings shall tell the matter.

XI

^1Cast thy bread upon the waters: for thou shalt find it after many days. ^2Give a portion to seven, and also to eight; for thou knowest not what evil shall be upon the earth. ^3If the clouds be full of rain, they empty themselves upon the earth: and if the tree fall toward the south, or toward the north, in the place where the tree falleth, there it shall be. ^4He that observeth the wind shall not sow; and he that regardeth the clouds shall not reap. ^5As thou knowest not what is the way of the spirit, nor how the bones do grow in the womb of her that is with child: even so thou knowest not the works of God who maketh all. ^6In the morning sow thy seed, and in the evening withhold not thine hand: for thou knowest not whether shall prosper, either this or that, or whether they both shall be alike good. ^7Truly the light is sweet, and a pleasant thing it is for the eyes to behold the sun: ^8but if a man live many years, and rejoice in them all; yet let him remember the days of darkness; for they shall be many. All that cometh is vanity.

^9Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth; and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thine heart, and in the sight of thine eyes: but know thou, that for all these things God will bring thee into judgment. ^10Therefore remove sorrow from thy heart, and put away evil from thy flesh: for childhood and youth are vanity.

XII

^1Remember now thy Creator in the days of thy youth, while the evil days come not, nor the years draw nigh, when thou shalt say, I have no pleasure in them; ^2while the sun, or the light, or the moon, or the stars, be not darkened, nor the clouds return after the rain: ^3in the day when the keepers of the house shall tremble, and the strong men shall bow themselves, and the grinders cease because they are few, and those that look out of the windows be darkened, ^4and the doors shall be shut in the streets, when the sound of the grinding is low, and he shall rise up at the voice of the bird, and all the daughters of musick shall be brought low; ^5also when they shall be afraid of that which is high, and fears shall be in the way, and the almond tree shall flourish, and the grasshopper shall be a burden, and desire shall fail: because man goeth to his long home, and the mourners go about the streets: ^6or ever the silver cord be loosed, or the golden bowl be broken, or the pitcher be broken at the fountain, or the wheel broken at the cistern. ^7Then shall the dust return to the earth as it was: and the spirit shall return unto God who gave it. ^8Vanity of vanities, saith the preacher; all is vanity. ^9And moreover, because the preacher was wise, he still taught the people knowledge; yea, he gave good heed, and sought out, and set in order many proverbs. ^10The preacher sought to find out acceptable words: and that which was written was upright, even words of truth.

^11The words of the wise are as goads, and as nails fastened by the masters of assemblies, which are given from one shepherd. ^12And further, by these, my son, be admonished: of making many books there is no end; and much study is a weariness of the flesh.

^13Let us hear the conclusion of the whole matter: Fear God, and keep his commandments: for this is the whole duty of man. ^14For God shall bring every work into judgment, with every secret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.

Lamentations

The Book of

Lamentations

I

^1How doth the city sit solitary, that was full of people! how is she become as a widow! she that was great among the nations, and princess among the provinces, how is she become tributary!

^2She weepeth sore in the night, and her tears are on her cheeks: among all her lovers she hath none to comfort her: all her friends have dealt treacherously with her, they are become her enemies.

^3Judah is gone into captivity because of affliction, and because of great servitude: she dwelleth among the heathen, she findeth no rest: all her persecutors overtook her between the straits.

^4The ways of Zion do mourn, because none come to the solemn feasts: all her gates are desolate: her priests sigh, her virgins are afflicted, and she is in bitterness.

^5Her adversaries are the chief, her enemies prosper; for the Lord hath afflicted her for the multitude of her transgressions: her children are gone into captivity before the enemy.

^6And from the daughter of Zion all her beauty is departed: her princes are become like harts that find no pasture, and they are gone without strength before the pursuer.

^7Jerusalem remembered in the days of her affliction and of her miseries all her pleasant things that she had in the days of old, when her people fell into the hand of the enemy, and none did help her: the adversaries saw her, and did mock at her sabbaths.

^8Jerusalem hath grievously sinned; therefore she is removed: all that honoured her despise her, because they have seen her nakedness: yea, she sigheth, and turneth backward.

^9Her filthiness is in her skirts; she remembereth not her last end; therefore she came down wonderfully: she had no comforter. O Lord, behold my affliction: for the enemy hath magnified himself.

^10The adversary hath spread out his hand upon all her pleasant things: for she hath seen that the heathen entered into her sanctuary, whom thou didst command that they should not enter into thy congregation.

^11All her people sigh, they seek bread; they have given their pleasant things for meat to relieve the soul: see, O Lord, and consider; for I am become vile.

^12Is it nothing to you, all ye that pass by? behold, and see if there be any sorrow like unto my sorrow, which is done unto me, wherewith the Lord hath afflicted me in the day of his fierce anger.

^13From above hath he sent fire into my bones, and it prevaileth against them: he hath spread a net for my feet, he hath turned me back: he hath made me desolate and faint all the day.

^14The yoke of my transgressions is bound by his hand: they are wreathed, and come up upon my neck: he hath made my strength to fall, the Lord hath delivered me into their hands, from whom I am not able to rise up.

^15The Lord hath trodden under foot all my mighty men in the midst of me: he hath called an assembly against me to crush my young men: the Lord hath trodden the virgin, the daughter of Judah, as in a winepress.

^16For these things I weep; mine eye, mine eye runneth down with water, because the comforter that should relieve my soul is far from me: my children are desolate, because the enemy prevailed.

^17Zion spreadeth forth her hands, and there is none to comfort her: the Lord hath commanded concerning Jacob, that his adversaries should be round about him: Jerusalem is as a menstruous woman among them.

^18The Lord is righteous; for I have rebelled against his commandment: hear, I pray you, all people, and behold my sorrow: my virgins and my young men are gone into captivity.

^19I called for my lovers, but they deceived me: my priests and mine elders gave up the ghost in the city, while they sought their meat to relieve their souls.

^20Behold, O Lord; for I am in distress: my bowels are troubled; mine heart is turned within me; for I have grievously rebelled: abroad the sword bereaveth, at home there is as death.

^21They have heard that I sigh: there is none to comfort me: all mine enemies have heard of my trouble; they are glad that thou hast done it: thou wilt bring the day that thou hast called, and they shall be like unto me.

^22Let all their wickedness come before thee; and do unto them, as thou hast done unto me for all my transgressions: for my sighs are many, and my heart is faint.

II

^1How hath the Lord covered the daughter of Zion with a cloud in his anger, and cast down from heaven unto the earth the beauty of Israel, and remembered not his footstool in the day of his anger!

^2The Lord hath swallowed up all the habitations of Jacob, and hath not pitied: he hath thrown down in his wrath the strong holds of the daughter of Judah; he hath brought them down to the ground: he hath polluted the kingdom and the princes thereof.

^3He hath cut off in his fierce anger all the horn of Israel: he hath drawn back his right hand from before the enemy, and he burned against Jacob like a flaming fire, which devoureth round about.

^4He hath bent his bow like an enemy: he stood with his right hand as an adversary, and slew all that were pleasant to the eye in the tabernacle of the daughter of Zion: he poured out his fury like fire.

^5The Lord was as an enemy: he hath swallowed up Israel, he hath swallowed up all her palaces: he hath destroyed his strong holds, and hath increased in the daughter of Judah mourning and lamentation.

^6And he hath violently taken away his tabernacle, as if it were of a garden: he hath destroyed his places of the assembly: the Lord hath caused the solemn feasts and sabbaths to be forgotten in Zion, and hath despised in the indignation of his anger the king and the priest.

^7The Lord hath cast off his altar, he hath abhorred his sanctuary, he hath given up into the hand of the enemy the walls of her palaces; they have made a noise in the house of the Lord, as in the day of a solemn feast.

^8The Lord hath purposed to destroy the wall of the daughter of Zion: he hath stretched out a line, he hath not withdrawn his hand from destroying: therefore he made the rampart and the wall to lament; they languished together.

^9Her gates are sunk into the ground; he hath destroyed and broken her bars: her king and her princes are among the Gentiles: the law is no more; her prophets also find no vision from the Lord.

^10The elders of the daughter of Zion sit upon the ground, and keep silence: they have cast up dust upon their heads; they have girded themselves with sackcloth: the virgins of Jerusalem hang down their heads to the ground.

^11Mine eyes do fail with tears, my bowels are troubled, my liver is poured upon the earth, for the destruction of the daughter of my people; because the children and the sucklings swoon in the streets of the city.

^12They say to their mothers, Where is corn and wine? when they swooned as the wounded in the streets of the city, when their soul was poured out into their mothers’ bosom.

^13What thing shall I take to witness for thee? what thing shall I liken to thee, O daughter of Jerusalem? what shall I equal to thee, that I may comfort thee, O virgin daughter of Zion? for thy breach is great like the sea: who can heal thee?

^14Thy prophets have seen vain and foolish things for thee: and they have not discovered thine iniquity, to turn away thy captivity; but have seen for thee false burdens and causes of banishment.

^15All that pass by clap their hands at thee; they hiss and wag their head at the daughter of Jerusalem, saying, Is this the city that men call The perfection of beauty, The joy of the whole earth?

^16All thine enemies have opened their mouth against thee: they hiss and gnash the teeth: they say, We have swallowed her up: certainly this is the day that we looked for; we have found, we have seen it.

^17The Lord hath done that which he had devised; he hath fulfilled his word that he had commanded in the days of old: he hath thrown down, and hath not pitied: and he hath caused thine enemy to rejoice over thee, he hath set up the horn of thine adversaries.

^18Their heart cried unto the Lord, O wall of the daughter of Zion, let tears run down like a river day and night: give thyself no rest; let not the apple of thine eye cease.

^19Arise, cry out in the night: in the beginning of the watches pour out thine heart like water before the face of the Lord: lift up thy hands toward him for the life of thy young children, that faint for hunger in the top of every street.

^20Behold, O Lord, and consider to whom thou hast done this. Shall the women eat their fruit, and children of a span long? shall the priest and the prophet be slain in the sanctuary of the Lord?

^21The young and the old lie on the ground in the streets: my virgins and my young men are fallen by the sword; thou hast slain them in the day of thine anger; thou hast killed, and not pitied.

^22Thou hast called as in a solemn day my terrors round about, so that in the day of the Lord’s anger none escaped nor remained: those that I have swaddled and brought up hath mine enemy consumed.

III

^1I am the man that hath seen affliction by the rod of his wrath.

^2He hath led me, and brought me into darkness, but not into light.

^3Surely against me is he turned; he turneth his hand against me all the day.

^4My flesh and my skin hath he made old; he hath broken my bones.

^5He hath builded against me, and compassed me with gall and travail.

^6He hath set me in dark places, as they that be dead of old.

^7He hath hedged me about, that I cannot get out: he hath made my chain heavy.

^8Also when I cry and shout, he shutteth out my prayer.

^9He hath inclosed my ways with hewn stone, he hath made my paths crooked.

^10He was unto me as a bear lying in wait, and as a lion in secret places.

^11He hath turned aside my ways, and pulled me in pieces: he hath made me desolate.

^12He hath bent his bow, and set me as a mark for the arrow.

^13He hath caused the arrows of his quiver to enter into my reins.

^14I was a derision to all my people; and their song all the day.

^15He hath filled me with bitterness, he hath made me drunken with wormwood.

^16He hath also broken my teeth with gravel stones, he hath covered me with ashes.

^17And thou hast removed my soul far off from peace: I forgat prosperity.

^18And I said, My strength and my hope is perished from the Lord:

^19Remembering mine affliction and my misery, the wormwood and the gall.

^20My soul hath them still in remembrance, and is humbled in me.

^21This I recall to my mind, therefore have I hope.

^22It is of the Lord’s mercies that we are not consumed, because his compassions fail not.

^23They are new every morning: great is thy faithfulness.

^24The Lord is my portion, saith my soul; therefore will I hope in him.

^25The Lord is good unto them that wait for him, to the soul that seeketh him.

^26It is good that a man should both hope and quietly wait for the salvation of the Lord.

^27It is good for a man that he bear the yoke of his youth.

^28He sitteth alone and keepeth silence, because he hath borne it upon him.

^29He putteth his mouth in the dust; if so be there may be hope.

^30He giveth his cheek to him that smiteth him: he is filled full with reproach.

^31For the Lord will not cast off for ever:

^32But though he cause grief, yet will he have compassion according to the multitude of his mercies.

^33For he doth not afflict willingly nor grieve the children of men.

^34To crush under his feet all the prisoners of the earth.

^35To turn aside the right of a man before the face of the most High,

^36To subvert a man in his cause, the Lord approveth not.

^37Who is he that saith, and it cometh to pass, when the Lord commandeth it not?

^38Out of the mouth of the most High proceedeth not evil and good?

^39Wherefore doth a living man complain, a man for the punishment of his sins?

^40Let us search and try our ways, and turn again to the Lord.

^41Let us lift up our heart with our hands unto God in the heavens.

^42We have transgressed and have rebelled: thou hast not pardoned.

^43Thou hast covered with anger, and persecuted us: thou hast slain, thou hast not pitied.

^44Thou hast covered thyself with a cloud, that our prayer should not pass through.

^45Thou hast made us as the offscouring and refuse in the midst of the people.

^46All our enemies have opened their mouths against us.

^47Fear and a snare is come upon us, desolation and destruction.

^48Mine eye runneth down with rivers of water for the destruction of the daughter of my people.

^49Mine eye trickleth down, and ceaseth not, without any intermission.

^50Till the Lord look down, and behold from heaven.

^51Mine eye affecteth mine heart because of all the daughters of my city.

^52Mine enemies chased me sore, like a bird, without cause.

^53They have cut off my life in the dungeon, and cast a stone upon me.

^54Waters flowed over mine head; then I said, I am cut off.

^55I called upon thy name, O Lord, out of the low dungeon.

^56Thou hast heard my voice: hide not thine ear at my breathing, at my cry.

^57Thou drewest near in the day that I called upon thee: thou saidst, Fear not.

^58O Lord, thou hast pleaded the causes of my soul; thou hast redeemed my life.

^59O Lord, thou hast seen my wrong: judge thou my cause.

^60Thou hast seen all their vengeance and all their imaginations against me.

^61Thou hast heard their reproach, O Lord, and all their imaginations against me;

^62The lips of those that rose up against me, and their device against me all the day.

^63Behold their sitting down, and their rising up; I am their musick.

^64Render unto them a recompence, O Lord, according to the work of their hands.

^65Give them sorrow of heart, thy curse unto them.

^66Persecute and destroy them in anger from under the heavens of the Lord.

IV

^1How is the gold become dim! how is the most fine gold changed! the stones of the sanctuary are poured out in the top of every street.

^2The precious sons of Zion, comparable to fine gold, how are they esteemed as earthen pitchers, the work of the hands of the potter!

^3Even the sea monsters draw out the breast, they give suck to their young ones: the daughter of my people is become cruel, like the ostriches in the wilderness.

^4The tongue of the sucking child cleaveth to the roof of his mouth for thirst: the young children ask bread, and no man breaketh it unto them.

^5They that did feed delicately are desolate in the streets: they that were brought up in scarlet embrace dunghills.

^6For the punishment of the iniquity of the daughter of my people is greater than the punishment of the sin of Sodom, that was overthrown as in a moment, and no hands stayed on her.

^7Her Nazarites were purer than snow, they were whiter than milk, they were more ruddy in body than rubies, their polishing was of sapphire:

^8Their visage is blacker than a coal; they are not known in the streets: their skin cleaveth to their bones; it is withered, it is become like a stick.

^9They that be slain with the sword are better than they that be slain with hunger: for these pine away, stricken through for want of the fruits of the field.

^10The hands of the pitiful women have sodden their own children: they were their meat in the destruction of the daughter of my people.

^11The Lord hath accomplished his fury; he hath poured out his fierce anger, and hath kindled a fire in Zion, and it hath devoured the foundations thereof.

^12The kings of the earth, and all the inhabitants of the world, would not have believed that the adversary and the enemy should have entered into the gates of Jerusalem.

^13For the sins of her prophets, and the iniquities of her priests, that have shed the blood of the just in the midst of her,

^14They have wandered as blind men in the streets, they have polluted themselves with blood, so that men could not touch their garments.

^15They cried unto them, Depart ye; it is unclean; depart, depart, touch not: when they fled away and wandered, they said among the heathen, They shall no more sojourn there.

^16The anger of the Lord hath divided them; he will no more regard them: they respected not the persons of the priests, they favoured not the elders.

^17As for us, our eyes as yet failed for our vain help: in our watching we have watched for a nation that could not save us.

^18They hunt our steps, that we cannot go in our streets: our end is near, our days are fulfilled; for our end is come.

^19Our persecutors are swifter than the eagles of the heaven: they pursued us upon the mountains, they laid wait for us in the wilderness.

^20The breath of our nostrils, the anointed of the Lord, was taken in their pits, of whom we said, Under his shadow we shall live among the heathen.

^21Rejoice and be glad, O daughter of Edom, that dwellest in the land of Uz; the cup also shall pass through unto thee: thou shalt be drunken, and shalt make thyself naked.

^22The punishment of thine iniquity is accomplished, O daughter of Zion; he will no more carry thee away into captivity: he will visit thine iniquity, O daughter of Edom; he will discover thy sins.

V

^1Remember, O Lord, what is come upon us: consider, and behold our reproach.

^2Our inheritance is turned to strangers, our houses to aliens.

^3We are orphans and fatherless, our mothers are as widows.

^4We have drunken our water for money; our wood is sold unto us.

^5Our necks are under persecution: we labour, and have no rest.

^6We have given the hand to the Egyptians, and to the Assyrians, to be satisfied with bread.

^7Our fathers have sinned, and are not; and we have borne their iniquities.

^8Servants have ruled over us: there is none that doth deliver us out of their hand.

^9We gat our bread with the peril of our lives because of the sword of the wilderness.

^10Our skin was black like an oven because of the terrible famine.

^11They ravished the women in Zion, and the maids in the cities of Judah.

^12Princes are hanged up by their hand: the faces of elders were not honoured.

^13They took the young men to grind, and the children fell under the wood.

^14The elders have ceased from the gate, the young men from their musick.

^15The joy of our heart is ceased; our dance is turned into mourning.

^16The crown is fallen from our head: woe unto us, that we have sinned!

^17For this our heart is faint; for these things our eyes are dim.

^18Because of the mountain of Zion, which is desolate, the foxes walk upon it.

^19Thou, O Lord, remainest for ever; thy throne from generation to generation.

^20Wherefore dost thou forget us for ever, and forsake us so long time?

^21Turn thou us unto thee, O Lord, and we shall be turned; renew our days as of old.

^22But thou hast utterly rejected us; thou art very wroth against us.

Joel

The Book of

Joel

I

^1The word of the Lord that came to Joel the son of Pethuel.

^2Hear this, ye old men, and give ear, all ye inhabitants of the land. Hath this been in your days, or even in the days of your fathers?

^3Tell ye your children of it, and let your children tell their children, and their children another generation.

^4That which the palmerworm hath left hath the locust eaten; and that which the locust hath left hath the cankerworm eaten; and that which the cankerworm hath left hath the caterpiller eaten.

^5Awake, ye drunkards, and weep; and howl, all ye drinkers of wine, because of the new wine; for it is cut off from your mouth.

^6For a nation is come up upon my land, strong, and without number, whose teeth are the teeth of a lion, and he hath the cheek teeth of a great lion.

^7He hath laid my vine waste, and barked my fig tree: he hath made it clean bare, and cast it away; the branches thereof are made white.

^8Lament like a virgin girded with sackcloth for the husband of her youth.

^9The meat offering and the drink offering is cut off from the house of the Lord; the priests, the Lord’s ministers, mourn.

^10The field is wasted, the land mourneth; for the corn is wasted: the new wine is dried up, the oil languisheth.

^11Be ye ashamed, O ye husbandmen; howl, O ye vinedressers, for the wheat and for the barley; because the harvest of the field is perished.

^12The vine is dried up, and the fig tree languisheth; the pomegranate tree, the palm tree also, and the apple tree, even all the trees of the field, are withered: because joy is withered away from the sons of men.

^13Gird yourselves, and lament, ye priests: howl, ye ministers of the altar: come, lie all night in sackcloth, ye ministers of my God: for the meat offering and the drink offering is withholden from the house of your God.

^14Sanctify ye a fast, call a solemn assembly, gather the elders and all the inhabitants of the land into the house of the Lord your God, and cry unto the Lord,

^15Alas for the day! for the day of the Lord is at hand, and as a destruction from the Almighty shall it come.

^16Is not the meat cut off before our eyes, yea, joy and gladness from the house of our God?

^17The seed is rotten under their clods, the garners are laid desolate, the barns are broken down; for the corn is withered.

^18How do the beasts groan! the herds of cattle are perplexed, because they have no pasture; yea, the flocks of sheep are made desolate.

^19O Lord, to thee will I cry: for the fire hath devoured the pastures of the wilderness, and the flame hath burned all the trees of the field.

^20The beasts of the field cry also unto thee: for the rivers of waters are dried up, and the fire hath devoured the pastures of the wilderness.

II

^1Blow ye the trumpet in Zion, and sound an alarm in my holy mountain: let all the inhabitants of the land tremble: for the day of the Lord cometh, for it is nigh at hand;

^2A day of darkness and of gloominess, a day of clouds and of thick darkness, as the morning spread upon the mountains: a great people and a strong; there hath not been ever the like, neither shall be any more after it, even to the years of many generations.

^3A fire devoureth before them; and behind them a flame burneth: the land is as the garden of Eden before them, and behind them a desolate wilderness; yea, and nothing shall escape them.

^4The appearance of them is as the appearance of horses; and as horsemen, so shall they run.

^5Like the noise of chariots on the tops of mountains shall they leap, like the noise of a flame of fire that devoureth the stubble, as a strong people set in battle array.

^6Before their face the people shall be much pained: all faces shall gather blackness.

^7They shall run like mighty men; they shall climb the wall like men of war; and they shall march every one on his ways, and they shall not break their ranks:

^8Neither shall one thrust another; they shall walk every one in his path: and when they fall upon the sword, they shall not be wounded.

^9They shall run to and fro in the city; they shall run upon the wall, they shall climb up upon the houses; they shall enter in at the windows like a thief.

^10The earth shall quake before them; the heavens shall tremble: the sun and the moon shall be dark, and the stars shall withdraw their shining:

^11And the Lord shall utter his voice before his army: for his camp is very great: for he is strong that executeth his word: for the day of the Lord is great and very terrible; and who can abide it?

^12Therefore also now, saith the Lord, turn ye even to me with all your heart, and with fasting, and with weeping, and with mourning:

^13And rend your heart, and not your garments, and turn unto the Lord your God: for he is gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and of great kindness, and repenteth him of the evil.

^14Who knoweth if he will return and repent, and leave a blessing behind him; even a meat offering and a drink offering unto the Lord your God?

^15Blow the trumpet in Zion, sanctify a fast, call a solemn assembly:

^16Gather the people, sanctify the congregation, assemble the elders, gather the children, and those that suck the breasts: let the bridegroom go forth of his chamber, and the bride out of her closet.

^17Let the priests, the ministers of the Lord, weep between the porch and the altar, and let them say, Spare thy people, O Lord, and give not thine heritage to reproach, that the heathen should rule over them: wherefore should they say among the people, Where is their God?

^18Then will the Lord be jealous for his land, and pity his people.

^19Yea, the Lord will answer and say unto his people, Behold, I will send you corn, and wine, and oil, and ye shall be satisfied therewith: and I will no more make you a reproach among the heathen:

^20But I will remove far off from you the northern army, and will drive him into a land barren and desolate, with his face toward the east sea, and his hinder part toward the utmost sea, and his stink shall come up, and his ill savour shall come up, because he hath done great things.

^21Fear not, O land; be glad and rejoice: for the Lord will do great things.

^22Be not afraid, ye beasts of the field: for the pastures of the wilderness do spring, for the tree beareth her fruit, the fig tree and the vine do yield their strength.

^23Be glad then, ye children of Zion, and rejoice in the Lord your God: for he hath given you the former rain moderately, and he will cause to come down for you the rain, the former rain, and the latter rain in the first month.

^24And the floors shall be full of wheat, and the vats shall overflow with wine and oil.

^25And I will restore to you the years that the locust hath eaten, the cankerworm, and the caterpiller, and the palmerworm, my great army which I sent among you.

^26And ye shall eat in plenty, and be satisfied, and praise the name of the Lord your God, that hath dealt wondrously with you: and my people shall never be ashamed.

^27And ye shall know that I am in the midst of Israel, and that I am the Lord your God, and none else: and my people shall never be ashamed.

^28And it shall come to pass afterward, that I will pour out my spirit upon all flesh; and your sons and your daughters shall prophesy, your old men shall dream dreams, your young men shall see visions:

^29And also upon the servants and upon the handmaids in those days will I pour out my spirit.

^30And I will shew wonders in the heavens and in the earth, blood, and fire, and pillars of smoke.

^31The sun shall be turned into darkness, and the moon into blood, before the great and terrible day of the Lord come.

^32And it shall come to pass, that whosoever shall call on the name of the Lord shall be delivered: for in mount Zion and in Jerusalem shall be deliverance, as the Lord hath said, and in the remnant whom the Lord shall call.

III

^1For, behold, in those days, and in that time, when I shall bring again the captivity of Judah and Jerusalem,

^2I will also gather all nations, and will bring them down into the valley of Jehoshaphat, and will plead with them there for my people and for my heritage Israel, whom they have scattered among the nations, and parted my land.

^3And they have cast lots for my people; and have given a boy for an harlot, and sold a girl for wine, that they might drink.

^4Yea, and what have ye to do with me, O Tyre, and Zidon, and all the coasts of Palestine? will ye render me a recompence? and if ye recompense me, swiftly and speedily will I return your recompence upon your own head;

^5Because ye have taken my silver and my gold, and have carried into your temples my goodly pleasant things:

^6The children also of Judah and the children of Jerusalem have ye sold unto the Grecians, that ye might remove them far from their border.

^7Behold, I will raise them out of the place whither ye have sold them, and will return your recompence upon your own head:

^8And I will sell your sons and your daughters into the hand of the children of Judah, and they shall sell them to the Sabeans, to a people far off: for the Lord hath spoken it.

^9Proclaim ye this among the Gentiles; Prepare war, wake up the mighty men, let all the men of war draw near; let them come up:

^10Beat your plowshares into swords and your pruninghooks into spears: let the weak say, I am strong.

^11Assemble yourselves, and come, all ye heathen, and gather yourselves together round about: thither cause thy mighty ones to come down, O Lord.

^12Let the heathen be wakened, and come up to the valley of Jehoshaphat: for there will I sit to judge all the heathen round about.

^13Put ye in the sickle, for the harvest is ripe: come, get you down; for the press is full, the fats overflow; for their wickedness is great.

^14Multitudes, multitudes in the valley of decision: for the day of the Lord is near in the valley of decision.

^15The sun and the moon shall be darkened, and the stars shall withdraw their shining.

^16The Lord also shall roar out of Zion, and utter his voice from Jerusalem; and the heavens and the earth shall shake: but the Lord will be the hope of his people, and the strength of the children of Israel.

^17So shall ye know that I am the Lord your God dwelling in Zion, my holy mountain: then shall Jerusalem be holy, and there shall no strangers pass through her any more.

^18And it shall come to pass in that day, that the mountains shall drop down new wine, and the hills shall flow with milk, and all the rivers of Judah shall flow with waters, and a fountain shall come forth out of the house of the Lord, and shall water the valley of Shittim.

^19Egypt shall be a desolation, and Edom shall be a desolate wilderness, for the violence against the children of Judah, because they have shed innocent blood in their land.

^20But Judah shall dwell for ever, and Jerusalem from generation to generation.

^21For I will cleanse their blood that I have not cleansed: for the Lord dwelleth in Zion.

Haggai

The Book of

Haggai

I

^1In the second year of Darius the king, in the sixth month, in the first day of the month, came the word of the Lord by Haggai the prophet unto Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest, saying,

^2Thus speaketh the Lord of hosts, saying, This people say, The time is not come, the time that the Lord’s house should be built.

^3Then came the word of the Lord by Haggai the prophet, saying,

^4Is it time for you, O ye, to dwell in your cieled houses, and this house lie waste?

^5Now therefore thus saith the Lord of hosts; Consider your ways.

^6Ye have sown much, and bring in little; ye eat, but ye have not enough; ye drink, but ye are not filled with drink; ye clothe you, but there is none warm; and he that earneth wages earneth wages to put it into a bag with holes.

^7Thus saith the Lord of hosts; Consider your ways.

^8Go up to the mountain, and bring wood, and build the house; and I will take pleasure in it, and I will be glorified, saith the Lord.

^9Ye looked for much, and, lo it came to little; and when ye brought it home, I did blow upon it. Why? saith the Lord of hosts. Because of mine house that is waste, and ye run every man unto his own house.

^10Therefore the heaven over you is stayed from dew, and the earth is stayed from her fruit.

^11And I called for a drought upon the land, and upon the mountains, and upon the corn, and upon the new wine, and upon the oil, and upon that which the ground bringeth forth, and upon men, and upon cattle, and upon all the labour of the hands.

^12Then Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest, with all the remnant of the people, obeyed the voice of the Lord their God, and the words of Haggai the prophet, as the Lord their God had sent him, and the people did fear before the Lord.

^13Then spake Haggai the Lord’s messenger in the Lord’s message unto the people, saying, I am with you, saith the Lord.

^14And the Lord stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people; and they came and did work in the house of the Lord of hosts, their God,

^15In the four and twentieth day of the sixth month, in the second year of Darius the king.

II

^1In the seventh month, in the one and twentieth day of the month, came the word of the Lord by the prophet Haggai, saying,

^2Speak now to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest, and to the residue of the people, saying,

^3Who is left among you that saw this house in her first glory? and how do ye see it now? is it not in your eyes in comparison of it as nothing?

^4Yet now be strong, O Zerubbabel, saith the Lord; and be strong, O Joshua, son of Josedech, the high priest; and be strong, all ye people of the land, saith the Lord, and work: for I am with you, saith the Lord of hosts:

^5According to the word that I covenanted with you when ye came out of Egypt, so my spirit remaineth among you: fear ye not.

^6For thus saith the Lord of hosts; Yet once, it is a little while, and I will shake the heavens, and the earth, and the sea, and the dry land;

^7And I will shake all nations, and the desire of all nations shall come: and I will fill this house with glory, saith the Lord of hosts.

^8The silver is mine, and the gold is mine, saith the Lord of hosts.

^9The glory of this latter house shall be greater than of the former, saith the Lord of hosts: and in this place will I give peace, saith the Lord of hosts.

^10In the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, in the second year of Darius, came the word of the Lord by Haggai the prophet, saying,

^11Thus saith the Lord of hosts; Ask now the priests concerning the law, saying,

^12If one bear holy flesh in the skirt of his garment, and with his skirt do touch bread, or pottage, or wine, or oil, or any meat, shall it be holy? And the priests answered and said, No.

^13Then said Haggai, If one that is unclean by a dead body touch any of these, shall it be unclean? And the priests answered and said, It shall be unclean.

^14Then answered Haggai, and said, So is this people, and so is this nation before me, saith the Lord; and so is every work of their hands; and that which they offer there is unclean.

^15And now, I pray you, consider from this day and upward, from before a stone was laid upon a stone in the temple of the Lord:

^16Since those days were, when one came to an heap of twenty measures, there were but ten: when one came to the pressfat for to draw out fifty vessels out of the press, there were but twenty.

^17I smote you with blasting and with mildew and with hail in all the labours of your hands; yet ye turned not to me, saith the Lord.

^18Consider now from this day and upward, from the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, even from the day that the foundation of the Lord’s temple was laid, consider it.

^19Is the seed yet in the barn? yea, as yet the vine, and the fig tree, and the pomegranate, and the olive tree, hath not brought forth: from this day will I bless you.

^20And again the word of the Lord came unto Haggai in the four and twentieth day of the month, saying,

^21Speak to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah, saying, I will shake the heavens and the earth;

^22And I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms, and I will destroy the strength of the kingdoms of the heathen; and I will overthrow the chariots, and those that ride in them; and the horses and their riders shall come down, every one by the sword of his brother.

^23In that day, saith the Lord of hosts, will I take thee, O Zerubbabel, my servant, the son of Shealtiel, saith the Lord, and will make thee as a signet: for I have chosen thee, saith the Lord of hosts.

I Corinthians

The First Epistle of Paul the Apostle to the

Corinthians

I

^1Paul called to be an apostle of Jesus Christ through the will of God, and Sosthenes our brother,

^2Unto the church of God which is at Corinth, to them that are sanctified in Christ Jesus, called to be saints, with all that in every place call upon the name of Jesus Christ our Lord, both their’s and our’s:

^3Grace be unto you, and peace, from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ.

^4I thank my God always on your behalf, for the grace of God which is given you by Jesus Christ;

^5That in every thing ye are enriched by him, in all utterance, and in all knowledge;

^6Even as the testimony of Christ was confirmed in you:

^7So that ye come behind in no gift; waiting for the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ:

^8Who shall also confirm you unto the end, that ye may be blameless in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.

^9God is faithful, by whom ye were called unto the fellowship of his Son Jesus Christ our Lord.

^10Now I beseech you, brethren, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye all speak the same thing, and that there be no divisions among you; but that ye be perfectly joined together in the same mind and in the same judgment.

^11For it hath been declared unto me of you, my brethren, by them which are of the house of Chloe, that there are contentions among you.

^12Now this I say, that every one of you saith, I am of Paul; and I of Apollos; and I of Cephas; and I of Christ.

^13Is Christ divided? was Paul crucified for you? or were ye baptized in the name of Paul?

^14I thank God that I baptized none of you, but Crispus and Gaius;

^15Lest any should say that I had baptized in mine own name.

^16And I baptized also the household of Stephanas: besides, I know not whether I baptized any other.

^17For Christ sent me not to baptize, but to preach the gospel: not with wisdom of words, lest the cross of Christ should be made of none effect.

^18For the preaching of the cross is to them that perish foolishness; but unto us which are saved it is the power of God.

^19For it is written, I will destroy the wisdom of the wise, and will bring to nothing the understanding of the prudent.

^20Where is the wise? where is the scribe? where is the disputer of this world? hath not God made foolish the wisdom of this world?

^21For after that in the wisdom of God the world by wisdom knew not God, it pleased God by the foolishness of preaching to save them that believe.

^22For the Jews require a sign, and the Greeks seek after wisdom:

^23But we preach Christ crucified, unto the Jews a stumblingblock, and unto the Greeks foolishness;

^24But unto them which are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ the power of God, and the wisdom of God.

^25Because the foolishness of God is wiser than men; and the weakness of God is stronger than men.

^26For ye see your calling, brethren, how that not many wise men after the flesh, not many mighty, not many noble, are called:

^27But God hath chosen the foolish things of the world to confound the wise; and God hath chosen the weak things of the world to confound the things which are mighty;

^28And base things of the world, and things which are despised, hath God chosen, yea, and things which are not, to bring to nought things that are:

^29That no flesh should glory in his presence.

^30But of him are ye in Christ Jesus, who of God is made unto us wisdom, and righteousness, and sanctification, and redemption:

^31That, according as it is written, He that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.

II

^1And I, brethren, when I came to you, came not with excellency of speech or of wisdom, declaring unto you the testimony of God.

^2For I determined not to know any thing among you, save Jesus Christ, and him crucified.

^3And I was with you in weakness, and in fear, and in much trembling.

^4And my speech and my preaching was not with enticing words of man’s wisdom, but in demonstration of the Spirit and of power:

^5That your faith should not stand in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God.

^6Howbeit we speak wisdom among them that are perfect: yet not the wisdom of this world, nor of the princes of this world, that come to nought:

^7But we speak the wisdom of God in a mystery, even the hidden wisdom, which God ordained before the world unto our glory:

^8Which none of the princes of this world knew: for had they known it, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory.

^9But as it is written, Eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, neither have entered into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him.

^10But God hath revealed them unto us by his Spirit: for the Spirit searcheth all things, yea, the deep things of God.

^11For what man knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of man which is in him? even so the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God.

^12Now we have received, not the spirit of the world, but the spirit which is of God; that we might know the things that are freely given to us of God.

^13Which things also we speak, not in the words which man’s wisdom teacheth, but which the Holy Ghost teacheth; comparing spiritual things with spiritual.

^14But the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God: for they are foolishness unto him: neither can he know them, because they are spiritually discerned.

^15But he that is spiritual judgeth all things, yet he himself is judged of no man.

^16For who hath known the mind of the Lord, that he may instruct him? But we have the mind of Christ.

III

^1And I, brethren, could not speak unto you as unto spiritual, but as unto carnal, even as unto babes in Christ.

^2I have fed you with milk, and not with meat: for hitherto ye were not able to bear it, neither yet now are ye able.

^3For ye are yet carnal: for whereas there is among you envying, and strife, and divisions, are ye not carnal, and walk as men?

^4For while one saith, I am of Paul; and another, I am of Apollos; are ye not carnal?

^5Who then is Paul, and who is Apollos, but ministers by whom ye believed, even as the Lord gave to every man?

^6I have planted, Apollos watered; but God gave the increase.

^7So then neither is he that planteth any thing, neither he that watereth; but God that giveth the increase.

^8Now he that planteth and he that watereth are one: and every man shall receive his own reward according to his own labour.

^9For we are labourers together with God: ye are God’s husbandry, ye are God’s building.

^10According to the grace of God which is given unto me, as a wise masterbuilder, I have laid the foundation, and another buildeth thereon. But let every man take heed how he buildeth thereupon.

^11For other foundation can no man lay than that is laid, which is Jesus Christ.

^12Now if any man build upon this foundation gold, silver, precious stones, wood, hay, stubble;

^13Every man’s work shall be made manifest: for the day shall declare it, because it shall be revealed by fire; and the fire shall try every man’s work of what sort it is.

^14If any man’s work abide which he hath built thereupon, he shall receive a reward.

^15If any man’s work shall be burned, he shall suffer loss: but he himself shall be saved; yet so as by fire.

^16Know ye not that ye are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?

^17If any man defile the temple of God, him shall God destroy; for the temple of God is holy, which temple ye are.

^18Let no man deceive himself. If any man among you seemeth to be wise in this world, let him become a fool, that he may be wise.

^19For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God. For it is written, He taketh the wise in their own craftiness.

^20And again, The Lord knoweth the thoughts of the wise, that they are vain.

^21Therefore let no man glory in men. For all things are your’s;

^22Whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things present, or things to come; all are your’s;

^23And ye are Christ’s; and Christ is God’s.

IV

^1Let a man so account of us, as of the ministers of Christ, and stewards of the mysteries of God.

^2Moreover it is required in stewards, that a man be found faithful.

^3But with me it is a very small thing that I should be judged of you, or of man’s judgment: yea, I judge not mine own self.

^4For I know nothing by myself; yet am I not hereby justified: but he that judgeth me is the Lord.

^5Therefore judge nothing before the time, until the Lord come, who both will bring to light the hidden things of darkness, and will make manifest the counsels of the hearts: and then shall every man have praise of God.

^6And these things, brethren, I have in a figure transferred to myself and to Apollos for your sakes; that ye might learn in us not to think of men above that which is written, that no one of you be puffed up for one against another.

^7For who maketh thee to differ from another? and what hast thou that thou didst not receive? now if thou didst receive it, why dost thou glory, as if thou hadst not received it?

^8Now ye are full, now ye are rich, ye have reigned as kings without us: and I would to God ye did reign, that we also might reign with you.

^9For I think that God hath set forth us the apostles last, as it were appointed to death: for we are made a spectacle unto the world, and to angels, and to men.

^10We are fools for Christ’s sake, but ye are wise in Christ; we are weak, but ye are strong; ye are honourable, but we are despised.

^11Even unto this present hour we both hunger, and thirst, and are naked, and are buffeted, and have no certain dwellingplace;

^12And labour, working with our own hands: being reviled, we bless; being persecuted, we suffer it:

^13Being defamed, we intreat: we are made as the filth of the world, and are the offscouring of all things unto this day.

^14I write not these things to shame you, but as my beloved sons I warn you.

^15For though ye have ten thousand instructors in Christ, yet have ye not many fathers: for in Christ Jesus I have begotten you through the gospel.

^16Wherefore I beseech you, be ye followers of me.

^17For this cause have I sent unto you Timotheus, who is my beloved son, and faithful in the Lord, who shall bring you into remembrance of my ways which be in Christ, as I teach every where in every church.

^18Now some are puffed up, as though I would not come to you.

^19But I will come to you shortly, if the Lord will, and will know, not the speech of them which are puffed up, but the power.

^20For the kingdom of God is not in word, but in power.

^21What will ye? shall I come unto you with a rod, or in love, and in the spirit of meekness?

V

^1It is reported commonly that there is fornication among you, and such fornication as is not so much as named among the Gentiles, that one should have his father’s wife.

^2And ye are puffed up, and have not rather mourned, that he that hath done this deed might be taken away from among you.

^3For I verily, as absent in body, but present in spirit, have judged already, as though I were present, concerning him that hath so done this deed,

^4In the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, when ye are gathered together, and my spirit, with the power of our Lord Jesus Christ,

^5To deliver such an one unto Satan for the destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.

^6Your glorying is not good. Know ye not that a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump?

^7Purge out therefore the old leaven, that ye may be a new lump, as ye are unleavened. For even Christ our passover is sacrificed for us:

^8Therefore let us keep the feast, not with old leaven, neither with the leaven of malice and wickedness; but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth.

^9I wrote unto you in an epistle not to company with fornicators:

^10Yet not altogether with the fornicators of this world, or with the covetous, or extortioners, or with idolaters; for then must ye needs go out of the world.

^11But now I have written unto you not to keep company, if any man that is called a brother be a fornicator, or covetous, or an idolater, or a railer, or a drunkard, or an extortioner; with such an one no not to eat.

^12For what have I to do to judge them also that are without? do not ye judge them that are within?

^13But them that are without God judgeth. Therefore put away from among yourselves that wicked person.

VI

^1Dare any of you, having a matter against another, go to law before the unjust, and not before the saints?

^2Do ye not know that the saints shall judge the world? and if the world shall be judged by you, are ye unworthy to judge the smallest matters?

^3Know ye not that we shall judge angels? how much more things that pertain to this life?

^4If then ye have judgments of things pertaining to this life, set them to judge who are least esteemed in the church.

^5I speak to your shame. Is it so, that there is not a wise man among you? no, not one that shall be able to judge between his brethren?

^6But brother goeth to law with brother, and that before the unbelievers.

^7Now therefore there is utterly a fault among you, because ye go to law one with another. Why do ye not rather take wrong? why do ye not rather suffer yourselves to be defrauded?

^8Nay, ye do wrong, and defraud, and that your brethren.

^9Know ye not that the unrighteous shall not inherit the kingdom of God? Be not deceived: neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor abusers of themselves with mankind,

^10Nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners, shall inherit the kingdom of God.

^11And such were some of you: but ye are washed, but ye are sanctified, but ye are justified in the name of the Lord Jesus, and by the Spirit of our God.

^12All things are lawful unto me, but all things are not expedient: all things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under the power of any.

^13Meats for the belly, and the belly for meats: but God shall destroy both it and them. Now the body is not for fornication, but for the Lord; and the Lord for the body.

^14And God hath both raised up the Lord, and will also raise up us by his own power.

^15Know ye not that your bodies are the members of Christ? shall I then take the members of Christ, and make them the members of an harlot? God forbid.

^16What? know ye not that he which is joined to an harlot is one body? for two, saith he, shall be one flesh.

^17But he that is joined unto the Lord is one spirit.

^18Flee fornication. Every sin that a man doeth is without the body; but he that committeth fornication sinneth against his own body.

^19What? know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghost which is in you, which ye have of God, and ye are not your own?

^20For ye are bought with a price: therefore glorify God in your body, and in your spirit, which are God’s.

VII

^1Now concerning the things whereof ye wrote unto me: It is good for a man not to touch a woman.

^2Nevertheless, to avoid fornication, let every man have his own wife, and let every woman have her own husband.

^3Let the husband render unto the wife due benevolence: and likewise also the wife unto the husband.

^4The wife hath not power of her own body, but the husband: and likewise also the husband hath not power of his own body, but the wife.

^5Defraud ye not one the other, except it be with consent for a time, that ye may give yourselves to fasting and prayer; and come together again, that Satan tempt you not for your incontinency.

^6But I speak this by permission, and not of commandment.

^7For I would that all men were even as I myself. But every man hath his proper gift of God, one after this manner, and another after that.

^8I say therefore to the unmarried and widows, It is good for them if they abide even as I.

^9But if they cannot contain, let them marry: for it is better to marry than to burn.

^10And unto the married I command, yet not I, but the Lord, Let not the wife depart from her husband:

^11But and if she depart, let her remain unmarried or be reconciled to her husband: and let not the husband put away his wife.

^12But to the rest speak I, not the Lord: If any brother hath a wife that believeth not, and she be pleased to dwell with him, let him not put her away.

^13And the woman which hath an husband that believeth not, and if he be pleased to dwell with her, let her not leave him.

^14For the unbelieving husband is sanctified by the wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified by the husband: else were your children unclean; but now are they holy.

^15But if the unbelieving depart, let him depart. A brother or a sister is not under bondage in such cases: but God hath called us to peace.

^16For what knowest thou, O wife, whether thou shalt save thy husband? or how knowest thou, O man, whether thou shalt save thy wife?

^17But as God hath distributed to every man, as the Lord hath called every one, so let him walk. And so ordain I in all churches.

^18Is any man called being circumcised? let him not become uncircumcised. Is any called in uncircumcision? let him not be circumcised.

^19Circumcision is nothing, and uncircumcision is nothing, but the keeping of the commandments of God.

^20Let every man abide in the same calling wherein he was called.

^21Art thou called being a servant? care not for it: but if thou mayest be made free, use it rather.

^22For he that is called in the Lord, being a servant, is the Lord’s freeman: likewise also he that is called, being free, is Christ’s servant.

^23Ye are bought with a price; be not ye the servants of men.

^24Brethren, let every man, wherein he is called, therein abide with God.

^25Now concerning virgins I have no commandment of the Lord: yet I give my judgment, as one that hath obtained mercy of the Lord to be faithful.

^26I suppose therefore that this is good for the present distress, I say, that it is good for a man so to be.

^27Art thou bound unto a wife? seek not to be loosed. Art thou loosed from a wife? seek not a wife.

^28But and if thou marry, thou hast not sinned; and if a virgin marry, she hath not sinned. Nevertheless such shall have trouble in the flesh: but I spare you.

^29But this I say, brethren, the time is short: it remaineth, that both they that have wives be as though they had none;

^30And they that weep, as though they wept not; and they that rejoice, as though they rejoiced not; and they that buy, as though they possessed not;

^31And they that use this world, as not abusing it: for the fashion of this world passeth away.

^32But I would have you without carefulness. He that is unmarried careth for the things that belong to the Lord, how he may please the Lord:

^33But he that is married careth for the things that are of the world, how he may please his wife.

^34There is difference also between a wife and a virgin. The unmarried woman careth for the things of the Lord, that she may be holy both in body and in spirit: but she that is married careth for the things of the world, how she may please her husband.

^35And this I speak for your own profit; not that I may cast a snare upon you, but for that which is comely, and that ye may attend upon the Lord without distraction.

^36But if any man think that he behaveth himself uncomely toward his virgin, if she pass the flower of her age, and need so require, let him do what he will, he sinneth not: let them marry.

^37Nevertheless he that standeth stedfast in his heart, having no necessity, but hath power over his own will, and hath so decreed in his heart that he will keep his virgin, doeth well.

^38So then he that giveth her in marriage doeth well; but he that giveth her not in marriage doeth better.

^39The wife is bound by the law as long as her husband liveth; but if her husband be dead, she is at liberty to be married to whom she will; only in the Lord.

^40But she is happier if she so abide, after my judgment: and I think also that I have the Spirit of God.

VIII

^1Now as touching things offered unto idols, we know that we all have knowledge. Knowledge puffeth up, but charity edifieth.

^2And if any man think that he knoweth any thing, he knoweth nothing yet as he ought to know.

^3But if any man love God, the same is known of him.

^4As concerning therefore the eating of those things that are offered in sacrifice unto idols, we know that an idol is nothing in the world, and that there is none other God but one.

^5For though there be that are called gods, whether in heaven or in earth, (as there be gods many, and lords many,)

^6But to us there is but one God, the Father, of whom are all things, and we in him; and one Lord Jesus Christ, by whom are all things, and we by him.

^7Howbeit there is not in every man that knowledge: for some with conscience of the idol unto this hour eat it as a thing offered unto an idol; and their conscience being weak is defiled.

^8But meat commendeth us not to God: for neither, if we eat, are we the better; neither, if we eat not, are we the worse.

^9But take heed lest by any means this liberty of your’s become a stumblingblock to them that are weak.

^10For if any man see thee which hast knowledge sit at meat in the idol’s temple, shall not the conscience of him which is weak be emboldened to eat those things which are offered to idols;

^11And through thy knowledge shall the weak brother perish, for whom Christ died?

^12But when ye sin so against the brethren, and wound their weak conscience, ye sin against Christ.

^13Wherefore, if meat make my brother to offend, I will eat no flesh while the world standeth, lest I make my brother to offend.

IX

^1Am I not an apostle? am I not free? have I not seen Jesus Christ our Lord? are not ye my work in the Lord?

^2If I be not an apostle unto others, yet doubtless I am to you: for the seal of mine apostleship are ye in the Lord.

^3Mine answer to them that do examine me is this,

^4Have we not power to eat and to drink?

^5Have we not power to lead about a sister, a wife, as well as other apostles, and as the brethren of the Lord, and Cephas?

^6Or I only and Barnabas, have not we power to forbear working?

^7Who goeth a warfare any time at his own charges? who planteth a vineyard, and eateth not of the fruit thereof? or who feedeth a flock, and eateth not of the milk of the flock?

^8Say I these things as a man? or saith not the law the same also?

^9For it is written in the law of Moses, Thou shalt not muzzle the mouth of the ox that treadeth out the corn. Doth God take care for oxen?

^10Or saith he it altogether for our sakes? For our sakes, no doubt, this is written: that he that ploweth should plow in hope; and that he that thresheth in hope should be partaker of his hope.

^11If we have sown unto you spiritual things, is it a great thing if we shall reap your carnal things?

^12If others be partakers of this power over you, are not we rather? Nevertheless we have not used this power; but suffer all things, lest we should hinder the gospel of Christ.

^13Do ye not know that they which minister about holy things live of the things of the temple? and they which wait at the altar are partakers with the altar?

^14Even so hath the Lord ordained that they which preach the gospel should live of the gospel.

^15But I have used none of these things: neither have I written these things, that it should be so done unto me: for it were better for me to die, than that any man should make my glorying void.

^16For though I preach the gospel, I have nothing to glory of: for necessity is laid upon me; yea, woe is unto me, if I preach not the gospel!

^17For if I do this thing willingly, I have a reward: but if against my will, a dispensation of the gospel is committed unto me.

^18What is my reward then? Verily that, when I preach the gospel, I may make the gospel of Christ without charge, that I abuse not my power in the gospel.

^19For though I be free from all men, yet have I made myself servant unto all, that I might gain the more.

^20And unto the Jews I became as a Jew, that I might gain the Jews; to them that are under the law, as under the law, that I might gain them that are under the law;

^21To them that are without law, as without law, (being not without law to God, but under the law to Christ,) that I might gain them that are without law.

^22To the weak became I as weak, that I might gain the weak: I am made all things to all men, that I might by all means save some.

^23And this I do for the gospel’s sake, that I might be partaker thereof with you.

^24Know ye not that they which run in a race run all, but one receiveth the prize? So run, that ye may obtain.

^25And every man that striveth for the mastery is temperate in all things. Now they do it to obtain a corruptible crown; but we an incorruptible.

^26I therefore so run, not as uncertainly; so fight I, not as one that beateth the air:

^27But I keep under my body, and bring it into subjection: lest that by any means, when I have preached to others, I myself should be a castaway.

X

^1Moreover, brethren, I would not that ye should be ignorant, how that all our fathers were under the cloud, and all passed through the sea;

^2And were all baptized unto Moses in the cloud and in the sea;

^3And did all eat the same spiritual meat;

^4And did all drink the same spiritual drink: for they drank of that spiritual Rock that followed them: and that Rock was Christ.

^5But with many of them God was not well pleased: for they were overthrown in the wilderness.

^6Now these things were our examples, to the intent we should not lust after evil things, as they also lusted.

^7Neither be ye idolaters, as were some of them; as it is written, The people sat down to eat and drink, and rose up to play.

^8Neither let us commit fornication, as some of them committed, and fell in one day three and twenty thousand.

^9Neither let us tempt Christ, as some of them also tempted, and were destroyed of serpents.

^10Neither murmur ye, as some of them also murmured, and were destroyed of the destroyer.

^11Now all these things happened unto them for ensamples: and they are written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come.

^12Wherefore let him that thinketh he standeth take heed lest he fall.

^13There hath no temptation taken you but such as is common to man: but God is faithful, who will not suffer you to be tempted above that ye are able; but will with the temptation also make a way to escape, that ye may be able to bear it.

^14Wherefore, my dearly beloved, flee from idolatry.

^15I speak as to wise men; judge ye what I say.

^16The cup of blessing which we bless, is it not the communion of the blood of Christ? The bread which we break, is it not the communion of the body of Christ?

^17For we being many are one bread, and one body: for we are all partakers of that one bread.

^18Behold Israel after the flesh: are not they which eat of the sacrifices partakers of the altar?

^19What say I then? that the idol is any thing, or that which is offered in sacrifice to idols is any thing?

^20But I say, that the things which the Gentiles sacrifice, they sacrifice to devils, and not to God: and I would not that ye should have fellowship with devils.

^21Ye cannot drink the cup of the Lord, and the cup of devils: ye cannot be partakers of the Lord’s table, and of the table of devils.

^22Do we provoke the Lord to jealousy? are we stronger than he?

^23All things are lawful for me, but all things are not expedient: all things are lawful for me, but all things edify not.

^24Let no man seek his own, but every man another’s wealth.

^25Whatsoever is sold in the shambles, that eat, asking no question for conscience sake:

^26For the earth is the Lord’s, and the fulness thereof.

^27If any of them that believe not bid you to a feast, and ye be disposed to go; whatsoever is set before you, eat, asking no question for conscience sake.

^28But if any man say unto you, This is offered in sacrifice unto idols, eat not for his sake that shewed it, and for conscience sake: for the earth is the Lord’s, and the fulness thereof:

^29Conscience, I say, not thine own, but of the other: for why is my liberty judged of another man’s conscience?

^30For if I by grace be a partaker, why am I evil spoken of for that for which I give thanks?

^31Whether therefore ye eat, or drink, or whatsoever ye do, do all to the glory of God.

^32Give none offence, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the church of God:

^33Even as I please all men in all things, not seeking mine own profit, but the profit of many, that they may be saved.

XI

^1Be ye followers of me, even as I also am of Christ.

^2Now I praise you, brethren, that ye remember me in all things, and keep the ordinances, as I delivered them to you.

^3But I would have you know, that the head of every man is Christ; and the head of the woman is the man; and the head of Christ is God.

^4Every man praying or prophesying, having his head covered, dishonoureth his head.

^5But every woman that prayeth or prophesieth with her head uncovered dishonoureth her head: for that is even all one as if she were shaven.

^6For if the woman be not covered, let her also be shorn: but if it be a shame for a woman to be shorn or shaven, let her be covered.

^7For a man indeed ought not to cover his head, forasmuch as he is the image and glory of God: but the woman is the glory of the man.

^8For the man is not of the woman: but the woman of the man.

^9Neither was the man created for the woman; but the woman for the man.

^10For this cause ought the woman to have power on her head because of the angels.

^11Nevertheless neither is the man without the woman, neither the woman without the man, in the Lord.

^12For as the woman is of the man, even so is the man also by the woman; but all things of God.

^13Judge in yourselves: is it comely that a woman pray unto God uncovered?

^14Doth not even nature itself teach you, that, if a man have long hair, it is a shame unto him?

^15But if a woman have long hair, it is a glory to her: for her hair is given her for a covering.

^16But if any man seem to be contentious, we have no such custom, neither the churches of God.

^17Now in this that I declare unto you I praise you not, that ye come together not for the better, but for the worse.

^18For first of all, when ye come together in the church, I hear that there be divisions among you; and I partly believe it.

^19For there must be also heresies among you, that they which are approved may be made manifest among you.

^20When ye come together therefore into one place, this is not to eat the Lord’s supper.

^21For in eating every one taketh before other his own supper: and one is hungry, and another is drunken.

^22What? have ye not houses to eat and to drink in? or despise ye the church of God, and shame them that have not? What shall I say to you? shall I praise you in this? I praise you not.

^23For I have received of the Lord that which also I delivered unto you, That the Lord Jesus the same night in which he was betrayed took bread:

^24And when he had given thanks, he brake it, and said, Take, eat: this is my body, which is broken for you: this do in remembrance of me.

^25After the same manner also he took the cup, when he had supped, saying, This cup is the new testament in my blood: this do ye, as oft as ye drink it, in remembrance of me.

^26For as often as ye eat this bread, and drink this cup, ye do shew the Lord’s death till he come.

^27Wherefore whosoever shall eat this bread, and drink this cup of the Lord, unworthily, shall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord.

^28But let a man examine himself, and so let him eat of that bread, and drink of that cup.

^29For he that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation to himself, not discerning the Lord’s body.

^30For this cause many are weak and sickly among you, and many sleep.

^31For if we would judge ourselves, we should not be judged.

^32But when we are judged, we are chastened of the Lord, that we should not be condemned with the world.

^33Wherefore, my brethren, when ye come together to eat, tarry one for another.

^34And if any man hunger, let him eat at home; that ye come not together unto condemnation. And the rest will I set in order when I come.

XII

^1Now concerning spiritual gifts, brethren, I would not have you ignorant.

^2Ye know that ye were Gentiles, carried away unto these dumb idols, even as ye were led.

^3Wherefore I give you to understand, that no man speaking by the Spirit of God calleth Jesus accursed: and that no man can say that Jesus is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghost.

^4Now there are diversities of gifts, but the same Spirit.

^5And there are differences of administrations, but the same Lord.

^6And there are diversities of operations, but it is the same God which worketh all in all.

^7But the manifestation of the Spirit is given to every man to profit withal.

^8For to one is given by the Spirit the word of wisdom; to another the word of knowledge by the same Spirit;

^9To another faith by the same Spirit; to another the gifts of healing by the same Spirit;

^10To another the working of miracles; to another prophecy; to another discerning of spirits; to another divers kinds of tongues; to another the interpretation of tongues:

^11But all these worketh that one and the selfsame Spirit, dividing to every man severally as he will.

^12For as the body is one, and hath many members, and all the members of that one body, being many, are one body: so also is Christ.

^13For by one Spirit are we all baptized into one body, whether we be Jews or Gentiles, whether we be bond or free; and have been all made to drink into one Spirit.

^14For the body is not one member, but many.

^15If the foot shall say, Because I am not the hand, I am not of the body; is it therefore not of the body?

^16And if the ear shall say, Because I am not the eye, I am not of the body; is it therefore not of the body?

^17If the whole body were an eye, where were the hearing? If the whole were hearing, where were the smelling?

^18But now hath God set the members every one of them in the body, as it hath pleased him.

^19And if they were all one member, where were the body?

^20But now are they many members, yet but one body.

^21And the eye cannot say unto the hand, I have no need of thee: nor again the head to the feet, I have no need of you.

^22Nay, much more those members of the body, which seem to be more feeble, are necessary:

^23And those members of the body, which we think to be less honourable, upon these we bestow more abundant honour; and our uncomely parts have more abundant comeliness.

^24For our comely parts have no need: but God hath tempered the body together, having given more abundant honour to that part which lacked.

^25That there should be no schism in the body; but that the members should have the same care one for another.

^26And whether one member suffer, all the members suffer with it; or one member be honoured, all the members rejoice with it.

^27Now ye are the body of Christ, and members in particular.

^28And God hath set some in the church, first apostles, secondarily prophets, thirdly teachers, after that miracles, then gifts of healings, helps, governments, diversities of tongues.

^29Are all apostles? are all prophets? are all teachers? are all workers of miracles?

^30Have all the gifts of healing? do all speak with tongues? do all interpret?

^31But covet earnestly the best gifts: and yet shew I unto you a more excellent way.

XIII

^1Though I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, and have not charity, I am become as sounding brass, or a tinkling cymbal.

^2And though I have the gift of prophecy, and understand all mysteries, and all knowledge; and though I have all faith, so that I could remove mountains, and have not charity, I am nothing.

^3And though I bestow all my goods to feed the poor, and though I give my body to be burned, and have not charity, it profiteth me nothing.

^4Charity suffereth long, and is kind; charity envieth not; charity vaunteth not itself, is not puffed up,

^5Doth not behave itself unseemly, seeketh not her own, is not easily provoked, thinketh no evil;

^6Rejoiceth not in iniquity, but rejoiceth in the truth;

^7Beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things.

^8Charity never faileth: but whether there be prophecies, they shall fail; whether there be tongues, they shall cease; whether there be knowledge, it shall vanish away.

^9For we know in part, and we prophesy in part.

^10But when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part shall be done away.

^11When I was a child, I spake as a child, I understood as a child, I thought as a child: but when I became a man, I put away childish things.

^12For now we see through a glass, darkly; but then face to face: now I know in part; but then shall I know even as also I am known.

^13And now abideth faith, hope, charity, these three; but the greatest of these is charity.

XIV

^1Follow after charity, and desire spiritual gifts, but rather that ye may prophesy.

^2For he that speaketh in an unknown tongue speaketh not unto men, but unto God: for no man understandeth him; howbeit in the spirit he speaketh mysteries.

^3But he that prophesieth speaketh unto men to edification, and exhortation, and comfort.

^4He that speaketh in an unknown tongue edifieth himself; but he that prophesieth edifieth the church.

^5I would that ye all spake with tongues but rather that ye prophesied: for greater is he that prophesieth than he that speaketh with tongues, except he interpret, that the church may receive edifying.

^6Now, brethren, if I come unto you speaking with tongues, what shall I profit you, except I shall speak to you either by revelation, or by knowledge, or by prophesying, or by doctrine?

^7And even things without life giving sound, whether pipe or harp, except they give a distinction in the sounds, how shall it be known what is piped or harped?

^8For if the trumpet give an uncertain sound, who shall prepare himself to the battle?

^9So likewise ye, except ye utter by the tongue words easy to be understood, how shall it be known what is spoken? for ye shall speak into the air.

^10There are, it may be, so many kinds of voices in the world, and none of them is without signification.

^11Therefore if I know not the meaning of the voice, I shall be unto him that speaketh a barbarian, and he that speaketh shall be a barbarian unto me.

^12Even so ye, forasmuch as ye are zealous of spiritual gifts, seek that ye may excel to the edifying of the church.

^13Wherefore let him that speaketh in an unknown tongue pray that he may interpret.

^14For if I pray in an unknown tongue, my spirit prayeth, but my understanding is unfruitful.

^15What is it then? I will pray with the spirit, and I will pray with the understanding also: I will sing with the spirit, and I will sing with the understanding also.

^16Else when thou shalt bless with the spirit, how shall he that occupieth the room of the unlearned say Amen at thy giving of thanks, seeing he understandeth not what thou sayest?

^17For thou verily givest thanks well, but the other is not edified.

^18I thank my God, I speak with tongues more than ye all:

^19Yet in the church I had rather speak five words with my understanding, that by my voice I might teach others also, than ten thousand words in an unknown tongue.

^20Brethren, be not children in understanding: howbeit in malice be ye children, but in understanding be men.

^21In the law it is written, With men of other tongues and other lips will I speak unto this people; and yet for all that will they not hear me, saith the Lord.

^22Wherefore tongues are for a sign, not to them that believe, but to them that believe not: but prophesying serveth not for them that believe not, but for them which believe.

^23If therefore the whole church be come together into one place, and all speak with tongues, and there come in those that are unlearned, or unbelievers, will they not say that ye are mad?

^24But if all prophesy, and there come in one that believeth not, or one unlearned, he is convinced of all, he is judged of all:

^25And thus are the secrets of his heart made manifest; and so falling down on his face he will worship God, and report that God is in you of a truth.

^26How is it then, brethren? when ye come together, every one of you hath a psalm, hath a doctrine, hath a tongue, hath a revelation, hath an interpretation. Let all things be done unto edifying.

^27If any man speak in an unknown tongue, let it be by two, or at the most by three, and that by course; and let one interpret.

^28But if there be no interpreter, let him keep silence in the church; and let him speak to himself, and to God.

^29Let the prophets speak two or three, and let the other judge.

^30If any thing be revealed to another that sitteth by, let the first hold his peace.

^31For ye may all prophesy one by one, that all may learn, and all may be comforted.

^32And the spirits of the prophets are subject to the prophets.

^33For God is not the author of confusion, but of peace, as in all churches of the saints.

^34Let your women keep silence in the churches: for it is not permitted unto them to speak; but they are commanded to be under obedience as also saith the law.

^35And if they will learn any thing, let them ask their husbands at home: for it is a shame for women to speak in the church.

^36What? came the word of God out from you? or came it unto you only?

^37If any man think himself to be a prophet, or spiritual, let him acknowledge that the things that I write unto you are the commandments of the Lord.

^38But if any man be ignorant, let him be ignorant.

^39Wherefore, brethren, covet to prophesy, and forbid not to speak with tongues.

^40Let all things be done decently and in order.

XV

^1Moreover, brethren, I declare unto you the gospel which I preached unto you, which also ye have received, and wherein ye stand;

^2By which also ye are saved, if ye keep in memory what I preached unto you, unless ye have believed in vain.

^3For I delivered unto you first of all that which I also received, how that Christ died for our sins according to the scriptures;

^4And that he was buried, and that he rose again the third day according to the scriptures:

^5And that he was seen of Cephas, then of the twelve:

^6After that, he was seen of above five hundred brethren at once; of whom the greater part remain unto this present, but some are fallen asleep.

^7After that, he was seen of James; then of all the apostles.

^8And last of all he was seen of me also, as of one born out of due time.

^9For I am the least of the apostles, that am not meet to be called an apostle, because I persecuted the church of God.

^10But by the grace of God I am what I am: and his grace which was bestowed upon me was not in vain; but I laboured more abundantly than they all: yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me.

^11Therefore whether it were I or they, so we preach, and so ye believed.

^12Now if Christ be preached that he rose from the dead, how say some among you that there is no resurrection of the dead?

^13But if there be no resurrection of the dead, then is Christ not risen:

^14And if Christ be not risen, then is our preaching vain, and your faith is also vain.

^15Yea, and we are found false witnesses of God; because we have testified of God that he raised up Christ: whom he raised not up, if so be that the dead rise not.

^16For if the dead rise not, then is not Christ raised:

^17And if Christ be not raised, your faith is vain; ye are yet in your sins.

^18Then they also which are fallen asleep in Christ are perished.

^19If in this life only we have hope in Christ, we are of all men most miserable.

^20But now is Christ risen from the dead, and become the firstfruits of them that slept.

^21For since by man came death, by man came also the resurrection of the dead.

^22For as in Adam all die, even so in Christ shall all be made alive.

^23But every man in his own order: Christ the firstfruits; afterward they that are Christ’s at his coming.

^24Then cometh the end, when he shall have delivered up the kingdom to God, even the Father; when he shall have put down all rule and all authority and power.

^25For he must reign, till he hath put all enemies under his feet.

^26The last enemy that shall be destroyed is death.

^27For he hath put all things under his feet. But when he saith all things are put under him, it is manifest that he is excepted, which did put all things under him.

^28And when all things shall be subdued unto him, then shall the Son also himself be subject unto him that put all things under him, that God may be all in all.

^29Else what shall they do which are baptized for the dead, if the dead rise not at all? why are they then baptized for the dead?

^30And why stand we in jeopardy every hour?

^31I protest by your rejoicing which I have in Christ Jesus our Lord, I die daily.

^32If after the manner of men I have fought with beasts at Ephesus, what advantageth it me, if the dead rise not? let us eat and drink; for to morrow we die.

^33Be not deceived: evil communications corrupt good manners.

^34Awake to righteousness, and sin not; for some have not the knowledge of God: I speak this to your shame.

^35But some man will say, How are the dead raised up? and with what body do they come?

^36Thou fool, that which thou sowest is not quickened, except it die:

^37And that which thou sowest, thou sowest not that body that shall be, but bare grain, it may chance of wheat, or of some other grain:

^38But God giveth it a body as it hath pleased him, and to every seed his own body.

^39All flesh is not the same flesh: but there is one kind of flesh of men, another flesh of beasts, another of fishes, and another of birds.

^40There are also celestial bodies, and bodies terrestrial: but the glory of the celestial is one, and the glory of the terrestrial is another.

^41There is one glory of the sun, and another glory of the moon, and another glory of the stars: for one star differeth from another star in glory.

^42So also is the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in corruption; it is raised in incorruption:

^43It is sown in dishonour; it is raised in glory: it is sown in weakness; it is raised in power:

^44It is sown a natural body; it is raised a spiritual body. There is a natural body, and there is a spiritual body.

^45And so it is written, The first man Adam was made a living soul; the last Adam was made a quickening spirit.

^46Howbeit that was not first which is spiritual, but that which is natural; and afterward that which is spiritual.

^47The first man is of the earth, earthy; the second man is the Lord from heaven.

^48As is the earthy, such are they also that are earthy: and as is the heavenly, such are they also that are heavenly.

^49And as we have borne the image of the earthy, we shall also bear the image of the heavenly.

^50Now this I say, brethren, that flesh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom of God; neither doth corruption inherit incorruption.

^51Behold, I shew you a mystery; We shall not all sleep, but we shall all be changed,

^52In a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trump: for the trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised incorruptible, and we shall be changed.

^53For this corruptible must put on incorruption, and this mortal must put on immortality.

^54So when this corruptible shall have put on incorruption, and this mortal shall have put on immortality, then shall be brought to pass the saying that is written, Death is swallowed up in victory.

^55O death, where is thy sting? O grave, where is thy victory?

^56The sting of death is sin; and the strength of sin is the law.

^57But thanks be to God, which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.

^58Therefore, my beloved brethren, be ye stedfast, unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, forasmuch as ye know that your labour is not in vain in the Lord.

XVI

^1Now concerning the collection for the saints, as I have given order to the churches of Galatia, even so do ye.

^2Upon the first day of the week let every one of you lay by him in store, as God hath prospered him, that there be no gatherings when I come.

^3And when I come, whomsoever ye shall approve by your letters, them will I send to bring your liberality unto Jerusalem.

^4And if it be meet that I go also, they shall go with me.

^5Now I will come unto you, when I shall pass through Macedonia: for I do pass through Macedonia.

^6And it may be that I will abide, yea, and winter with you, that ye may bring me on my journey whithersoever I go.

^7For I will not see you now by the way; but I trust to tarry a while with you, if the Lord permit.

^8But I will tarry at Ephesus until Pentecost.

^9For a great door and effectual is opened unto me, and there are many adversaries.

^10Now if Timotheus come, see that he may be with you without fear: for he worketh the work of the Lord, as I also do.

^11Let no man therefore despise him: but conduct him forth in peace, that he may come unto me: for I look for him with the brethren.

^12As touching our brother Apollos, I greatly desired him to come unto you with the brethren: but his will was not at all to come at this time; but he will come when he shall have convenient time.

^13Watch ye, stand fast in the faith, quit you like men, be strong.

^14Let all your things be done with charity.

^15I beseech you, brethren, (ye know the house of Stephanas, that it is the firstfruits of Achaia, and that they have addicted themselves to the ministry of the saints,)

^16That ye submit yourselves unto such, and to every one that helpeth with us, and laboureth.

^17I am glad of the coming of Stephanas and Fortunatus and Achaicus: for that which was lacking on your part they have supplied.

^18For they have refreshed my spirit and your’s: therefore acknowledge ye them that are such.

^19The churches of Asia salute you. Aquila and Priscilla salute you much in the Lord, with the church that is in their house.

^20All the brethren greet you. Greet ye one another with an holy kiss.

^21The salutation of me Paul with mine own hand.

^22If any man love not the Lord Jesus Christ, let him be Anathema Maranatha.

^23The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.

^24My love be with you all in Christ Jesus. Amen.

Ephesians

The Epistle of Paul the Apostle to the

Ephesians

I

^1Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, to the saints which are at Ephesus, and to the faithful in Christ Jesus: ^2grace be to you, and peace, from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ.

^3Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who hath blessed us with all spiritual blessings in heavenly places in Christ: ^4according as he hath chosen us in him before the foundation of the world, that we should be holy and without blame before him in love: ^5having predestinated us unto the adoption of children by Jesus Christ to himself, according to the good pleasure of his will, ^6to the praise of the glory of his grace, wherein he hath made us accepted in the beloved. ^7In whom we have redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of sins, according to the riches of his grace; ^8wherein he hath abounded toward us in all wisdom and prudence; ^9having made known unto us the mystery of his will, according to his good pleasure which he hath purposed in himself: ^10that in the dispensation of the fulness of times he might gather together in one all things in Christ, both which are in heaven, and which are on earth; even in him: ^11in whom also we have obtained an inheritance, being predestinated according to the purpose of him who worketh all things after the counsel of his own will: ^12that we should be to the praise of his glory, who first trusted in Christ. ^13In whom ye also trusted, after that ye heard the word of truth, the gospel of your salvation: in whom also after that ye believed, ye were sealed with that holy Spirit of promise, ^14which is the earnest of our inheritance until the redemption of the purchased possession, unto the praise of his glory.

^15Wherefore I also, after I heard of your faith in the Lord Jesus, and love unto all the saints, ^16cease not to give thanks for you, making mention of you in my prayers; ^17that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, may give unto you the spirit of wisdom and revelation in the knowledge of him: ^18the eyes of your understanding being enlightened; that ye may know what is the hope of his calling, and what the riches of the glory of his inheritance in the saints, ^19and what is the exceeding greatness of his power to us-ward who believe, according to the working of his mighty power, ^20which he wrought in Christ, when he raised him from the dead, and set him at his own right hand in the heavenly places, ^21far above all principality, and power, and might, and dominion, and every name that is named, not only in this world, but also in that which is to come: ^22and hath put all things under his feet, and gave him to be the head over all things to the church, ^23which is his body, the fulness of him that filleth all in all.

II

^1And you hath he quickened, who were dead in trespasses and sins; ^2wherein in time past ye walked according to the course of this world, according to the prince of the power of the air, the spirit that now worketh in the children of disobedience: ^3among whom also we all had our conversation in times past in the lusts of our flesh, fulfilling the desires of the flesh and of the mind; and were by nature the children of wrath, even as others. ^4But God, who is rich in mercy, for his great love wherewith he loved us, ^5even when we were dead in sins, hath quickened us together with Christ, (by grace ye are saved;) ^6and hath raised us up together, and made us sit together in heavenly places in Christ Jesus: ^7that in the ages to come he might shew the exceeding riches of his grace in his kindness toward us through Christ Jesus. ^8For by grace are ye saved through faith; and that not of yourselves: it is the gift of God: ^9not of works, lest any man should boast. ^10For we are his workmanship, created in Christ Jesus unto good works, which God hath before ordained that we should walk in them.

^11Wherefore remember, that ye being in time past Gentiles in the flesh, who are called Uncircumcision by that which is called the Circumcision in the flesh made by hands; ^12that at that time ye were without Christ, being aliens from the commonwealth of Israel, and strangers from the covenants of promise, having no hope, and without God in the world: ^13but now in Christ Jesus ye who sometimes were far off are made nigh by the blood of Christ. ^14For he is our peace, who hath made both one, and hath broken down the middle wall of partition between us; ^15having abolished in his flesh the enmity, even the law of commandments contained in ordinances; for to make in himself of twain one new man, so making peace; ^16and that he might reconcile both unto God in one body by the cross, having slain the enmity thereby: ^17and came and preached peace to you which were afar off, and to them that were nigh. ^18For through him we both have access by one Spirit unto the Father. ^19Now therefore ye are no more strangers and foreigners, but fellowcitizens with the saints, and of the household of God; ^20and are built upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Jesus Christ himself being the chief corner stone; ^21in whom all the building fitly framed together groweth unto an holy temple in the Lord: ^22in whom ye also are builded together for an habitation of God through the Spirit.

III

^1For this cause I Paul, the prisoner of Jesus Christ for you Gentiles, ^2if ye have heard of the dispensation of the grace of God which is given me to you-ward: ^3how that by revelation he made known unto me the mystery; (as I wrote afore in few words, ^4whereby, when ye read, ye may understand my knowledge in the mystery of Christ) ^5which in other ages was not made known unto the sons of men, as it is now revealed unto his holy apostles and prophets by the Spirit; ^6that the Gentiles should be fellowheirs, and of the same body, and partakers of his promise in Christ by the gospel: ^7whereof I was made a minister, according to the gift of the grace of God given unto me by the effectual working of his power. ^8Unto me, who am less than the least of all saints, is this grace given, that I should preach among the Gentiles the unsearchable riches of Christ; ^9and to make all men see what is the fellowship of the mystery, which from the beginning of the world hath been hid in God, who created all things by Jesus Christ: ^10to the intent that now unto the principalities and powers in heavenly places might be known by the church the manifold wisdom of God, ^11according to the eternal purpose which he purposed in Christ Jesus our Lord: ^12in whom we have boldness and access with confidence by the faith of him. ^13Wherefore I desire that ye faint not at my tribulations for you, which is your glory.

^14For this cause I bow my knees unto the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, ^15of whom the whole family in heaven and earth is named, ^16that he would grant you, according to the riches of his glory, to be strengthened with might by his Spirit in the inner man; ^17that Christ may dwell in your hearts by faith; that ye, being rooted and grounded in love, ^18may be able to comprehend with all saints what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and height; ^19and to know the love of Christ, which passeth knowledge, that ye might be filled with all the fulness of God. ^20Now unto him that is able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think, according to the power that worketh in us, ^21unto him be glory in the church by Christ Jesus throughout all ages, world without end. Amen.

IV

^1I therefore, the prisoner of the Lord, beseech you that ye walk worthy of the vocation wherewith ye are called, ^2with all lowliness and meekness, with longsuffering, forbearing one another in love; ^3endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. ^4There is one body, and one Spirit, even as ye are called in one hope of your calling; ^5one Lord, one faith, one baptism, ^6one God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all. ^7But unto every one of us is given grace according to the measure of the gift of Christ. ^8Wherefore he saith,

When he ascended up on high, he led captivity captive,
And gave gifts unto men.

^9(Now that he ascended, what is it but that he also descended first into the lower parts of the earth? ^10He that descended is the same also that ascended up far above all heavens, that he might fill all things.) ^11And he gave some, apostles; and some, prophets; and some, evangelists; and some, pastors and teachers; ^12for the perfecting of the saints, for the work of the ministry, for the edifying of the body of Christ: ^13till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the measure of the stature of the fulness of Christ: ^14that we henceforth be no more children, tossed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine, by the sleight of men, and cunning craftiness, whereby they lie in wait to deceive; ^15but speaking the truth in love, may grow up into him in all things, which is the head, even Christ: ^16from whom the whole body fitly joined together and compacted by that which every joint supplieth, according to the effectual working in the measure of every part, maketh increase of the body unto the edifying of itself in love.

^17This I say therefore, and testify in the Lord, that ye henceforth walk not as other Gentiles walk, in the vanity of their mind, ^18having the understanding darkened, being alienated from the life of God through the ignorance that is in them, because of the blindness of their heart: ^19who being past feeling have given themselves over unto lasciviousness, to work all uncleanness with greediness. ^20But ye have not so learned Christ; ^21if so be that ye have heard him, and have been taught by him, as the truth is in Jesus: ^22that ye put off concerning the former conversation the old man, which is corrupt according to the deceitful lusts; ^23and be renewed in the spirit of your mind; ^24and that ye put on the new man, which after God is created in righteousness and true holiness.

^25Wherefore putting away lying, speak every man truth with his neighbour: for we are members one of another. ^26Be ye angry, and sin not: let not the sun go down upon your wrath: ^27neither give place to the devil. ^28Let him that stole steal no more: but rather let him labour, working with his hands the thing which is good, that he may have to give to him that needeth. ^29Let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouth, but that which is good to the use of edifying, that it may minister grace unto the hearers. ^30And grieve not the holy Spirit of God, whereby ye are sealed unto the day of redemption. ^31Let all bitterness, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evil speaking, be put away from you, with all malice: ^32and be ye kind one to another, tenderhearted, forgiving one another, even as God for Christ’s sake hath forgiven you.

V

^1Be ye therefore followers of God, as dear children; ^2and walk in love, as Christ also hath loved us, and hath given himself for us an offering and a sacrifice to God for a sweetsmelling savour.

^3But fornication, and all uncleanness, or covetousness, let it not be once named among you, as becometh saints; ^4neither filthiness, nor foolish talking, nor jesting, which are not convenient: but rather giving of thanks. ^5For this ye know, that no whoremonger, nor unclean person, nor covetous man, who is an idolater, hath any inheritance in the kingdom of Christ and of God.

^6Let no man deceive you with vain words: for because of these things cometh the wrath of God upon the children of disobedience. ^7Be not ye therefore partakers with them. ^8For ye were sometimes darkness, but now are ye light in the Lord: walk as children of light: ^9(for the fruit of the Spirit is in all goodness and righteousness and truth;) ^10proving what is acceptable unto the Lord. ^11And have no fellowship with the unfruitful works of darkness, but rather reprove them. ^12For it is a shame even to speak of those things which are done of them in secret. ^13But all things that are reproved are made manifest by the light: for whatsoever doth make manifest is light. ^14Wherefore he saith, Awake thou that sleepest, and arise from the dead, and Christ shall give thee light.

^15See then that ye walk circumspectly, not as fools, but as wise, ^16redeeming the time, because the days are evil. ^17Wherefore be ye not unwise, but understanding what the will of the Lord is. ^18And be not drunk with wine, wherein is excess; but be filled with the Spirit; ^19speaking to yourselves in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing and making melody in your heart to the Lord; ^20giving thanks always for all things unto God and the Father in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ; ^21submitting yourselves one to another in the fear of God.

^22Wives, submit yourselves unto your own husbands, as unto the Lord. ^23For the husband is the head of the wife, even as Christ is the head of the church: and he is the saviour of the body. ^24Therefore as the church is subject unto Christ, so let the wives be to their own husbands in every thing. ^25Husbands, love your wives, even as Christ also loved the church, and gave himself for it; ^26that he might sanctify and cleanse it with the washing of water by the word, ^27that he might present it to himself a glorious church, not having spot, or wrinkle, or any such thing; but that it should be holy and without blemish. ^28So ought men to love their wives as their own bodies. He that loveth his wife loveth himself. ^29For no man ever yet hated his own flesh; but nourisheth and cherisheth it, even as the Lord the church: ^30for we are members of his body, of his flesh, and of his bones. ^31For this cause shall a man leave his father and mother, and shall be joined unto his wife, and they two shall be one flesh. ^32This is a great mystery: but I speak concerning Christ and the church. ^33Nevertheless let every one of you in particular so love his wife even as himself; and the wife see that she reverence her husband.

VI

^1Children, obey your parents in the Lord: for this is right. ^2Honour thy father and mother; which is the first commandment with promise; ^3that it may be well with thee, and thou mayest live long on the earth. ^4And, ye fathers, provoke not your children to wrath: but bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord.

^5Servants, be obedient to them that are your masters according to the flesh, with fear and trembling, in singleness of your heart, as unto Christ; ^6not with eyeservice, as menpleasers; but as the servants of Christ, doing the will of God from the heart; ^7with good will doing service, as to the Lord, and not to men: ^8knowing that whatsoever good thing any man doeth, the same shall he receive of the Lord, whether he be bond or free. ^9And, ye masters, do the same things unto them, forbearing threatening: knowing that your Master also is in heaven; neither is there respect of persons with him.

^10Finally, my brethren, be strong in the Lord, and in the power of his might. ^11Put on the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to stand against the wiles of the devil. ^12For we wrestle not against flesh and blood, but against principalities, against powers, against the rulers of the darkness of this world, against spiritual wickedness in high places. ^13Wherefore take unto you the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to withstand in the evil day, and having done all, to stand. ^14Stand therefore, having your loins girt about with truth, and having on the breastplate of righteousness; ^15and your feet shod with the preparation of the gospel of peace; ^16above all, taking the shield of faith, wherewith ye shall be able to quench all the fiery darts of the wicked. ^17And take the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God: ^18praying always with all prayer and supplication in the Spirit, and watching thereunto with all perseverance and supplication for all saints; ^19and for me, that utterance may be given unto me, that I may open my mouth boldly, to make known the mystery of the gospel, ^20for which I am an ambassador in bonds: that therein I may speak boldly, as I ought to speak.

^21But that ye also may know my affairs, and how I do, Tychicus, a beloved brother and faithful minister in the Lord, shall make known to you all things: ^22whom I have sent unto you for the same purpose, that ye might know our affairs, and that he might comfort your hearts.

^23Peace be to the brethren, and love with faith, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. ^24Grace be with all them that love our Lord Jesus Christ in sincerity. Amen.

I Thessalonians

The First Epistle of Paul the Apostle to the

Thessalonians

I

^1Paul, and Silvanus, and Timotheus, unto the church of the Thessalonians which is in God the Father and in the Lord Jesus Christ: Grace be unto you, and peace, from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ.

^2We give thanks to God always for you all, making mention of you in our prayers;

^3Remembering without ceasing your work of faith, and labour of love, and patience of hope in our Lord Jesus Christ, in the sight of God and our Father;

^4Knowing, brethren beloved, your election of God.

^5For our gospel came not unto you in word only, but also in power, and in the Holy Ghost, and in much assurance; as ye know what manner of men we were among you for your sake.

^6And ye became followers of us, and of the Lord, having received the word in much affliction, with joy of the Holy Ghost.

^7So that ye were ensamples to all that believe in Macedonia and Achaia.

^8For from you sounded out the word of the Lord not only in Macedonia and Achaia, but also in every place your faith to God-ward is spread abroad; so that we need not to speak any thing.

^9For they themselves shew of us what manner of entering in we had unto you, and how ye turned to God from idols to serve the living and true God;

^10And to wait for his Son from heaven, whom he raised from the dead, even Jesus, which delivered us from the wrath to come.

II

^1For yourselves, brethren, know our entrance in unto you, that it was not in vain:

^2But even after that we had suffered before, and were shamefully entreated, as ye know, at Philippi, we were bold in our God to speak unto you the gospel of God with much contention.

^3For our exhortation was not of deceit, nor of uncleanness, nor in guile:

^4But as we were allowed of God to be put in trust with the gospel, even so we speak; not as pleasing men, but God, which trieth our hearts.

^5For neither at any time used we flattering words, as ye know, nor a cloke of covetousness; God is witness:

^6Nor of men sought we glory, neither of you, nor yet of others, when we might have been burdensome, as the apostles of Christ.

^7But we were gentle among you, even as a nurse cherisheth her children:

^8So being affectionately desirous of you, we were willing to have imparted unto you, not the gospel of God only, but also our own souls, because ye were dear unto us.

^9For ye remember, brethren, our labour and travail: for labouring night and day, because we would not be chargeable unto any of you, we preached unto you the gospel of God.

^10Ye are witnesses, and God also, how holily and justly and unblameably we behaved ourselves among you that believe:

^11As ye know how we exhorted and comforted and charged every one of you, as a father doth his children,

^12That ye would walk worthy of God, who hath called you unto his kingdom and glory.

^13For this cause also thank we God without ceasing, because, when ye received the word of God which ye heard of us, ye received it not as the word of men, but as it is in truth, the word of God, which effectually worketh also in you that believe.

^14For ye, brethren, became followers of the churches of God which in Judaea are in Christ Jesus: for ye also have suffered like things of your own countrymen, even as they have of the Jews:

^15Who both killed the Lord Jesus, and their own prophets, and have persecuted us; and they please not God, and are contrary to all men:

^16Forbidding us to speak to the Gentiles that they might be saved, to fill up their sins alway: for the wrath is come upon them to the uttermost.

^17But we, brethren, being taken from you for a short time in presence, not in heart, endeavoured the more abundantly to see your face with great desire.

^18Wherefore we would have come unto you, even I Paul, once and again; but Satan hindered us.

^19For what is our hope, or joy, or crown of rejoicing? Are not even ye in the presence of our Lord Jesus Christ at his coming?

^20For ye are our glory and joy.

III

^1Wherefore when we could no longer forbear, we thought it good to be left at Athens alone;

^2And sent Timotheus, our brother, and minister of God, and our fellowlabourer in the gospel of Christ, to establish you, and to comfort you concerning your faith:

^3That no man should be moved by these afflictions: for yourselves know that we are appointed thereunto.

^4For verily, when we were with you, we told you before that we should suffer tribulation; even as it came to pass, and ye know.

^5For this cause, when I could no longer forbear, I sent to know your faith, lest by some means the tempter have tempted you, and our labour be in vain.

^6But now when Timotheus came from you unto us, and brought us good tidings of your faith and charity, and that ye have good remembrance of us always, desiring greatly to see us, as we also to see you:

^7Therefore, brethren, we were comforted over you in all our affliction and distress by your faith:

^8For now we live, if ye stand fast in the Lord.

^9For what thanks can we render to God again for you, for all the joy wherewith we joy for your sakes before our God;

^10Night and day praying exceedingly that we might see your face, and might perfect that which is lacking in your faith?

^11Now God himself and our Father, and our Lord Jesus Christ, direct our way unto you.

^12And the Lord make you to increase and abound in love one toward another, and toward all men, even as we do toward you:

^13To the end he may stablish your hearts unblameable in holiness before God, even our Father, at the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ with all his saints.

IV

^1Furthermore then we beseech you, brethren, and exhort you by the Lord Jesus, that as ye have received of us how ye ought to walk and to please God, so ye would abound more and more.

^2For ye know what commandments we gave you by the Lord Jesus.

^3For this is the will of God, even your sanctification, that ye should abstain from fornication:

^4That every one of you should know how to possess his vessel in sanctification and honour;

^5Not in the lust of concupiscence, even as the Gentiles which know not God:

^6That no man go beyond and defraud his brother in any matter: because that the Lord is the avenger of all such, as we also have forewarned you and testified.

^7For God hath not called us unto uncleanness, but unto holiness.

^8He therefore that despiseth, despiseth not man, but God, who hath also given unto us his holy Spirit.

^9But as touching brotherly love ye need not that I write unto you: for ye yourselves are taught of God to love one another.

^10And indeed ye do it toward all the brethren which are in all Macedonia: but we beseech you, brethren, that ye increase more and more;

^11And that ye study to be quiet, and to do your own business, and to work with your own hands, as we commanded you;

^12That ye may walk honestly toward them that are without, and that ye may have lack of nothing.

^13But I would not have you to be ignorant, brethren, concerning them which are asleep, that ye sorrow not, even as others which have no hope.

^14For if we believe that Jesus died and rose again, even so them also which sleep in Jesus will God bring with him.

^15For this we say unto you by the word of the Lord, that we which are alive and remain unto the coming of the Lord shall not prevent them which are asleep.

^16For the Lord himself shall descend from heaven with a shout, with the voice of the archangel, and with the trump of God: and the dead in Christ shall rise first:

^17Then we which are alive and remain shall be caught up together with them in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the air: and so shall we ever be with the Lord.

^18Wherefore comfort one another with these words.

V

^1But of the times and the seasons, brethren, ye have no need that I write unto you.

^2For yourselves know perfectly that the day of the Lord so cometh as a thief in the night.

^3For when they shall say, Peace and safety; then sudden destruction cometh upon them, as travail upon a woman with child; and they shall not escape.

^4But ye, brethren, are not in darkness, that that day should overtake you as a thief.

^5Ye are all the children of light, and the children of the day: we are not of the night, nor of darkness.

^6Therefore let us not sleep, as do others; but let us watch and be sober.

^7For they that sleep sleep in the night; and they that be drunken are drunken in the night.

^8But let us, who are of the day, be sober, putting on the breastplate of faith and love; and for an helmet, the hope of salvation.

^9For God hath not appointed us to wrath, but to obtain salvation by our Lord Jesus Christ,

^10Who died for us, that, whether we wake or sleep, we should live together with him.

^11Wherefore comfort yourselves together, and edify one another, even as also ye do.

^12And we beseech you, brethren, to know them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admonish you;

^13And to esteem them very highly in love for their work’s sake. And be at peace among yourselves.

^14Now we exhort you, brethren, warn them that are unruly, comfort the feebleminded, support the weak, be patient toward all men.

^15See that none render evil for evil unto any man; but ever follow that which is good, both among yourselves, and to all men.

^16Rejoice evermore.

^17Pray without ceasing.

^18In every thing give thanks: for this is the will of God in Christ Jesus concerning you.

^19Quench not the Spirit.

^20Despise not prophesyings.

^21Prove all things; hold fast that which is good.

^22Abstain from all appearance of evil.

^23And the very God of peace sanctify you wholly; and I pray God your whole spirit and soul and body be preserved blameless unto the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ.

^24Faithful is he that calleth you, who also will do it.

^25Brethren, pray for us.

^26Greet all the brethren with an holy kiss.

^27I charge you by the Lord that this epistle be read unto all the holy brethren.

^28The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you. Amen.

Titus

The Epistle of Paul the Apostle to

Titus

I

^1Paul, a servant of God, and an apostle of Jesus Christ, according to the faith of God’s elect, and the acknowledging of the truth which is after godliness;

^2In hope of eternal life, which God, that cannot lie, promised before the world began;

^3But hath in due times manifested his word through preaching, which is committed unto me according to the commandment of God our Saviour;

^4To Titus, mine own son after the common faith: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ our Saviour.

^5For this cause left I thee in Crete, that thou shouldest set in order the things that are wanting, and ordain elders in every city, as I had appointed thee:

^6If any be blameless, the husband of one wife, having faithful children not accused of riot or unruly.

^7For a bishop must be blameless, as the steward of God; not selfwilled, not soon angry, not given to wine, no striker, not given to filthy lucre;

^8But a lover of hospitality, a lover of good men, sober, just, holy, temperate;

^9Holding fast the faithful word as he hath been taught, that he may be able by sound doctrine both to exhort and to convince the gainsayers.

^10For there are many unruly and vain talkers and deceivers, specially they of the circumcision:

^11Whose mouths must be stopped, who subvert whole houses, teaching things which they ought not, for filthy lucre’s sake.

^12One of themselves, even a prophet of their own, said, The Cretians are alway liars, evil beasts, slow bellies.

^13This witness is true. Wherefore rebuke them sharply, that they may be sound in the faith;

^14Not giving heed to Jewish fables, and commandments of men, that turn from the truth.

^15Unto the pure all things are pure: but unto them that are defiled and unbelieving is nothing pure; but even their mind and conscience is defiled.

^16They profess that they know God; but in works they deny him, being abominable, and disobedient, and unto every good work reprobate.

II

^1But speak thou the things which become sound doctrine:

^2That the aged men be sober, grave, temperate, sound in faith, in charity, in patience.

^3The aged women likewise, that they be in behaviour as becometh holiness, not false accusers, not given to much wine, teachers of good things;

^4That they may teach the young women to be sober, to love their husbands, to love their children,

^5To be discreet, chaste, keepers at home, good, obedient to their own husbands, that the word of God be not blasphemed.

^6Young men likewise exhort to be sober minded.

^7In all things shewing thyself a pattern of good works: in doctrine shewing uncorruptness, gravity, sincerity,

^8Sound speech, that cannot be condemned; that he that is of the contrary part may be ashamed, having no evil thing to say of you.

^9Exhort servants to be obedient unto their own masters, and to please them well in all things; not answering again;

^10Not purloining, but shewing all good fidelity; that they may adorn the doctrine of God our Saviour in all things.

^11For the grace of God that bringeth salvation hath appeared to all men,

^12Teaching us that, denying ungodliness and worldly lusts, we should live soberly, righteously, and godly, in this present world;

^13Looking for that blessed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God and our Saviour Jesus Christ;

^14Who gave himself for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purify unto himself a peculiar people, zealous of good works.

^15These things speak, and exhort, and rebuke with all authority. Let no man despise thee.

III

^1Put them in mind to be subject to principalities and powers, to obey magistrates, to be ready to every good work,

^2To speak evil of no man, to be no brawlers, but gentle, shewing all meekness unto all men.

^3For we ourselves also were sometimes foolish, disobedient, deceived, serving divers lusts and pleasures, living in malice and envy, hateful, and hating one another.

^4But after that the kindness and love of God our Saviour toward man appeared,

^5Not by works of righteousness which we have done, but according to his mercy he saved us, by the washing of regeneration, and renewing of the Holy Ghost;

^6Which he shed on us abundantly through Jesus Christ our Saviour;

^7That being justified by his grace, we should be made heirs according to the hope of eternal life.

^8This is a faithful saying, and these things I will that thou affirm constantly, that they which have believed in God might be careful to maintain good works. These things are good and profitable unto men.

^9But avoid foolish questions, and genealogies, and contentions, and strivings about the law; for they are unprofitable and vain.

^10A man that is an heretick after the first and second admonition reject;

^11Knowing that he that is such is subverted, and sinneth, being condemned of himself.

^12When I shall send Artemas unto thee, or Tychicus, be diligent to come unto me to Nicopolis: for I have determined there to winter.

^13Bring Zenas the lawyer and Apollos on their journey diligently, that nothing be wanting unto them.

^14And let our’s also learn to maintain good works for necessary uses, that they be not unfruitful.

^15All that are with me salute thee. Greet them that love us in the faith. Grace be with you all. Amen.

II John

The Second Epistle of

John

I

^1The elder unto the elect lady and her children, whom I love in the truth; and not I only, but also all they that have known the truth;

^2For the truth’s sake, which dwelleth in us, and shall be with us for ever.

^3Grace be with you, mercy, and peace, from God the Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ, the Son of the Father, in truth and love.

^4I rejoiced greatly that I found of thy children walking in truth, as we have received a commandment from the Father.

^5And now I beseech thee, lady, not as though I wrote a new commandment unto thee, but that which we had from the beginning, that we love one another.

^6And this is love, that we walk after his commandments. This is the commandment, That, as ye have heard from the beginning, ye should walk in it.

^7For many deceivers are entered into the world, who confess not that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh. This is a deceiver and an antichrist.

^8Look to yourselves, that we lose not those things which we have wrought, but that we receive a full reward.

^9Whosoever transgresseth, and abideth not in the doctrine of Christ, hath not God. He that abideth in the doctrine of Christ, he hath both the Father and the Son.

^10If there come any unto you, and bring not this doctrine, receive him not into your house, neither bid him God speed:

^11For he that biddeth him God speed is partaker of his evil deeds.

^12Having many things to write unto you, I would not write with paper and ink: but I trust to come unto you, and speak face to face, that our joy may be full.

^13The children of thy elect sister greet thee. Amen.

Exodus

The Second Book of Moses Called

Exodus

I

^1Now these are the names of the children of Israel, which came into Egypt; every man and his household came with Jacob. ^2Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah, ^3Issachar, Zebulun, and Benjamin, ^4Dan, and Naphtali, Gad, and Asher. ^5And all the souls that came out of the loins of Jacob were seventy souls: for Joseph was in Egypt already. ^6And Joseph died, and all his brethren, and all that generation. ^7And the children of Israel were fruitful, and increased abundantly, and multiplied, and waxed exceeding mighty; and the land was filled with them.

^8Now there arose up a new king over Egypt, which knew not Joseph. ^9And he said unto his people, Behold, the people of the children of Israel are more and mightier than we: ^10come on, let us deal wisely with them; lest they multiply, and it come to pass, that, when there falleth out any war, they join also unto our enemies, and fight against us, and so get them up out of the land. ^11Therefore they did set over them taskmasters to afflict them with their burdens. And they built for Pharaoh treasure cities, Pithom and Raamses. ^12But the more they afflicted them, the more they multiplied and grew. And they were grieved because of the children of Israel. ^13And the Egyptians made the children of Israel to serve with rigour: ^14and they made their lives bitter with hard bondage, in morter, and in brick, and in all manner of service in the field: all their service, wherein they made them serve, was with rigour.

^15And the king of Egypt spake to the Hebrew midwives, of which the name of the one was Shiphrah, and the name of the other Puah: ^16and he said, When ye do the office of a midwife to the Hebrew women, and see them upon the stools; if it be a son, then ye shall kill him: but if it be a daughter, then she shall live. ^17But the midwives feared God, and did not as the king of Egypt commanded them, but saved the men children alive. ^18And the king of Egypt called for the midwives, and said unto them, Why have ye done this thing, and have saved the men children alive? ^19And the midwives said unto Pharaoh, Because the Hebrew women are not as the Egyptian women; for they are lively, and are delivered ere the midwives come in unto them. ^20Therefore God dealt well with the midwives: and the people multiplied, and waxed very mighty. ^21And it came to pass, because the midwives feared God, that he made them houses. ^22And Pharaoh charged all his people, saying, Every son that is born ye shall cast into the river, and every daughter ye shall save alive.

II

^1And there went a man of the house of Levi, and took to wife a daughter of Levi. ^2And the woman conceived, and bare a son: and when she saw him that he was a goodly child, she hid him three months. ^3And when she could not longer hide him, she took for him an ark of bulrushes, and daubed it with slime and with pitch, and put the child therein; and she laid it in the flags by the river’s brink. ^4And his sister stood afar off, to wit what would be done to him.

^5And the daughter of Pharaoh came down to wash herself at the river; and her maidens walked along by the river’s side; and when she saw the ark among the flags, she sent her maid to fetch it. ^6And when she had opened it, she saw the child: and, behold, the babe wept. And she had compassion on him, and said, This is one of the Hebrews’ children. ^7Then said his sister to Pharaoh’s daughter, Shall I go and call to thee a nurse of the Hebrew women, that she may nurse the child for thee? ^8And Pharaoh’s daughter said to her, Go. And the maid went and called the child’s mother. ^9And Pharaoh’s daughter said unto her, Take this child away, and nurse it for me, and I will give thee thy wages. And the women took the child, and nursed it. ^10And the child grew, and she brought him unto Pharaoh’s daughter, and he became her son. And she called his name Moses: and she said, Because I drew him out of the water.

^11And it came to pass in those days, when Moses was grown, that he went out unto his brethren, and looked on their burdens: and he spied an Egyptian smiting an Hebrew, one of his brethren. ^12And he looked this way and that way, and when he saw that there was no man, he slew the Egyptian, and hid him in the sand. ^13And when he went out the second day, behold, two men of the Hebrews strove together: and he said to him that did the wrong, Wherefore smitest thou thy fellow? ^14And he said, Who made thee a prince and a judge over us? intendest thou to kill me, as thou killedst the Egyptian? And Moses feared, and said, Surely this thing is known. ^15Now when Pharaoh heard this thing, he sought to slay Moses. But Moses fled from the face of Pharaoh, and dwelt in the land of Midian: and he sat down by a well.

^16Now the priest of Midian had seven daughters: and they came and drew water, and filled the troughs to water their father’s flock. ^17And the shepherds came and drove them away: but Moses stood up and helped them, and watered their flock. ^18And when they came to Reuel their father, he said, How is it that ye are come so soon to day? ^19And they said, An Egyptian delivered us out of the hand of the shepherds, and also drew water enough for us, and watered the flock. ^20And he said unto his daughters, And where is he? why is it that ye have left the man? call him, that he may eat bread. ^21And Moses was content to dwell with the man: and he gave Moses Zipporah his daughter. ^22And she bare him a son, and he called his name Gershom: for he said, I have been a stranger in a strange land.

^23And it came to pass in process of time, that the king of Egypt died: and the children of Israel sighed by reason of the bondage, and they cried, and their cry came up unto God by reason of the bondage. ^24And God heard their groaning, and God remembered his covenant with Abraham, with Isaac, and with Jacob. ^25And God looked upon the children of Israel, and God had respect unto them.

III

^1Now Moses kept the flock of Jethro his father in law, the priest of Midian: and he led the flock to the backside of the desert, and came to the mountain of God, even to Horeb. ^2And the angel of the Lord appeared unto him in a flame of fire out of the midst of a bush: and he looked, and, behold, the bush burned with fire, and the bush was not consumed. ^3And Moses said, I will now turn aside, and see this great sight, why the bush is not burnt. ^4And when the Lord saw that he turned aside to see, God called unto him out of the midst of the bush, and said, Moses, Moses. And he said, Here am I. ^5And he said, Draw not nigh hither: put off thy shoes from off thy feet, for the place whereon thou standest is holy ground. ^6Moreover he said, I am the God of thy father, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob. And Moses hid his face; for he was afraid to look upon God.

^7And the Lord said, I have surely seen the affliction of my people which are in Egypt, and have heard their cry by reason of their taskmasters; for I know their sorrows; ^8and I am come down to deliver them out of the hand of the Egyptians, and to bring them up out of that land unto a good land and a large, unto a land flowing with milk and honey; unto the place of the Canaanites, and the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites. ^9Now therefore, behold, the cry of the children of Israel is come unto me: and I have also seen the oppression wherewith the Egyptians oppress them. ^10Come now therefore, and I will send thee unto Pharaoh, that thou mayest bring forth my people the children of Israel out of Egypt. ^11And Moses said unto God, Who am I, that I should go unto Pharaoh, and that I should bring forth the children of Israel out of Egypt? ^12And he said, Certainly I will be with thee; and this shall be a token unto thee, that I have sent thee: When thou hast brought forth the people out of Egypt, ye shall serve God upon this mountain.

^13And Moses said unto God, Behold, when I come unto the children of Israel, and shall say unto them, The God of your fathers hath sent me unto you; and they shall say to me, What is his name? what shall I say unto them? ^14And God said unto Moses, I Am That I Am: and he said, Thus shalt thou say unto the children of Israel, I Am hath sent me unto you. ^15And God said moreover unto Moses, Thus shalt thou say unto the children of Israel, the Lord God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, hath sent me unto you: this is my name for ever, and this is my memorial unto all generations. ^16Go, and gather the elders of Israel together, and say unto them, The Lord God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Jacob, appeared unto me, saying, I have surely visited you, and seen that which is done to you in Egypt: ^17and I have said, I will bring you up out of the affliction of Egypt unto the land of the Canaanites, and the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, unto a land flowing with milk and honey. ^18And they shall hearken to thy voice: and thou shalt come, thou and the elders of Israel, unto the king of Egypt, and ye shall say unto him, The Lord God of the Hebrews hath met with us: and now let us go, we beseech thee, three days’ journey into the wilderness, that we may sacrifice to the Lord our God. ^19And I am sure that the king of Egypt will not let you go, no, not by a mighty hand. ^20And I will stretch out my hand, and smite Egypt with all my wonders which I will do in the midst thereof: and after that he will let you go. ^21And I will give this people favour in the sight of the Egyptians: and it shall come to pass, that, when ye go, ye shall not go empty. ^22But every woman shall borrow of her neighbour, and of her that sojourneth in her house, jewels of silver, and jewels of gold, and raiment: and ye shall put them upon your sons, and upon your daughters; and ye shall spoil the Egyptians.

IV

^1And Moses answered and said, But, behold, they will not believe me, nor hearken unto my voice: for they will say, The Lord hath not appeared unto thee. ^2And the Lord said unto him, What is that in thine hand? And he said, A rod. ^3And he said, Cast it on the ground. And he cast it on the ground, and it became a serpent; and Moses fled from before it. ^4And the Lord said unto Moses, Put forth thine hand, and take it by the tail. And he put forth his hand, and caught it, and it became a rod in his hand: ^5that they may believe that the Lord God of their fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, hath appeared unto thee.

^6And the Lord said furthermore unto him, Put now thine hand into thy bosom. And he put his hand into his bosom: and when he took it out, behold, his hand was leprous as snow. ^7And he said, Put thine hand into thy bosom again. And he put his hand into his bosom again; and plucked it out of his bosom, and, behold, it was turned again as his other flesh. ^8And it shall come to pass, if they will not believe thee, neither hearken to the voice of the first sign, that they will believe the voice of the latter sign. ^9And it shall come to pass, if they will not believe also these two signs, neither hearken unto thy voice, that thou shalt take of the water of the river, and pour it upon the dry land: and the water which thou takest out of the river shall become blood upon the dry land.

^10And Moses said unto the Lord, O my Lord, I am not eloquent, neither heretofore, nor since thou hast spoken unto thy servant: but I am slow of speech, and of a slow tongue. ^11And the Lord said unto him, Who hath made man’s mouth? or who maketh the dumb, or deaf, or the seeing, or the blind? have not I the Lord? ^12Now therefore go, and I will be with thy mouth, and teach thee what thou shalt say. ^13And he said, O my Lord, send, I pray thee, by the hand of him whom thou wilt send. ^14And the anger of the Lord was kindled against Moses, and he said, Is not Aaron the Levite thy brother? I know that he can speak well. And also, behold, he cometh forth to meet thee: and when he seeth thee, he will be glad in his heart. ^15And thou shalt speak unto him, and put words in his mouth: and I will be with thy mouth, and with his mouth, and will teach you what ye shall do. ^16And he shall be thy spokesman unto the people: and he shall be, even he shall be to thee instead of a mouth, and thou shalt be to him instead of God. ^17And thou shalt take this rod in thine hand, wherewith thou shalt do signs.

^18And Moses went and returned to Jethro his father in law, and said unto him, Let me go, I pray thee, and return unto my brethren which are in Egypt, and see whether they be yet alive. And Jethro said to Moses, Go in peace. ^19And the Lord said unto Moses in Midian, Go, return into Egypt: for all the men are dead which sought thy life. ^20And Moses took his wife and his sons, and set them upon an ass, and he returned to the land of Egypt: and Moses took the rod of God in his hand. ^21And the Lord said unto Moses, When thou goest to return into Egypt, see that thou do all those wonders before Pharaoh, which I have put in thine hand: but I will harden his heart, that he shall not let the people go. ^22And thou shalt say unto Pharaoh, Thus saith the Lord, Israel is my son, even my firstborn: ^23and I say unto thee, Let my son go, that he may serve me: and if thou refuse to let him go, behold, I will slay thy son, even thy firstborn.

^24And it came to pass by the way in the inn, that the Lord met him, and sought to kill him. ^25Then Zipporah took a sharp stone, and cut off the foreskin of her son, and cast it at his feet, and said, Surely a bloody husband art thou to me. ^26So he let him go: then she said, A bloody husband thou art, because of the circumcision.

^27And the Lord said to Aaron, Go into the wilderness to meet Moses. And he went, and met him in the mount of God, and kissed him. ^28And Moses told Aaron all the words of the Lord who had sent him, and all the signs which he had commanded him.

^29And Moses and Aaron went and gathered together all the elders of the children of Israel: ^30and Aaron spake all the words which the Lord had spoken unto Moses, and did the signs in the sight of the people. ^31And the people believed: and when they heard that the Lord had visited the children of Israel, and that he had looked upon their affliction, then they bowed their heads and worshipped.

V

^1And afterward Moses and Aaron went in, and told Pharaoh, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, Let my people go, that they may hold a feast unto me in the wilderness. ^2And Pharaoh said, Who is the Lord, that I should obey his voice to let Israel go? I know not the Lord, neither will I let Israel go. ^3And they said, The God of the Hebrews hath met with us: let us go, we pray thee, three days’ journey into the desert, and sacrifice unto the Lord our God; lest he fall upon us with pestilence, or with the sword. ^4And the king of Egypt said unto them, Wherefore do ye, Moses and Aaron, let the people from their works? get you unto your burdens. ^5And Pharaoh said, Behold, the people of the land now are many, and ye make them rest from their burdens. ^6And Pharaoh commanded the same day the taskmasters of the people, and their officers, saying, ^7Ye shall no more give the people straw to make brick, as heretofore: let them go and gather straw for themselves. ^8And the tale of the bricks, which they did make heretofore, ye shall lay upon them; ye shall not diminish ought thereof: for they be idle; therefore they cry, saying, Let us go and sacrifice to our God. ^9Let there more work be laid upon the men, that they may labour therein; and let them not regard vain words.

^10And the taskmasters of the people went out, and their officers, and they spake to the people, saying, Thus saith Pharaoh, I will not give you straw. ^11Go ye, get you straw where ye can find it: yet not ought of your work shall be diminished. ^12So the people were scattered abroad throughout all the land of Egypt to gather stubble instead of straw. ^13And the taskmasters hasted them, saying, Fulfil your works, your daily tasks, as when there was straw. ^14And the officers of the children of Israel, which Pharaoh’s taskmasters had set over them, were beaten, and demanded, Wherefore have ye not fulfilled your task in making brick both yesterday and to day, as heretofore?

^15Then the officers of the children of Israel came and cried unto Pharaoh, saying, Wherefore dealest thou thus with thy servants? ^16There is no straw given unto thy servants, and they say to us, Make brick: and, behold, thy servants are beaten; but the fault is in thine own people. ^17But he said, Ye are idle, ye are idle: therefore ye say, Let us go and do sacrifice to the Lord. ^18Go therefore now, and work; for there shall no straw be given you, yet shall ye deliver the tale of bricks. ^19And the officers of the children of Israel did see that they were in evil case, after it was said, Ye shall not minish ought from your bricks of your daily task.

^20And they met Moses and Aaron, who stood in the way, as they came forth from Pharaoh: ^21and they said unto them, The Lord look upon you, and judge; because ye have made our savour to be abhorred in the eyes of Pharaoh, and in the eyes of his servants, to put a sword in their hand to slay us. ^22And Moses returned unto the Lord, and said, Lord, wherefore hast thou so evil entreated this people? why is it that thou hast sent me? ^23For since I came to Pharaoh to speak in thy name, he hath done evil to this people; neither hast thou delivered thy people at all.

VI

^1Then the Lord said unto Moses, Now shalt thou see what I will do to Pharaoh: for with a strong hand shall he let them go, and with a strong hand shall he drive them out of his land. ^2And God spake unto Moses, and said unto him, I am the Lord: ^3and I appeared unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob, by the name of God Almighty, but by my name Jehovah was I not known to them. ^4And I have also established my covenant with them, to give them the land of Canaan, the land of their pilgrimage, wherein they were strangers. ^5And I have also heard the groaning of the children of Israel, whom the Egyptians keep in bondage; and I have remembered my covenant. ^6Wherefore say unto the children of Israel, I am the Lord, and I will bring you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians, and I will rid you out of their bondage, and I will redeem you with a stretched out arm, and with great judgments: ^7and I will take you to me for a people, and I will be to you a God: and ye shall know that I am the Lord your God, which bringeth you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians. ^8And I will bring you in unto the land, concerning the which I did swear to give it to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob; and I will give it you for an heritage: I am the Lord.

^9And Moses spake so unto the children of Israel: but they hearkened not unto Moses for anguish of spirit, and for cruel bondage. ^10And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^11Go in, speak unto Pharaoh king of Egypt, that he let the children of Israel go out of his land. ^12And Moses spake before the Lord, saying, Behold, the children of Israel have not hearkened unto me; how then shall Pharaoh hear me, who am of uncircumcised lips? ^13And the Lord spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, and gave them a charge unto the children of Israel, and unto Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring the children of Israel out of the land of Egypt.

^14These be the heads of their fathers’ houses: The sons of Reuben the firstborn of Israel; Hanoch, and Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi: these be the families of Reuben. ^15And the sons of Simeon; Jemuel, and Jamin, and Ohad, and Jachin, and Zohar, and Shaul the son of a Canaanitish woman: these are the families of Simeon. ^16And these are the names of the sons of Levi according to their generations; Gershon, and Kohath, and Merari: and the years of the life of Levi were an hundred thirty and seven years. ^17The sons of Gershon; Libni, and Shimi, according to their families. ^18And the sons of Kohath; Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel: and the years of the life of Kohath were an hundred thirty and three years. ^19And the sons of Merari; Mahali and Mushi: these are the families of Levi according to their generations. ^20And Amram took him Jochebed his father’s sister to wife; and she bare him Aaron and Moses: and the years of the life of Amram were an hundred and thirty and seven years. ^21And the sons of Izhar; Korah, and Nepheg, and Zichri. ^22And the sons of Uzziel; Mishael, and Elzaphan, and Zithri. ^23And Aaron took him Elisheba, daughter of Amminadab, sister of Naashon, to wife; and she bare him Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. ^24And the sons of Korah; Assir, and Elkanah, and Abiasaph: these are the families of the Korhites. ^25And Eleazar Aaron’s son took him one of the daughters of Putiel to wife; and she bare him Phinehas: these are the heads of the fathers of the Levites according to their families. ^26These are that Aaron and Moses, to whom the Lord said, Bring out the children of Israel from the land of Egypt according to their armies. ^27These are they which spake to Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring out the children of Israel from Egypt: these are that Moses and Aaron.

^28And it came to pass on the day when the Lord spake unto Moses in the land of Egypt, ^29that the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, I am the Lord: speak thou unto Pharaoh king of Egypt all that I say unto thee. ^30And Moses said before the Lord, Behold, I am of uncircumcised lips, and how shall Pharaoh hearken unto me?

VII

^1And the Lord said unto Moses, See, I have made thee a god to Pharaoh: and Aaron thy brother shall be thy prophet. ^2Thou shalt speak all that I command thee: and Aaron thy brother shall speak unto Pharaoh, that he send the children of Israel out of his land. ^3And I will harden Pharaoh’s heart, and multiply my signs and my wonders in the land of Egypt. ^4But Pharaoh shall not hearken unto you, that I may lay my hand upon Egypt, and bring forth mine armies, and my people the children of Israel, out of the land of Egypt by great judgments. ^5And the Egyptians shall know that I am the Lord, when I stretch forth mine hand upon Egypt, and bring out the children of Israel from among them. ^6And Moses and Aaron did as the Lord commanded them, so did they. ^7And Moses was fourscore years old, and Aaron fourscore and three years old, when they spake unto Pharaoh.

^8And the Lord spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, ^9When Pharaoh shall speak unto you, saying, Shew a miracle for you: then thou shalt say unto Aaron, Take thy rod, and cast it before Pharaoh, and it shall become a serpent. ^10And Moses and Aaron went in unto Pharaoh, and they did so as the Lord had commanded: and Aaron cast down his rod before Pharaoh, and before his servants, and it became a serpent. ^11Then Pharaoh also called the wise men and the sorcerers: now the magicians of Egypt, they also did in like manner with their enchantments. ^12For they cast down every man his rod, and they became serpents: but Aaron’s rod swallowed up their rods. ^13And he hardened Pharaoh’s heart, that he hearkened not unto them; as the Lord had said.

^14And the Lord said unto Moses, Pharaoh’s heart is hardened, he refuseth to let the people go. ^15Get thee unto Pharaoh in the morning; lo, he goeth out unto the water; and thou shalt stand by the river’s brink against he come; and the rod which was turned to a serpent shalt thou take in thine hand. ^16And thou shalt say unto him, The Lord God of the Hebrews hath sent me unto thee, saying, Let my people go, that they may serve me in the wilderness: and, behold, hitherto thou wouldest not hear. ^17Thus saith the Lord, In this thou shalt know that I am the Lord: behold, I will smite with the rod that is in mine hand upon the waters which are in the river, and they shall be turned to blood. ^18And the fish that is in the river shall die, and the river shall stink; and the Egyptians shall lothe to drink of the water of the river. ^19And the Lord spake unto Moses, Say unto Aaron, Take thy rod, and stretch out thine hand upon the waters of Egypt, upon their streams, upon their rivers, and upon their ponds, and upon all their pools of water, that they may become blood; and that there may be blood throughout all the land of Egypt, both in vessels of wood, and in vessels of stone.

^20And Moses and Aaron did so, as the Lord commanded; and he lifted up the rod, and smote the waters that were in the river, in the sight of Pharaoh, and in the sight of his servants; and all the waters that were in the river were turned to blood. ^21And the fish that was in the river died; and the river stank, and the Egyptians could not drink of the water of the river; and there was blood throughout all the land of Egypt. ^22And the magicians of Egypt did so with their enchantments: and Pharaoh’s heart was hardened, neither did he hearken unto them; as the Lord had said. ^23And Pharaoh turned and went into his house, neither did he set his heart to this also. ^24And all the Egyptians digged round about the river for water to drink; for they could not drink of the water of the river. ^25And seven days were fulfilled, after that the Lord had smitten the river.

VIII

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, Go unto Pharaoh, and say unto him, Thus saith the Lord, Let my people go, that they may serve me. ^2And if thou refuse to let them go, behold, I will smite all thy borders with frogs: ^3and the river shall bring forth frogs abundantly, which shall go up and come into thine house, and into thy bedchamber, and upon thy bed, and into the house of thy servants, and upon thy people, and into thine ovens, and into thy kneadingtroughs: ^4and the frogs shall come up both on thee, and upon thy people, and upon all thy servants.

^5And the Lord spake unto Moses, Say unto Aaron, Stretch forth thine hand with thy rod over the streams, over the rivers, and over the ponds, and cause frogs to come up upon the land of Egypt. ^6And Aaron stretched out his hand over the waters of Egypt; and the frogs came up, and covered the land of Egypt. ^7And the magicians did so with their enchantments, and brought up frogs upon the land of Egypt.

^8Then Pharaoh called for Moses and Aaron, and said, Intreat the Lord, that he may take away the frogs from me, and from my people; and I will let the people go, that they may do sacrifice unto the Lord. ^9And Moses said unto Pharaoh, Glory over me: when shall I intreat for thee, and for thy servants, and for thy people, to destroy the frogs from thee and thy houses, that they may remain in the river only? ^10And he said, To morrow. And he said, Be it according to thy word: that thou mayest know that there is none like unto the Lord our God. ^11And the frogs shall depart from thee, and from thy houses, and from thy servants, and from thy people; they shall remain in the river only. ^12And Moses and Aaron went out from Pharaoh: and Moses cried unto the Lord because of the frogs which he had brought against Pharaoh. ^13And the Lord did according to the word of Moses; and the frogs died out of the houses, out of the villages, and out of the fields. ^14And they gathered them together upon heaps: and the land stank. ^15But when Pharaoh saw that there was respite, he hardened his heart, and hearkened not unto them; as the Lord had said.

^16And the Lord said unto Moses, Say unto Aaron, Stretch out thy rod, and smite the dust of the land, that it may become lice throughout all the land of Egypt. ^17And they did so; for Aaron stretched out his hand with his rod, and smote the dust of the earth, and it became lice in man, and in beast; all the dust of the land became lice throughout all the land of Egypt. ^18And the magicians did so with their enchantments to bring forth lice, but they could not: so there were lice upon man, and upon beast. ^19Then the magicians said unto Pharaoh, This is the finger of God: and Pharaoh’s heart was hardened, and he hearkened not unto them; as the Lord had said.

^20And the Lord said unto Moses, Rise up early in the morning, and stand before Pharaoh; lo, he cometh forth to the water; and say unto him, Thus saith the Lord, Let my people go, that they may serve me. ^21Else, if thou wilt not let my people go, behold, I will send swarms of flies upon thee, and upon thy servants, and upon thy people, and into thy houses: and the houses of the Egyptians shall be full of swarms of flies, and also the ground whereon they are. ^22And I will sever in that day the land of Goshen, in which my people dwell, that no swarms of flies shall be there; to the end thou mayest know that I am the Lord in the midst of the earth. ^23And I will put a division between my people and thy people: to morrow shall this sign be. ^24And the Lord did so; and there came a grievous swarm of flies into the house of Pharaoh, and into his servants’ houses, and into all the land of Egypt: the land was corrupted by reason of the swarm of flies.

^25And Pharaoh called for Moses and for Aaron, and said, Go ye, sacrifice to your God in the land. ^26And Moses said, It is not meet so to do; for we shall sacrifice the abomination of the Egyptians to the Lord our God: lo, shall we sacrifice the abomination of the Egyptians before their eyes, and will they not stone us? ^27We will go three days’ journey into the wilderness, and sacrifice to the Lord our God, as he shall command us. ^28And Pharaoh said, I will let you go, that ye may sacrifice to the Lord your God in the wilderness; only ye shall not go very far away: intreat for me. ^29And Moses said, Behold, I go out from thee, and I will intreat the Lord that the swarms of flies may depart from Pharaoh, from his servants, and from his people, to morrow: but let not Pharaoh deal deceitfully any more in not letting the people go to sacrifice to the Lord. ^30And Moses went out from Pharaoh, and intreated the Lord. ^31And the Lord did according to the word of Moses; and he removed the swarms of flies from Pharaoh, from his servants, and from his people; there remained not one. ^32And Pharaoh hardened his heart at this time also, neither would he let the people go.

IX

^1Then the Lord said unto Moses, Go in unto Pharaoh, and tell him, Thus saith the Lord God of the Hebrews, Let my people go, that they may serve me. ^2For if thou refuse to let them go, and wilt hold them still, ^3behold, the hand of the Lord is upon thy cattle which is in the field, upon the horses, upon the asses, upon the camels, upon the oxen, and upon the sheep: there shall be a very grievous murrain. ^4And the Lord shall sever between the cattle of Israel and the cattle of Egypt: and there shall nothing die of all that is the children’s of Israel. ^5And the Lord appointed a set time, saying, To morrow the Lord shall do this thing in the land. ^6And the Lord did that thing on the morrow, and all the cattle of Egypt died: but of the cattle of the children of Israel died not one. ^7And Pharaoh sent, and, behold, there was not one of the cattle of the Israelites dead. And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, and he did not let the people go.

^8And the Lord said unto Moses and unto Aaron, Take to you handfuls of ashes of the furnace, and let Moses sprinkle it toward the heaven in the sight of Pharaoh. ^9And it shall become small dust in all the land of Egypt, and shall be a boil breaking forth with blains upon man, and upon beast, throughout all the land of Egypt. ^10And they took ashes of the furnace, and stood before Pharaoh; and Moses sprinkled it up toward heaven; and it became a boil breaking forth with blains upon man, and upon beast. ^11And the magicians could not stand before Moses because of the boils; for the boil was upon the magicians, and upon all the Egyptians. ^12And the Lord hardened the heart of Pharaoh, and he hearkened not unto them; as the Lord had spoken unto Moses.

^13And the Lord said unto Moses, Rise up early in the morning, and stand before Pharaoh, and say unto him, Thus saith the Lord God of the Hebrews, Let my people go, that they may serve me. ^14For I will at this time send all my plagues upon thine heart, and upon thy servants, and upon thy people; that thou mayest know that there is none like me in all the earth. ^15For now I will stretch out my hand, that I may smite thee and thy people with pestilence; and thou shalt be cut off from the earth. ^16And in very deed for this cause have I raised thee up, for to shew in thee my power; and that my name may be declared throughout all the earth. ^17As yet exaltest thou thyself against my people, that thou wilt not let them go? ^18Behold, to morrow about this time I will cause it to rain a very grievous hail, such as hath not been in Egypt since the foundation thereof even until now. ^19Send therefore now, and gather thy cattle, and all that thou hast in the field; for upon every man and beast which shall be found in the field, and shall not be brought home, the hail shall come down upon them, and they shall die. ^20He that feared the word of the Lord among the servants of Pharaoh made his servants and his cattle flee into the houses: ^21and he that regarded not the word of the Lord left his servants and his cattle in the field.

^22And the Lord said unto Moses, Stretch forth thine hand toward heaven, that there may be hail in all the land of Egypt, upon man, and upon beast, and upon every herb of the field, throughout the land of Egypt. ^23And Moses stretched forth his rod toward heaven: and the Lord sent thunder and hail, and the fire ran along upon the ground; and the Lord rained hail upon the land of Egypt. ^24So there was hail, and fire mingled with the hail, very grievous, such as there was none like it in all the land of Egypt since it became a nation. ^25And the hail smote throughout all the land of Egypt all that was in the field, both man and beast; and the hail smote every herb of the field, and brake every tree of the field. ^26Only in the land of Goshen, where the children of Israel were, was there no hail.

^27And Pharaoh sent, and called for Moses and Aaron, and said unto them, I have sinned this time: the Lord is righteous, and I and my people are wicked. ^28Intreat the Lord (for it is enough) that there be no more mighty thunderings and hail; and I will let you go, and ye shall stay no longer. ^29And Moses said unto him, As soon as I am gone out of the city, I will spread abroad my hands unto the Lord; and the thunder shall cease, neither shall there be any more hail; that thou mayest know how that the earth is the Lord’s. ^30But as for thee and thy servants, I know that ye will not yet fear the Lord God. ^31And the flax and the barley was smitten: for the barley was in the ear, and the flax was bolled. ^32But the wheat and the rie were not smitten: for they were not grown up. ^33And Moses went out of the city from Pharaoh, and spread abroad his hands unto the Lord: and the thunders and hail ceased, and the rain was not poured upon the earth. ^34And when Pharaoh saw that the rain and the hail and the thunders were ceased, he sinned yet more, and hardened his heart, he and his servants. ^35And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, neither would he let the children of Israel go; as the Lord had spoken by Moses.

X

^1And the Lord said unto Moses, Go in unto Pharaoh: for I have hardened his heart, and the heart of his servants, that I might shew these my signs before him: ^2and that thou mayest tell in the ears of thy son, and of thy son’s son, what things I have wrought in Egypt, and my signs which I have done among them; that ye may know how that I am the Lord. ^3And Moses and Aaron came in unto Pharaoh, and said unto him, Thus saith the Lord God of the Hebrews, How long wilt thou refuse to humble thyself before me? let my people go, that they may serve me. ^4Else, if thou refuse to let my people go, behold, to morrow will I bring the locusts into thy coast: ^5and they shall cover the face of the earth, that one cannot be able to see the earth: and they shall eat the residue of that which is escaped, which remaineth unto you from the hail, and shall eat every tree which groweth for you out of the field: ^6and they shall fill thy houses, and the houses of all thy servants, and the houses of all the Egyptians; which neither thy fathers, nor thy fathers’ fathers have seen, since the day that they were upon the earth unto this day. And he turned himself, and went out from Pharaoh. ^7And Pharaoh’s servants said unto him, How long shall this man be a snare unto us? let the men go, that they may serve the Lord their God: knowest thou not yet that Egypt is destroyed? ^8And Moses and Aaron were brought again unto Pharaoh: and he said unto them, Go, serve the Lord your God: but who are they that shall go? ^9And Moses said, We will go with our young and with our old, with our sons and with our daughters, with our flocks and with our herds will we go; for we must hold a feast unto the Lord. ^10And he said unto them, Let the Lord be so with you, as I will let you go, and your little ones: look to it; for evil is before you. ^11Not so: go now ye that are men, and serve the Lord; for that ye did desire. And they were driven out from Pharaoh’s presence.

^12And the Lord said unto Moses, Stretch out thine hand over the land of Egypt for the locusts, that they may come up upon the land of Egypt, and eat every herb of the land, even all that the hail hath left. ^13And Moses stretched forth his rod over the land of Egypt, and the Lord brought an east wind upon the land all that day, and all that night; and when it was morning, the east wind brought the locusts. ^14And the locust went up over all the land of Egypt, and rested in all the coasts of Egypt: very grievous were they; before them there were no such locusts as they, neither after them shall be such. ^15For they covered the face of the whole earth, so that the land was darkened; and they did eat every herb of the land, and all the fruit of the trees which the hail had left: and there remained not any green thing in the trees, or in the herbs of the field, through all the land of Egypt.

^16Then Pharaoh called for Moses and Aaron in haste; and he said, I have sinned against the Lord your God, and against you. ^17Now therefore forgive, I pray thee, my sin only this once, and intreat the Lord your God, that he may take away from me this death only. ^18And he went out from Pharaoh, and intreated the Lord. ^19And the Lord turned a mighty strong west wind, which took away the locusts, and cast them into the Red sea; there remained not one locust in all the coasts of Egypt. ^20But the Lord hardened Pharaoh’s heart, so that he would not let the children of Israel go.

^21And the Lord said unto Moses, Stretch out thine hand toward heaven, that there may be darkness over the land of Egypt, even darkness which may be felt. ^22And Moses stretched forth his hand toward heaven; and there was a thick darkness in all the land of Egypt three days: ^23they saw not one another, neither rose any from his place for three days: but all the children of Israel had light in their dwellings.

^24And Pharaoh called unto Moses, and said, Go ye, serve the Lord; only let your flocks and your herds be stayed: let your little ones also go with you. ^25And Moses said, Thou must give us also sacrifices and burnt offerings, that we may sacrifice unto the Lord our God. ^26Our cattle also shall go with us; there shall not an hoof be left behind; for thereof must we take to serve the Lord our God; and we know not with what we must serve the Lord, until we come thither.

^27But the Lord hardened Pharaoh’s heart, and he would not let them go. ^28And Pharaoh said unto him, Get thee from me, take heed to thyself, see my face no more; for in that day thou seest my face thou shalt die. ^29And Moses said, Thou hast spoken well, I will see thy face again no more.

XI

^1And the Lord said unto Moses, Yet will I bring one plague more upon Pharaoh, and upon Egypt; afterwards he will let you go hence: when he shall let you go, he shall surely thrust you out hence altogether. ^2Speak now in the ears of the people, and let every man borrow of his neighbour, and every woman of her neighbour, jewels of silver and jewels of gold. ^3And the Lord gave the people favour in the sight of the Egyptians. Moreover the man Moses was very great in the land of Egypt, in the sight of Pharaoh’s servants, and in the sight of the people.

^4And Moses said, Thus saith the Lord, About midnight will I go out into the midst of Egypt: ^5and all the firstborn in the land of Egypt shall die, from the first born of Pharaoh that sitteth upon his throne, even unto the firstborn of the maidservant that is behind the mill; and all the firstborn of beasts. ^6And there shall be a great cry throughout all the land of Egypt, such as there was none like it, nor shall be like it any more. ^7But against any of the children of Israel shall not a dog move his tongue, against man or beast: that ye may know how that the Lord doth put a difference between the Egyptians and Israel. ^8And all these thy servants shall come down unto me, and bow down themselves unto me, saying, Get thee out, and all the people that follow thee: and after that I will go out. And he went out from Pharaoh in a great anger.

^9And the Lord said unto Moses, Pharaoh shall not hearken unto you; that my wonders may be multiplied in the land of Egypt. ^10And Moses and Aaron did all these wonders before Pharaoh: and the Lord hardened Pharaoh’s heart, so that he would not let the children of Israel go out of his land.

XII

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses and Aaron in the land of Egypt saying, ^2This month shall be unto you the beginning of months: it shall be the first month of the year to you. ^3Speak ye unto all the congregation of Israel, saying, In the tenth day of this month they shall take to them every man a lamb, according to the house of their fathers, a lamb for an house: ^4and if the household be too little for the lamb, let him and his neighbour next unto his house take it according to the number of the souls; every man according to his eating shall make your count for the lamb. ^5Your lamb shall be without blemish, a male of the first year: ye shall take it out from the sheep, or from the goats: ^6and ye shall keep it up until the fourteenth day of the same month: and the whole assembly of the congregation of Israel shall kill it in the evening. ^7And they shall take of the blood, and strike it on the two side posts and on the upper door post of the houses, wherein they shall eat it. ^8And they shall eat the flesh in that night, roast with fire, and unleavened bread; and with bitter herbs they shall eat it. ^9Eat not of it raw, nor sodden at all with water, but roast with fire; his head with his legs, and with the purtenance thereof. ^10And ye shall let nothing of it remain until the morning; and that which remaineth of it until the morning ye shall burn with fire.

^11And thus shall ye eat it; with your loins girded, your shoes on your feet, and your staff in your hand; and ye shall eat it in haste: it is the Lord’s passover. ^12For I will pass through the land of Egypt this night, and will smite all the firstborn in the land of Egypt, both man and beast; and against all the gods of Egypt I will execute judgment: I am the Lord. ^13And the blood shall be to you for a token upon the houses where ye are: and when I see the blood, I will pass over you, and the plague shall not be upon you to destroy you, when I smite the land of Egypt. ^14And this day shall be unto you for a memorial; and ye shall keep it a feast to the Lord throughout your generations; ye shall keep it a feast by an ordinance for ever. ^15Seven days shall ye eat unleavened bread; even the first day ye shall put away leaven out of your houses: for whosoever eateth leavened bread from the first day until the seventh day, that soul shall be cut off from Israel. ^16And in the first day there shall be an holy convocation, and in the seventh day there shall be an holy convocation to you; no manner of work shall be done in them, save that which every man must eat, that only may be done of you. ^17And ye shall observe the feast of unleavened bread; for in this selfsame day have I brought your armies out of the land of Egypt: therefore shall ye observe this day in your generations by an ordinance for ever.

^18In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month at even, ye shall eat unleavened bread, until the one and twentieth day of the month at even. ^19Seven days shall there be no leaven found in your houses: for whosoever eateth that which is leavened, even that soul shall be cut off from the congregation of Israel, whether he be a stranger, or born in the land. ^20Ye shall eat nothing leavened; in all your habitations shall ye eat unleavened bread.

^21Then Moses called for all the elders of Israel, and said unto them, Draw out and take you a lamb according to your families, and kill the passover. ^22And ye shall take a bunch of hyssop, and dip it in the blood that is in the bason, and strike the lintel and the two side posts with the blood that is in the bason; and none of you shall go out at the door of his house until the morning. ^23For the Lord will pass through to smite the Egyptians; and when he seeth the blood upon the lintel, and on the two side posts, the Lord will pass over the door, and will not suffer the destroyer to come in unto your houses to smite you. ^24And ye shall observe this thing for an ordinance to thee and to thy sons for ever. ^25And it shall come to pass, when ye be come to the land which the Lord will give you, according as he hath promised, that ye shall keep this service. ^26And it shall come to pass, when your children shall say unto you, What mean ye by this service? ^27That ye shall say, It is the sacrifice of the Lord’s passover, who passed over the houses of the children of Israel in Egypt, when he smote the Egyptians, and delivered our houses. And the people bowed the head and worshipped. ^28And the children of Israel went away, and did as the Lord had commanded Moses and Aaron, so did they.

^29And it came to pass, that at midnight the Lord smote all the firstborn in the land of Egypt, from the firstborn of Pharaoh that sat on his throne unto the firstborn of the captive that was in the dungeon; and all the firstborn of cattle. ^30And Pharaoh rose up in the night, he, and all his servants, and all the Egyptians; and there was a great cry in Egypt; for there was not a house where there was not one dead.

^31And he called for Moses and Aaron by night, and said, Rise up, and get you forth from among my people, both ye and the children of Israel; and go, serve the Lord, as ye have said. ^32Also take your flocks and your herds, as ye have said, and be gone; and bless me also. ^33And the Egyptians were urgent upon the people, that they might send them out of the land in haste; for they said, We be all dead men. ^34And the people took their dough before it was leavened, their kneadingtroughs being bound up in their clothes upon their shoulders. ^35And the children of Israel did according to the word of Moses; and they borrowed of the Egyptians jewels of silver, and jewels of gold, and raiment: ^36and the Lord gave the people favour in the sight of the Egyptians, so that they lent unto them such things as they required. And they spoiled the Egyptians.

^37And the children of Israel journeyed from Rameses to Succoth, about six hundred thousand on foot that were men, beside children. ^38And a mixed multitude went up also with them; and flocks, and herds, even very much cattle. ^39And they baked unleavened cakes of the dough which they brought forth out of Egypt, for it was not leavened; because they were thrust out of Egypt, and could not tarry, neither had they prepared for themselves any victual.

^40Now the sojourning of the children of Israel, who dwelt in Egypt, was four hundred and thirty years. ^41And it came to pass at the end of the four hundred and thirty years, even the selfsame day it came to pass, that all the hosts of the Lord went out from the land of Egypt. ^42It is a night to be much observed unto the Lord for bringing them out from the land of Egypt: this is that night of the Lord to be observed of all the children of Israel in their generations.

^43And the Lord said unto Moses and Aaron, This is the ordinance of the passover: There shall no stranger eat thereof: ^44but every man’s servant that is bought for money, when thou hast circumcised him, then shall he eat thereof. ^45A foreigner and an hired servant shall not eat thereof. ^46In one house shall it be eaten; thou shalt not carry forth ought of the flesh abroad out of the house; neither shall ye break a bone thereof. ^47All the congregation of Israel shall keep it. ^48And when a stranger shall sojourn with thee, and will keep the passover to the Lord, let all his males be circumcised, and then let him come near and keep it; and he shall be as one that is born in the land: for no uncircumcised person shall eat thereof. ^49One law shall be to him that is homeborn, and unto the stranger that sojourneth among you. ^50Thus did all the children of Israel; as the Lord commanded Moses and Aaron, so did they. ^51And it came to pass the selfsame day, that the Lord did bring the children of Israel out of the land of Egypt by their armies.

XIII

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Sanctify unto me all the firstborn, whatsoever openeth the womb among the children of Israel, both of man and of beast: it is mine.

^3And Moses said unto the people, Remember this day, in which ye came out from Egypt, out of the house of bondage; for by strength of hand the Lord brought you out from this place: there shall no leavened bread be eaten. ^4This day came ye out in the month Abib.

^5And it shall be when the Lord shall bring thee into the land of the Canaanites, and the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, which he sware unto thy fathers to give thee, a land flowing with milk and honey, that thou shalt keep this service in this month. ^6Seven days thou shalt eat unleavened bread, and in the seventh day shall be a feast to the Lord. ^7Unleavened bread shall be eaten seven days; and there shall no leavened bread be seen with thee, neither shall there be leaven seen with thee in all thy quarters.

^8And thou shalt shew thy son in that day, saying, This is done because of that which the Lord did unto me when I came forth out of Egypt. ^9And it shall be for a sign unto thee upon thine hand, and for a memorial between thine eyes, that the Lord’s law may be in thy mouth: for with a strong hand hath the Lord brought thee out of Egypt. ^10Thou shalt therefore keep this ordinance in his season from year to year.

^11And it shall be when the Lord shall bring thee into the land of the Canaanites, as he sware unto thee and to thy fathers, and shall give it thee, ^12that thou shalt set apart unto the Lord all that openeth the matrix, and every firstling that cometh of a beast which thou hast; the males shall be the Lord’s. ^13And every firstling of an ass thou shalt redeem with a lamb; and if thou wilt not redeem it, then thou shalt break his neck: and all the firstborn of man among thy children shalt thou redeem.

^14And it shall be when thy son asketh thee in time to come, saying, What is this? that thou shalt say unto him, By strength of hand the Lord brought us out from Egypt, from the house of bondage: ^15and it came to pass, when Pharaoh would hardly let us go, that the Lord slew all the firstborn in the land of Egypt, both the firstborn of man, and the firstborn of beast: therefore I sacrifice to the Lord all that openeth the matrix, being males; but all the firstborn of my children I redeem. ^16And it shall be for a token upon thine hand, and for frontlets between thine eyes: for by strength of hand the Lord brought us forth out of Egypt.

^17And it came to pass, when Pharaoh had let the people go, that God led them not through the way of the land of the Philistines, although that was near; for God said, Lest peradventure the people repent when they see war, and they return to Egypt: ^18but God led the people about, through the way of the wilderness of the Red sea: and the children of Israel went up harnessed out of the land of Egypt. ^19And Moses took the bones of Joseph with him: for he had straitly sworn the children of Israel, saying, God will surely visit you; and ye shall carry up my bones away hence with you.

^20And they took their journey from Succoth, and encamped in Etham, in the edge of the wilderness. ^21And the Lord went before them by day in a pillar of a cloud, to lead them the way; and by night in a pillar of fire, to give them light; to go by day and night: ^22he took not away the pillar of the cloud by day, nor the pillar of fire by night, from before the people.

XIV

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, that they turn and encamp before Pihahiroth, between Migdol and the sea, over against Baalzephon: before it shall ye encamp by the sea. ^3For Pharaoh will say of the children of Israel, They are entangled in the land, the wilderness hath shut them in. ^4And I will harden Pharaoh’s heart, that he shall follow after them; and I will be honoured upon Pharaoh, and upon all his host; that the Egyptians may know that I am the Lord. And they did so.

^5And it was told the king of Egypt that the people fled: and the heart of Pharaoh and of his servants was turned against the people, and they said, Why have we done this, that we have let Israel go from serving us? ^6And he made ready his chariot, and took his people with him: ^7and he took six hundred chosen chariots, and all the chariots of Egypt, and captains over every one of them. ^8And the Lord hardened the heart of Pharaoh king of Egypt, and he pursued after the children of Israel: and the children of Israel went out with an high hand. ^9But the Egyptians pursued after them, all the horses and chariots of Pharaoh, and his horsemen, and his army, and overtook them encamping by the sea, beside Pihahiroth, before Baalzephon.

^10And when Pharaoh drew nigh, the children of Israel lifted up their eyes, and, behold, the Egyptians marched after them; and they were sore afraid: and the children of Israel cried out unto the Lord. ^11And they said unto Moses, Because there were no graves in Egypt, hast thou taken us away to die in the wilderness? wherefore hast thou dealt thus with us, to carry us forth out of Egypt? ^12Is not this the word that we did tell thee in Egypt, saying, Let us alone, that we may serve the Egyptians? For it had been better for us to serve the Egyptians, than that we should die in the wilderness.

^13And Moses said unto the people, Fear ye not, stand still, and see the salvation of the Lord, which he will shew to you to day: for the Egyptians whom ye have seen to day, ye shall see them again no more for ever. ^14The Lord shall fight for you, and ye shall hold your peace.

^15And the Lord said unto Moses, Wherefore criest thou unto me? speak unto the children of Israel, that they go forward: ^16but lift thou up thy rod, and stretch out thine hand over the sea, and divide it: and the children of Israel shall go on dry ground through the midst of the sea. ^17And I, behold, I will harden the hearts of the Egyptians, and they shall follow them: and I will get me honour upon Pharaoh, and upon all his host, upon his chariots, and upon his horsemen. ^18And the Egyptians shall know that I am the Lord, when I have gotten me honour upon Pharaoh, upon his chariots, and upon his horsemen.

^19And the angel of God, which went before the camp of Israel, removed and went behind them; and the pillar of the cloud went from before their face, and stood behind them: ^20and it came between the camp of the Egyptians and the camp of Israel; and it was a cloud and darkness to them, but it gave light by night to these: so that the one came not near the other all the night. ^21And Moses stretched out his hand over the sea; and the Lord caused the sea to go back by a strong east wind all that night, and made the sea dry land, and the waters were divided. ^22And the children of Israel went into the midst of the sea upon the dry ground: and the waters were a wall unto them on their right hand, and on their left.

^23And the Egyptians pursued, and went in after them to the midst of the sea, even all Pharaoh’s horses, his chariots, and his horsemen. ^24And it came to pass, that in the morning watch the Lord looked unto the host of the Egyptians through the pillar of fire and of the cloud, and troubled the host of the Egyptians, ^25and took off their chariot wheels, that they drave them heavily: so that the Egyptians said, Let us flee from the face of Israel; for the Lord fighteth for them against the Egyptians.

^26And the Lord said unto Moses, Stretch out thine hand over the sea, that the waters may come again upon the Egyptians, upon their chariots, and upon their horsemen. ^27And Moses stretched forth his hand over the sea, and the sea returned to his strength when the morning appeared; and the Egyptians fled against it; and the Lord overthrew the Egyptians in the midst of the sea. ^28And the waters returned, and covered the chariots, and the horsemen, and all the host of Pharaoh that came into the sea after them; there remained not so much as one of them. ^29But the children of Israel walked upon dry land in the midst of the sea; and the waters were a wall unto them on their right hand, and on their left. ^30Thus the Lord saved Israel that day out of the hand of the Egyptians; and Israel saw the Egyptians dead upon the sea shore. ^31And Israel saw that great work which the Lord did upon the Egyptians: and the people feared the Lord, and believed the Lord, and his servant Moses.

XV

^1Then sang Moses and the children of Israel this song unto the Lord, and spake, saying,

I will sing unto the Lord, for he hath triumphed gloriously:
The horse and his rider hath he thrown into the sea.
^2The Lord is my strength and song,
And he is become my salvation:
He is my God, and I will prepare him an habitation;
My father’s God, and I will exalt him.
^3The Lord is a man of war:
The Lord is his name.
^4Pharaoh’s chariots and his host hath he cast into the sea:
His chosen captains also are drowned in the Red sea.
^5The depths have covered them:
They sank into the bottom as a stone.
^6Thy right hand, O Lord, is become glorious in power:
Thy right hand, O Lord, hath dashed in pieces the enemy.
^7And in the greatness of thine excellency thou hast overthrown them that rose up against thee:
Thou sentest forth thy wrath, which consumed them as stubble.
^8And with the blast of thy nostrils the waters were gathered together,
The floods stood upright as an heap,
And the depths were congealed in the heart of the sea.
^9The enemy said,
I will pursue, I will overtake, I will divide the spoil;
My lust shall be satisfied upon them;
I will draw my sword, my hand shall destroy them.
^10Thou didst blow with thy wind, the sea covered them:
They sank as lead in the mighty waters.
^11Who is like unto thee, O Lord, among the gods?
Who is like thee, glorious in holiness,
Fearful in praises, doing wonders?
^12Thou stretchedst out thy right hand,
The earth swallowed them.
^13Thou in thy mercy hast led forth the people which thou hast redeemed:
Thou hast guided them in thy strength unto thy holy habitation.
^14The people shall hear, and be afraid:
Sorrow shall take hold on the inhabitants of Palestina.
^15Then the dukes of Edom shall be amazed;
The mighty men of Moab, trembling shall take hold upon them;
All the inhabitants of Canaan shall melt away.
^16Fear and dread shall fall upon them;
By the greatness of thine arm they shall be as still as a stone;
Till thy people pass over, O Lord,
Till the people pass over, which thou hast purchased.
^17Thou shalt bring them in, and plant them in the mountain of thine inheritance,
In the place, O Lord, which thou hast made for thee to dwell in,
In the Sanctuary, O Lord, which thy hands have established.
^18The Lord shall reign for ever and ever.

^19For the horse of Pharaoh went in with his chariots and with his horsemen into the sea, and the Lord brought again the waters of the sea upon them; but the children of Israel went on dry land in the midst of the sea. ^20And Miriam the prophetess, the sister of Aaron, took a timbrel in her hand; and all the women went out after her with timbrels and with dances. ^21And Miriam answered them,

Sing ye to the Lord, for he hath triumphed gloriously;
The horse and his rider hath he thrown into the sea.

^22So Moses brought Israel from the Red sea, and they went out into the wilderness of Shur; and they went three days in the wilderness, and found no water. ^23And when they came to Marah, they could not drink of the waters of Marah, for they were bitter: therefore the name of it was called Marah. ^24And the people murmured against Moses, saying, What shall we drink? ^25And he cried unto the Lord; and the Lord shewed him a tree, which when he had cast into the waters, the waters were made sweet: there he made for them a statute and an ordinance, and there he proved them, ^26and said, If thou wilt diligently hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God, and wilt do that which is right in his sight, and wilt give ear to his commandments, and keep all his statutes, I will put none of these diseases upon thee, which I have brought upon the Egyptians: for I am the Lord that healeth thee.

^27And they came to Elim, where were twelve wells of water, and threescore and ten palm trees: and they encamped there by the waters.

XVI

^1And they took their journey from Elim, and all the congregation of the children of Israel came unto the wilderness of Sin, which is between Elim and Sinai, on the fifteenth day of the second month after their departing out of the land of Egypt. ^2And the whole congregation of the children of Israel murmured against Moses and Aaron in the wilderness: ^3and the children of Israel said unto them, Would to God we had died by the hand of the Lord in the land of Egypt, when we sat by the flesh pots, and when we did eat bread to the full; for ye have brought us forth into this wilderness, to kill this whole assembly with hunger.

^4Then said the Lord unto Moses, Behold, I will rain bread from heaven for you; and the people shall go out and gather a certain rate every day, that I may prove them, whether they will walk in my law, or no. ^5And it shall come to pass, that on the sixth day they shall prepare that which they bring in; and it shall be twice as much as they gather daily. ^6And Moses and Aaron said unto all the children of Israel, At even, then ye shall know that the Lord hath brought you out from the land of Egypt: ^7and in the morning, then ye shall see the glory of the Lord; for that he heareth your murmurings against the Lord: and what are we, that ye murmur against us? ^8And Moses said, This shall be, when the Lord shall give you in the evening flesh to eat, and in the morning bread to the full; for that the Lord heareth your murmurings which ye murmur against him: and what are we? your murmurings are not against us, but against the Lord.

^9And Moses spake unto Aaron, Say unto all the congregation of the children of Israel, Come near before the Lord: for he hath heard your murmurings. ^10And it came to pass, as Aaron spake unto the whole congregation of the children of Israel, that they looked toward the wilderness, and, behold, the glory of the Lord appeared in the cloud.

^11And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^12I have heard the murmurings of the children of Israel: speak unto them, saying, At even ye shall eat flesh, and in the morning ye shall be filled with bread; and ye shall know that I am the Lord your God. ^13And it came to pass, that at even the quails came up, and covered the camp: and in the morning the dew lay round about the host. ^14And when the dew that lay was gone up, behold, upon the face of the wilderness there lay a small round thing, as small as the hoar frost on the ground.

^15And when the children of Israel saw it, they said one to another, It is manna: for they wist not what it was. And Moses said unto them, This is the bread which the Lord hath given you to eat. ^16This is the thing which the Lord hath commanded, Gather of it every man according to his eating, an omer for every man, according to the number of your persons; take ye every man for them which are in his tents. ^17And the children of Israel did so, and gathered, some more, some less. ^18And when they did mete it with an omer, he that gathered much had nothing over, and he that gathered little had no lack; they gathered every man according to his eating. ^19And Moses said, Let no man leave of it till the morning. ^20Notwithstanding they hearkened not unto Moses; but some of them left of it until the morning, and it bred worms, and stank: and Moses was wroth with them. ^21And they gathered it every morning, every man according to his eating: and when the sun waxed hot, it melted.

^22And it came to pass, that on the sixth day they gathered twice as much bread, two omers for one man: and all the rulers of the congregation came and told Moses. ^23And he said unto them, This is that which the Lord hath said, To morrow is the rest of the holy sabbath unto the Lord: bake that which ye will bake to day, and seethe that ye will seethe; and that which remaineth over lay up for you to be kept until the morning. ^24And they laid it up till the morning, as Moses bade: and it did not stink, neither was there any worm therein. ^25And Moses said, Eat that to day; for to day is a sabbath unto the Lord: to day ye shall not find it in the field. ^26Six days ye shall gather it; but on the seventh day, which is the sabbath, in it there shall be none.

^27And it came to pass, that there went out some of the people on the seventh day for to gather, and they found none. ^28And the Lord said unto Moses, How long refuse ye to keep my commandments and my laws? ^29See, for that the Lord hath given you the sabbath, therefore he giveth you on the sixth day the bread of two days; abide ye every man in his place, let no man go out of his place on the seventh day. ^30So the people rested on the seventh day. ^31And the house of Israel called the name thereof Manna: and it was like coriander seed, white; and the taste of it was like wafers made with honey.

^32And Moses said, This is the thing which the Lord commandeth, Fill an omer of it to be kept for your generations; that they may see the bread wherewith I have fed you in the wilderness, when I brought you forth from the land of Egypt. ^33And Moses said unto Aaron, Take a pot, and put an omer full of manna therein, and lay it up before the Lord, to be kept for your generations. ^34As the Lord commanded Moses, so Aaron laid it up before the Testimony, to be kept. ^35And the children of Israel did eat manna forty years, until they came to a land inhabited; they did eat manna, until they came unto the borders of the land of Canaan. ^36Now an omer is the tenth part of an ephah.

XVII

^1And all the congregation of the children of Israel journeyed from the wilderness of Sin, after their journeys, according to the commandment of the Lord, and pitched in Rephidim: and there was no water for the people to drink. ^2Wherefore the people did chide with Moses, and said, Give us water that we may drink. And Moses said unto them, Why chide ye with me? wherefore do ye tempt the Lord? ^3And the people thirsted there for water; and the people murmured against Moses, and said, Wherefore is this that thou hast brought us up out of Egypt, to kill us and our children and our cattle with thirst? ^4And Moses cried unto the Lord, saying, What shall I do unto this people? they be almost ready to stone me. ^5And the Lord said unto Moses, Go on before the people, and take with thee of the elders of Israel; and thy rod, wherewith thou smotest the river, take in thine hand, and go. ^6Behold, I will stand before thee there upon the rock in Horeb; and thou shalt smite the rock, and there shall come water out of it, that the people may drink. And Moses did so in the sight of the elders of Israel. ^7And he called the name of the place Massah, and Meribah, because of the chiding of the children of Israel, and because they tempted the Lord, saying, Is the Lord among us, or not?

^8Then came Amalek, and fought with Israel in Rephidim. ^9And Moses said unto Joshua, Choose us out men, and go out, fight with Amalek: to morrow I will stand on the top of the hill with the rod of God in mine hand. ^10So Joshua did as Moses had said to him, and fought with Amalek: and Moses, Aaron, and Hur went up to the top of the hill. ^11And it came to pass, when Moses held up his hand, that Israel prevailed: and when he let down his hand, Amalek prevailed. ^12But Moses hands were heavy; and they took a stone, and put it under him, and he sat thereon; and Aaron and Hur stayed up his hands, the one on the one side, and the other on the other side; and his hands were steady until the going down of the sun. ^13And Joshua discomfited Amalek and his people with the edge of the sword. ^14And the Lord said unto Moses, Write this for a memorial in a book, and rehearse it in the ears of Joshua: for I will utterly put out the remembrance of Amalek from under heaven. ^15And Moses built an altar, and called the name of it Jehovahnissi: ^16for he said, Because the Lord hath sworn that the Lord will have war with Amalek from generation to generation.

XVIII

^1When Jethro, the priest of Midian, Moses’ father in law, heard of all that God had done for Moses, and for Israel his people, and that the Lord had brought Israel out of Egypt; ^2then Jethro, Moses’ father in law, took Zipporah, Moses’ wife, after he had sent her back, ^3and her two sons; of which the name of the one was Gershom; for he said, I have been an alien in a strange land: ^4and the name of the other was Eliezer; for the God of my father, said he, was mine help, and delivered me from the sword of Pharaoh: ^5and Jethro, Moses’ father in law, came with his sons and his wife unto Moses into the wilderness, where he encamped at the mount of God: ^6and he said unto Moses, I thy father in law Jethro am come unto thee, and thy wife, and her two sons with her.

^7And Moses went out to meet his father in law, and did obeisance, and kissed him; and they asked each other of their welfare; and they came into the tent. ^8And Moses told his father in law all that the Lord had done unto Pharaoh and to the Egyptians for Israel’s sake, and all the travail that had come upon them by the way, and how the Lord delivered them. ^9And Jethro rejoiced for all the goodness which the Lord had done to Israel, whom he had delivered out of the hand of the Egyptians. ^10And Jethro said, Blessed be the Lord, who hath delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of Pharaoh, who hath delivered the people from under the hand of the Egyptians. ^11Now I know that the Lord is greater than all gods: for in the thing wherein they dealt proudly he was above them. ^12And Jethro, Moses’ father in law, took a burnt offering and sacrifices for God: and Aaron came, and all the elders of Israel, to eat bread with Moses’ father in law before God.

^13And it came to pass on the morrow, that Moses sat to judge the people: and the people stood by Moses from the morning unto the evening. ^14And when Moses’ father in law saw all that he did to the people, he said, What is this thing that thou doest to the people? why sittest thou thyself alone, and all the people stand by thee from morning unto even? ^15And Moses said unto his father in law, Because the people come unto me to enquire of God: ^16when they have a matter, they come unto me; and I judge between one and another, and I do make them know the statutes of God, and his laws.

^17And Moses’ father in law said unto him, The thing that thou doest is not good. ^18Thou wilt surely wear away, both thou, and this people that is with thee: for this thing is too heavy for thee; thou art not able to perform it thyself alone. ^19Hearken now unto my voice, I will give thee counsel, and God shall be with thee: Be thou for the people to God-ward, that thou mayest bring the causes unto God: ^20and thou shalt teach them ordinances and laws, and shalt shew them the way wherein they must walk, and the work that they must do. ^21Moreover thou shalt provide out of all the people able men, such as fear God, men of truth, hating covetousness; and place such over them, to be rulers of thousands, and rulers of hundreds, rulers of fifties, and rulers of tens: ^22and let them judge the people at all seasons: and it shall be, that every great matter they shall bring unto thee, but every small matter they shall judge: so shall it be easier for thyself, and they shall bear the burden with thee. ^23If thou shalt do this thing, and God command thee so, then thou shalt be able to endure, and all this people shall also go to their place in peace.

^24So Moses hearkened to the voice of his father in law, and did all that he had said. ^25And Moses chose able men out of all Israel, and made them heads over the people, rulers of thousands, rulers of hundreds, rulers of fifties, and rulers of tens. ^26And they judged the people at all seasons: the hard causes they brought unto Moses, but every small matter they judged themselves. ^27And Moses let his father in law depart; and he went his way into his own land.

XIX

^1In the third month, when the children of Israel were gone forth out of the land of Egypt, the same day came they into the wilderness of Sinai. ^2For they were departed from Rephidim, and were come to the desert of Sinai, and had pitched in the wilderness; and there Israel camped before the mount. ^3And Moses went up unto God, and the Lord called unto him out of the mountain, saying, Thus shalt thou say to the house of Jacob, and tell the children of Israel; ^4ye have seen what I did unto the Egyptians, and how I bare you on eagles’ wings, and brought you unto myself. ^5Now therefore, if ye will obey my voice indeed, and keep my covenant, then ye shall be a peculiar treasure unto me above all people: for all the earth is mine: ^6and ye shall be unto me a kingdom of priests, and an holy nation. These are the words which thou shalt speak unto the children of Israel.

^7And Moses came and called for the elders of the people, and laid before their faces all these words which the Lord commanded him. ^8And all the people answered together, and said, All that the Lord hath spoken we will do. And Moses returned the words of the people unto the Lord. ^9And the Lord said unto Moses, Lo, I come unto thee in a thick cloud, that the people may hear when I speak with thee, and believe thee for ever. And Moses told the words of the people unto the Lord.

^10And the Lord said unto Moses, Go unto the people, and sanctify them to day and to morrow, and let them wash their clothes, ^11and be ready against the third day: for the third day the Lord will come down in the sight of all the people upon mount Sinai. ^12And thou shalt set bounds unto the people round about, saying, Take heed to yourselves, that ye go not up into the mount, or touch the border of it: whosoever toucheth the mount shall be surely put to death: ^13there shall not an hand touch it, but he shall surely be stoned, or shot through; whether it be beast or man, it shall not live: when the trumpet soundeth long, they shall come up to the mount.

^14And Moses went down from the mount unto the people, and sanctified the people; and they washed their clothes. ^15And he said unto the people, Be ready against the third day: come not at your wives.

^16And it came to pass on the third day in the morning, that there were thunders and lightnings, and a thick cloud upon the mount, and the voice of the trumpet exceeding loud; so that all the people that was in the camp trembled. ^17And Moses brought forth the people out of the camp to meet with God; and they stood at the nether part of the mount. ^18And mount Sinai was altogether on a smoke, because the Lord descended upon it in fire: and the smoke thereof ascended as the smoke of a furnace, and the whole mount quaked greatly. ^19And when the voice of the trumpet sounded long, and waxed louder and louder, Moses spake, and God answered him by a voice. ^20And the Lord came down upon mount Sinai, on the top of the mount: and the Lord called Moses up to the top of the mount; and Moses went up. ^21And the Lord said unto Moses, Go down, charge the people, lest they break through unto the Lord to gaze, and many of them perish. ^22And let the priests also, which come near to the Lord, sanctify themselves, lest the Lord break forth upon them. ^23And Moses said unto the Lord, The people cannot come up to mount Sinai: for thou chargedst us, saying, Set bounds about the mount, and sanctify it. ^24And the Lord said unto him, Away, get thee down, and thou shalt come up, thou, and Aaron with thee: but let not the priests and the people break through to come up unto the Lord, lest he break forth upon them. ^25So Moses went down unto the people, and spake unto them.

XX

^1And God spake all these words, saying,

^2I am the Lord thy God, which have brought thee out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage.

^3Thou shalt have no other gods before me.

^4Thou shalt not make unto thee any graven image, or any likeness of any thing that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth. ^5Thou shalt not bow down thyself to them, nor serve them: for I the Lord thy God am a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children unto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me; ^6and shewing mercy unto thousands of them that love me, and keep my commandments.

^7Thou shalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain; for the Lord will not hold him guiltless that taketh his name in vain.

^8Remember the sabbath day, to keep it holy. ^9Six days shalt thou labour, and do all thy work: ^10but the seventh day is the sabbath of the Lord thy God: in it thou shalt not do any work, thou, nor thy son, nor thy daughter, thy manservant, nor thy maidservant, nor thy cattle, nor thy stranger that is within thy gates: ^11for in six days the Lord made heaven and earth, the sea, and all that in them is, and rested the seventh day: wherefore the Lord blessed the sabbath day, and hallowed it.

^12Honour thy father and thy mother: that thy days may be long upon the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.

^13Thou shalt not kill.

^14Thou shalt not commit adultery.

^15Thou shalt not steal.

^16Thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbour.

^17Thou shalt not covet thy neighbour’s house, thou shalt not covet thy neighbour’s wife, nor his manservant, nor his maidservant, nor his ox, nor his ass, nor any thing that is thy neighbour’s.

^18And all the people saw the thunderings, and the lightnings, and the noise of the trumpet, and the mountain smoking: and when the people saw it, they removed, and stood afar off. ^19And they said unto Moses, Speak thou with us, and we will hear: but let not God speak with us, lest we die. ^20And Moses said unto the people, Fear not: for God is come to prove you, and that his fear may be before your faces, that ye sin not. ^21And the people stood afar off, and Moses drew near unto the thick darkness where God was.

^22And the Lord said unto Moses, Thus thou shalt say unto the children of Israel, Ye have seen that I have talked with you from heaven. ^23Ye shall not make with me gods of silver, neither shall ye make unto you gods of gold. ^24An altar of earth thou shalt make unto me, and shalt sacrifice thereon thy burnt offerings, and thy peace offerings, thy sheep, and thine oxen: in all places where I record my name I will come unto thee, and I will bless thee. ^25And if thou wilt make me an altar of stone, thou shalt not build it of hewn stone: for if thou lift up thy tool upon it, thou hast polluted it. ^26Neither shalt thou go up by steps unto mine altar, that thy nakedness be not discovered thereon.

XXI

^1Now these are the judgments which thou shalt set before them.

^2If thou buy an Hebrew servant, six years he shall serve: and in the seventh he shall go out free for nothing. ^3If he came in by himself, he shall go out by himself: if he were married, then his wife shall go out with him. ^4If his master have given him a wife, and she have born him sons or daughters; the wife and her children shall be her master’s, and he shall go out by himself. ^5And if the servant shall plainly say, I love my master, my wife, and my children; I will not go out free: ^6then his master shall bring him unto the judges; he shall also bring him to the door, or unto the door post; and his master shall bore his ear through with an aul; and he shall serve him for ever.

^7And if a man sell his daughter to be a maidservant, she shall not go out as the menservants do. ^8If she please not her master, who hath betrothed her to himself, then shall he let her be redeemed: to sell her unto a strange nation he shall have no power, seeing he hath dealt deceitfully with her. ^9And if he have betrothed her unto his son, he shall deal with her after the manner of daughters. ^10If he take him another wife; her food, her raiment, and her duty of marriage, shall he not diminish. ^11And if he do not these three unto her, then shall she go out free without money.

^12He that smiteth a man, so that he die, shall be surely put to death. ^13And if a man lie not in wait, but God deliver him into his hand; then I will appoint thee a place whither he shall flee. ^14But if a man come presumptuously upon his neighbour, to slay him with guile; thou shalt take him from mine altar, that he may die.

^15And he that smiteth his father, or his mother, shall be surely put to death.

^16And he that stealeth a man, and selleth him, or if he be found in his hand, he shall surely be put to death.

^17And he that curseth his father, or his mother, shall surely be put to death.

^18And if men strive together, and one smite another with a stone, or with his fist, and he die not, but keepeth his bed: ^19if he rise again, and walk abroad upon his staff, then shall he that smote him be quit: only he shall pay for the loss of his time, and shall cause him to be thoroughly healed.

^20And if a man smite his servant, or his maid, with a rod, and he die under his hand; he shall be surely punished. ^21Notwithstanding, if he continue a day or two, he shall not be punished: for he is his money.

^22If men strive, and hurt a woman with child, so that her fruit depart from her, and yet no mischief follow: he shall be surely punished, according as the woman’s husband will lay upon him; and he shall pay as the judges determine. ^23And if any mischief follow, then thou shalt give life for life, ^24eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot, ^25burning for burning, wound for wound, stripe for stripe.

^26And if a man smite the eye of his servant, or the eye of his maid, that it perish; he shall let him go free for his eye’s sake. ^27And if he smite out his manservant’s tooth, or his maidservant’s tooth; he shall let him go free for his tooth’s sake.

^28If an ox gore a man or a woman, that they die: then the ox shall be surely stoned, and his flesh shall not be eaten; but the owner of the ox shall be quit. ^29But if the ox were wont to push with his horn in time past, and it hath been testified to his owner, and he hath not kept him in, but that he hath killed a man or a woman; the ox shall be stoned, and his owner also shall be put to death. ^30If there be laid on him a sum of money, then he shall give for the ransom of his life whatsoever is laid upon him. ^31Whether he have gored a son, or have gored a daughter, according to this judgment shall it be done unto him. ^32If the ox shall push a manservant or a maidservant; he shall give unto their master thirty shekels of silver, and the ox shall be stoned.

^33And if a man shall open a pit, or if a man shall dig a pit, and not cover it, and an ox or an ass fall therein; ^34the owner of the pit shall make it good, and give money unto the owner of them; and the dead beast shall be his.

^35And if one man’s ox hurt another’s, that he die; then they shall sell the live ox, and divide the money of it; and the dead ox also they shall divide. ^36Or if it be known that the ox hath used to push in time past, and his owner hath not kept him in; he shall surely pay ox for ox; and the dead shall be his own.

XXII

^1If a man shall steal an ox, or a sheep, and kill it, or sell it; he shall restore five oxen for an ox, and four sheep for a sheep.

^2If a thief be found breaking up, and be smitten that he die, there shall no blood be shed for him. ^3If the sun be risen upon him, there shall be blood shed for him; for he should make full restitution; if he have nothing, then he shall be sold for his theft. ^4If the theft be certainly found in his hand alive, whether it be ox, or ass, or sheep; he shall restore double.

^5If a man shall cause a field or vineyard to be eaten, and shall put in his beast, and shall feed in another man’s field; of the best of his own field, and of the best of his own vineyard, shall he make restitution.

^6If fire break out, and catch in thorns, so that the stacks of corn, or the standing corn, or the field, be consumed therewith; he that kindled the fire shall surely make restitution.

^7If a man shall deliver unto his neighbour money or stuff to keep, and it be stolen out of the man’s house; if the thief be found, let him pay double. ^8If the thief be not found, then the master of the house shall be brought unto the judges, to see whether he have put his hand unto his neighbour’s goods. ^9For all manner of trespass, whether it be for ox, for ass, for sheep, for raiment, or for any manner of lost thing which another challengeth to be his, the cause of both parties shall come before the judges; and whom the judges shall condemn, he shall pay double unto his neighbour.

^10If a man deliver unto his neighbour an ass, or an ox, or a sheep, or any beast, to keep; and it die, or be hurt, or driven away, no man seeing it: ^11then shall an oath of the Lord be between them both, that he hath not put his hand unto his neighbour’s goods; and the owner of it shall accept thereof, and he shall not make it good. ^12And if it be stolen from him, he shall make restitution unto the owner thereof. ^13If it be torn in pieces, then let him bring it for witness, and he shall not make good that which was torn.

^14And if a man borrow ought of his neighbour, and it be hurt, or die, the owner thereof being not with it, he shall surely make it good. ^15But if the owner thereof be with it, he shall not make it good: if it be an hired thing, it came for his hire.

^16And if a man entice a maid that is not betrothed, and lie with her, he shall surely endow her to be his wife. ^17If her father utterly refuse to give her unto him, he shall pay money according to the dowry of virgins.

^18Thou shalt not suffer a witch to live.

^19Whosoever lieth with a beast shall surely be put to death.

^20He that sacrificeth unto any god, save unto the Lord only, he shall be utterly destroyed.

^21Thou shalt neither vex a stranger, nor oppress him: for ye were strangers in the land of Egypt.

^22Ye shall not afflict any widow, or fatherless child. ^23If thou afflict them in any wise, and they cry at all unto me, I will surely hear their cry; ^24and my wrath shall wax hot, and I will kill you with the sword; and your wives shall be widows, and your children fatherless.

^25If thou lend money to any of my people that is poor by thee, thou shalt not be to him as an usurer, neither shalt thou lay upon him usury. ^26If thou at all take thy neighbour’s raiment to pledge, thou shalt deliver it unto him by that the sun goeth down: ^27for that is his covering only, it is his raiment for his skin: wherein shall he sleep? and it shall come to pass, when he crieth unto me, that I will hear; for I am gracious.

^28Thou shalt not revile the gods, nor curse the ruler of thy people.

^29Thou shalt not delay to offer the first of thy ripe fruits, and of thy liquors: the firstborn of thy sons shalt thou give unto me. ^30Likewise shalt thou do with thine oxen, and with thy sheep: seven days it shall be with his dam; on the eighth day thou shalt give it me.

^31And ye shall be holy men unto me: neither shall ye eat any flesh that is torn of beasts in the field; ye shall cast it to the dogs.

XXIII

^1Thou shalt not raise a false report: put not thine hand with the wicked to be an unrighteous witness. ^2Thou shalt not follow a multitude to do evil; neither shalt thou speak in a cause to decline after many to wrest judgment: ^3neither shalt thou countenance a poor man in his cause.

^4If thou meet thine enemy’s ox or his ass going astray, thou shalt surely bring it back to him again. ^5If thou see the ass of him that hateth thee lying under his burden, and wouldest forbear to help him, thou shalt surely help with him.

^6Thou shalt not wrest the judgment of thy poor in his cause. ^7Keep thee far from a false matter; and the innocent and righteous slay thou not: for I will not justify the wicked. ^8And thou shalt take no gift: for the gift blindeth the wise, and perverteth the words of the righteous. ^9Also thou shalt not oppress a stranger: for ye know the heart of a stranger, seeing ye were strangers in the land of Egypt.

^10And six years thou shalt sow thy land, and shalt gather in the fruits thereof: ^11but the seventh year thou shalt let it rest and lie still; that the poor of thy people may eat: and what they leave the beasts of the field shall eat. In like manner thou shalt deal with thy vineyard, and with thy oliveyard. ^12Six days thou shalt do thy work, and on the seventh day thou shalt rest: that thine ox and thine ass may rest, and the son of thy handmaid, and the stranger, may be refreshed. ^13And in all things that I have said unto you be circumspect: and make no mention of the name of other gods, neither let it be heard out of thy mouth.

^14Three times thou shalt keep a feast unto me in the year. ^15Thou shalt keep the feast of unleavened bread: (thou shalt eat unleavened bread seven days, as I commanded thee, in the time appointed of the month Abib; for in it thou camest out from Egypt: and none shall appear before me empty:) ^16and the feast of harvest, the firstfruits of thy labours, which thou hast sown in the field: and the feast of ingathering, which is in the end of the year, when thou hast gathered in thy labours out of the field. ^17Three times in the year all thy males shall appear before the Lord God.

^18Thou shalt not offer the blood of my sacrifice with leavened bread; neither shall the fat of my sacrifice remain until the morning. ^19The first of the firstfruits of thy land thou shalt bring into the house of the Lord thy God. Thou shalt not seethe a kid in his mother’s milk.

^20Behold, I send an Angel before thee, to keep thee in the way, and to bring thee into the place which I have prepared. ^21Beware of him, and obey his voice, provoke him not; for he will not pardon your transgressions: for my name is in him. ^22But if thou shalt indeed obey his voice, and do all that I speak; then I will be an enemy unto thine enemies, and an adversary unto thine adversaries. ^23For mine Angel shall go before thee, and bring thee in unto the Amorites, and the Hittites, and the Perizzites, and the Canaanites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites: and I will cut them off. ^24Thou shalt not bow down to their gods, nor serve them, nor do after their works: but thou shalt utterly overthrow them, and quite break down their images. ^25And ye shall serve the Lord your God, and he shall bless thy bread, and thy water; and I will take sickness away from the midst of thee. ^26There shall nothing cast their young, nor be barren, in thy land: the number of thy days I will fulfil. ^27I will send my fear before thee, and will destroy all the people to whom thou shalt come, and I will make all thine enemies turn their backs unto thee. ^28And I will send hornets before thee, which shall drive out the Hivite, the Canaanite, and the Hittite, from before thee. ^29I will not drive them out from before thee in one year; lest the land become desolate, and the beast of the field multiply against thee. ^30By little and little I will drive them out from before thee, until thou be increased, and inherit the land. ^31And I will set thy bounds from the Red sea even unto the sea of the Philistines, and from the desert unto the river: for I will deliver the inhabitants of the land into your hand; and thou shalt drive them out before thee. ^32Thou shalt make no covenant with them, nor with their gods. ^33They shall not dwell in thy land, lest they make thee sin against me: for if thou serve their gods, it will surely be a snare unto thee.

XXIV

^1And he said unto Moses, Come up unto the Lord, thou, and Aaron, Nadab, and Abihu, and seventy of the elders of Israel; and worship ye afar off. ^2And Moses alone shall come near the Lord: but they shall not come nigh; neither shall the people go up with him.

^3And Moses came and told the people all the words of the Lord, and all the judgments: and all the people answered with one voice, and said, All the words which the Lord hath said will we do. ^4And Moses wrote all the words of the Lord, and rose up early in the morning, and builded an altar under the hill, and twelve pillars, according to the twelve tribes of Israel. ^5And he sent young men of the children of Israel, which offered burnt offerings, and sacrificed peace offerings of oxen unto the Lord. ^6And Moses took half of the blood, and put it in basons; and half of the blood he sprinkled on the altar. ^7And he took the book of the covenant, and read in the audience of the people: and they said, All that the Lord hath said will we do, and be obedient. ^8And Moses took the blood, and sprinkled it on the people, and said, Behold the blood of the covenant, which the Lord hath made with you concerning all these words.

^9Then went up Moses, and Aaron, Nadab, and Abihu, and seventy of the elders of Israel: ^10and they saw the God of Israel: and there was under his feet as it were a paved work of a sapphire stone, and as it were the body of heaven in his clearness. ^11And upon the nobles of the children of Israel he laid not his hand: also they saw God, and did eat and drink.

^12And the Lord said unto Moses, Come up to me into the mount, and be there: and I will give thee tables of stone, and a law, and commandments which I have written; that thou mayest teach them. ^13And Moses rose up, and his minister Joshua: and Moses went up into the mount of God. ^14And he said unto the elders, Tarry ye here for us, until we come again unto you: and, behold, Aaron and Hur are with you: if any man have any matters to do, let him come unto them. ^15And Moses went up into the mount, and a cloud covered the mount. ^16And the glory of the Lord abode upon mount Sinai, and the cloud covered it six days: and the seventh day he called unto Moses out of the midst of the cloud. ^17And the sight of the glory of the Lord was like devouring fire on the top of the mount in the eyes of the children of Israel. ^18And Moses went into the midst of the cloud, and gat him up into the mount: and Moses was in the mount forty days and forty nights.

XXV

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, that they bring me an offering: of every man that giveth it willingly with his heart ye shall take my offering. ^3And this is the offering which ye shall take of them; gold, and silver, and brass, ^4and blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine linen, and goats’ hair, ^5and rams’ skins dyed red, and badgers’ skins, and shittim wood, ^6oil for the light, spices for anointing oil, and for sweet incense, ^7onyx stones, and stones to be set in the ephod, and in the breastplate. ^8And let them make me a sanctuary; that I may dwell among them. ^9According to all that I shew thee, after the pattern of the tabernacle, and the pattern of all the instruments thereof, even so shall ye make it.

^10And they shall make an ark of shittim wood: two cubits and a half shall be the length thereof, and a cubit and a half the breadth thereof, and a cubit and a half the height thereof. ^11And thou shalt overlay it with pure gold, within and without shalt thou overlay it, and shalt make upon it a crown of gold round about. ^12And thou shalt cast four rings of gold for it, and put them in the four corners thereof; and two rings shall be in the one side of it, and two rings in the other side of it. ^13And thou shalt make staves of shittim wood, and overlay them with gold. ^14And thou shalt put the staves into the rings by the sides of the ark, that the ark may be borne with them. ^15The staves shall be in the rings of the ark: they shall not be taken from it. ^16And thou shalt put into the ark the testimony which I shall give thee. ^17And thou shalt make a mercy seat of pure gold: two cubits and a half shall be the length thereof, and a cubit and a half the breadth thereof. ^18And thou shalt make two cherubims of gold, of beaten work shalt thou make them, in the two ends of the mercy seat. ^19And make one cherub on the one end, and the other cherub on the other end: even of the mercy seat shall ye make the cherubims on the two ends thereof. ^20And the cherubims shall stretch forth their wings on high, covering the mercy seat with their wings, and their faces shall look one to another; toward the mercy seat shall the faces of the cherubims be. ^21And thou shalt put the mercy seat above upon the ark; and in the ark thou shalt put the testimony that I shall give thee. ^22And there I will meet with thee, and I will commune with thee from above the mercy seat, from between the two cherubims which are upon the ark of the testimony, of all things which I will give thee in commandment unto the children of Israel.

^23Thou shalt also make a table of shittim wood: two cubits shall be the length thereof, and a cubit the breadth thereof, and a cubit and a half the height thereof. ^24And thou shalt overlay it with pure gold, and make thereto a crown of gold round about. ^25And thou shalt make unto it a border of an hand breadth round about, and thou shalt make a golden crown to the border thereof round about. ^26And thou shalt make for it four rings of gold, and put the rings in the four corners that are on the four feet thereof. ^27Over against the border shall the rings be for places of the staves to bear the table. ^28And thou shalt make the staves of shittim wood, and overlay them with gold, that the table may be borne with them. ^29And thou shalt make the dishes thereof, and spoons thereof, and covers thereof, and bowls thereof, to cover withal: of pure gold shalt thou make them. ^30And thou shalt set upon the table shewbread before me alway.

^31And thou shalt make a candlestick of pure gold: of beaten work shall the candlestick be made: his shaft, and his branches, his bowls, his knops, and his flowers, shall be of the same. ^32And six branches shall come out of the sides of it; three branches of the candlestick out of the one side, and three branches of the candlestick out of the other side: ^33three bowls made like unto almonds, with a knop and a flower in one branch; and three bowls made like almonds in the other branch, with a knop and a flower: so in the six branches that come out of the candlestick. ^34And in the candlesticks shall be four bowls made like unto almonds, with their knops and their flowers. ^35And there shall be a knop under two branches of the same, and a knop under two branches of the same, and a knop under two branches of the same, according to the six branches that proceed out of the candlestick. ^36Their knops and their branches shall be of the same: all it shall be one beaten work of pure gold. ^37And thou shalt make the seven lamps thereof: and they shall light the lamps thereof, that they may give light over against it. ^38And the tongs thereof, and the snuffdishes thereof, shall be of pure gold. ^39Of a talent of pure gold shall he make it, with all these vessels. ^40And look that thou make them after their pattern, which was shewed thee in the mount.

XXVI

^1Moreover thou shalt make the tabernacle with ten curtains of fine twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet: with cherubims of cunning work shalt thou make them. ^2The length of one curtain shall be eight and twenty cubits, and the breadth of one curtain four cubits: and every one of the curtains shall have one measure. ^3The five curtains shall be coupled together one to another; and other five curtains shall be coupled one to another. ^4And thou shalt make loops of blue upon the edge of the one curtain from the selvedge in the coupling; and likewise shalt thou make in the uttermost edge of another curtain, in the coupling of the second. ^5Fifty loops shalt thou make in the one curtain, and fifty loops shalt thou make in the edge of the curtain that is in the coupling of the second; that the loops may take hold one of another. ^6And thou shalt make fifty taches of gold, and couple the curtains together with the taches: and it shall be one tabernacle.

^7And thou shalt make curtains of goats’ hair to be a covering upon the tabernacle: eleven curtains shalt thou make. ^8The length of one curtain shall be thirty cubits, and the breadth of one curtain four cubits: and the eleven curtains shall be all of one measure. ^9And thou shalt couple five curtains by themselves, and six curtains by themselves, and shalt double the sixth curtain in the forefront of the tabernacle. ^10And thou shalt make fifty loops on the edge of the one curtain that is outmost in the coupling, and fifty loops in the edge of the curtain which coupleth the second. ^11And thou shalt make fifty taches of brass, and put the taches into the loops, and couple the tent together, that it may be one. ^12And the remnant that remaineth of the curtains of the tent, the half curtain that remaineth, shall hang over the backside of the tabernacle. ^13And a cubit on the one side, and a cubit on the other side of that which remaineth in the length of the curtains of the tent, it shall hang over the sides of the tabernacle on this side and on that side, to cover it. ^14And thou shalt make a covering for the tent of rams’ skins dyed red, and a covering above of badgers’ skins.

^15And thou shalt make boards for the tabernacle of shittim wood standing up. ^16Ten cubits shall be the length of a board, and a cubit and a half shall be the breadth of one board. ^17Two tenons shall there be in one board, set in order one against another: thus shalt thou make for all the boards of the tabernacle. ^18And thou shalt make the boards for the tabernacle, twenty boards on the south side southward. ^19And thou shalt make forty sockets of silver under the twenty boards; two sockets under one board for his two tenons, and two sockets under another board for his two tenons. ^20And for the second side of the tabernacle on the north side there shall be twenty boards: ^21and their forty sockets of silver; two sockets under one board, and two sockets under another board. ^22And for the sides of the tabernacle westward thou shalt make six boards. ^23And two boards shalt thou make for the corners of the tabernacle in the two sides. ^24And they shall be coupled together beneath, and they shall be coupled together above the head of it unto one ring: thus shall it be for them both; they shall be for the two corners. ^25And they shall be eight boards, and their sockets of silver, sixteen sockets; two sockets under one board, and two sockets under another board.

^26And thou shalt make bars of shittim wood; five for the boards of the one side of the tabernacle, ^27and five bars for the boards of the other side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the boards of the side of the tabernacle, for the two sides westward. ^28And the middle bar in the midst of the boards shall reach from end to end. ^29And thou shalt overlay the boards with gold, and make their rings of gold for places for the bars: and thou shalt overlay the bars with gold. ^30And thou shalt rear up the tabernacle according to the fashion thereof which was shewed thee in the mount.

^31And thou shalt make a vail of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen of cunning work: with cherubims shall it be made: ^32and thou shalt hang it upon four pillars of shittim wood overlaid with gold: their hooks shall be of gold, upon the four sockets of silver. ^33And thou shalt hang up the vail under the taches, that thou mayest bring in thither within the vail the ark of the testimony: and the vail shall divide unto you between the holy place and the most holy. ^34And thou shalt put the mercy seat upon the ark of the testimony in the most holy place. ^35And thou shalt set the table without the vail, and the candlestick over against the table on the side of the tabernacle toward the south: and thou shalt put the table on the north side.

^36And thou shalt make an hanging for the door of the tent, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen, wrought with needlework. ^37And thou shalt make for the hanging five pillars of shittim wood, and overlay them with gold, and their hooks shall be of gold: and thou shalt cast five sockets of brass for them.

XXVII

^1And thou shalt make an altar of shittim wood, five cubits long, and five cubits broad; the altar shall be foursquare: and the height thereof shall be three cubits. ^2And thou shalt make the horns of it upon the four corners thereof: his horns shall be of the same: and thou shalt overlay it with brass. ^3And thou shalt make his pans to receive his ashes, and his shovels, and his basons, and his fleshhooks, and his firepans: all the vessels thereof thou shalt make of brass. ^4And thou shalt make for it a grate of network of brass; and upon the net shalt thou make four brasen rings in the four corners thereof. ^5And thou shalt put it under the compass of the altar beneath, that the net may be even to the midst of the altar. ^6And thou shalt make staves for the altar, staves of shittim wood, and overlay them with brass. ^7And the staves shall be put into the rings, and the staves shall be upon the two sides of the altar, to bear it. ^8Hollow with boards shalt thou make it: as it was shewed thee in the mount, so shall they make it.

^9And thou shalt make the court of the tabernacle: for the south side southward there shall be hangings for the court of fine twined linen of an hundred cubits long for one side: ^10and the twenty pillars thereof and their twenty sockets shall be of brass; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets shall be of silver. ^11And likewise for the north side in length there shall be hangings of an hundred cubits long, and his twenty pillars and their twenty sockets of brass; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets of silver. ^12And for the breadth of the court on the west side shall be hangings of fifty cubits: their pillars ten, and their sockets ten. ^13And the breadth of the court on the east side eastward shall be fifty cubits. ^14The hangings of one side of the gate shall be fifteen cubits: their pillars three, and their sockets three. ^15And on the other side shall be hangings fifteen cubits: their pillars three, and their sockets three. ^16And for the gate of the court shall be an hanging of twenty cubits, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen, wrought with needlework: and their pillars shall be four, and their sockets four. ^17All the pillars round about the court shall be filleted with silver; their hooks shall be of silver, and their sockets of brass. ^18The length of the court shall be an hundred cubits, and the breadth fifty every where, and the height five cubits of fine twined linen, and their sockets of brass. ^19All the vessels of the tabernacle in all the service thereof, and all the pins thereof, and all the pins of the court, shall be of brass.

^20And thou shalt command the children of Israel, that they bring thee pure oil olive beaten for the light, to cause the lamp to burn always. ^21In the tabernacle of the congregation without the vail, which is before the testimony, Aaron and his sons shall order it from evening to morning before the Lord: it shall be a statute for ever unto their generations on the behalf of the children of Israel.

XXVIII

^1And take thou unto thee Aaron thy brother, and his sons with him, from among the children of Israel, that he may minister unto me in the priest’s office, even Aaron, Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar, Aaron’s sons. ^2And thou shalt make holy garments for Aaron thy brother for glory and for beauty. ^3And thou shalt speak unto all that are wise hearted, whom I have filled with the spirit of wisdom, that they may make Aaron’s garments to consecrate him, that he may minister unto me in the priest’s office. ^4And these are the garments which they shall make; a breastplate, and an ephod, and a robe, and a broidered coat, a mitre, and a girdle: and they shall make holy garments for Aaron thy brother, and his sons, that he may minister unto me in the priest’s office. ^5And they shall take gold, and blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine linen.

^6And they shall make the ephod of gold, of blue, and of purple, of scarlet, and fine twined linen, with cunning work. ^7It shall have the two shoulderpieces thereof joined at the two edges thereof; and so it shall be joined together. ^8And the curious girdle of the ephod, which is upon it, shall be of the same, according to the work thereof; even of gold, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen. ^9And thou shalt take two onyx stones, and grave on them the names of the children of Israel: ^10six of their names on one stone, and the other six names of the rest on the other stone, according to their birth. ^11With the work of an engraver in stone, like the engravings of a signet, shalt thou engrave the two stones with the names of the children of Israel: thou shalt make them to be set in ouches of gold. ^12And thou shalt put the two stones upon the shoulders of the ephod for stones of memorial unto the children of Israel: and Aaron shall bear their names before the Lord upon his two shoulders for a memorial.

^13And thou shalt make ouches of gold; ^14and two chains of pure gold at the ends; of wreathen work shalt thou make them, and fasten the wreathen chains to the ouches.

^15And thou shalt make the breastplate of judgment with cunning work; after the work of the ephod thou shalt make it; of gold, of blue, and of purple, and of scarlet, and of fine twined linen, shalt thou make it. ^16Foursquare it shall be being doubled; a span shall be the length thereof, and a span shall be the breadth thereof. ^17And thou shalt set in it settings of stones, even four rows of stones: the first row shall be a sardius, a topaz, and a carbuncle: this shall be the first row. ^18And the second row shall be an emerald, a sapphire, and a diamond. ^19And the third row a ligure, an agate, and an amethyst. ^20And the fourth row a beryl, and an onyx, and a jasper: they shall be set in gold in their inclosings. ^21And the stones shall be with the names of the children of Israel, twelve, according to their names, like the engravings of a signet; every one with his name shall they be according to the twelve tribes.

^22And thou shalt make upon the breastplate chains at the ends of wreathen work of pure gold. ^23And thou shalt make upon the breastplate two rings of gold, and shalt put the two rings on the two ends of the breastplate. ^24And thou shalt put the two wreathen chains of gold in the two rings which are on the ends of the breastplate. ^25And the other two ends of the two wreathen chains thou shalt fasten in the two ouches, and put them on the shoulderpieces of the ephod before it.

^26And thou shalt make two rings of gold, and thou shalt put them upon the two ends of the breastplate in the border thereof, which is in the side of the ephod inward. ^27And two other rings of gold thou shalt make, and shalt put them on the two sides of the ephod underneath, toward the forepart thereof, over against the other coupling thereof, above the curious girdle of the ephod. ^28And they shall bind the breastplate by the rings thereof unto the rings of the ephod with a lace of blue, that it may be above the curious girdle of the ephod, and that the breastplate be not loosed from the ephod. ^29And Aaron shall bear the names of the children of Israel in the breastplate of judgment upon his heart, when he goeth in unto the holy place, for a memorial before the Lord continually.

^30And thou shalt put in the breastplate of judgment the Urim and the Thummim; and they shall be upon Aaron’s heart, when he goeth in before the Lord: and Aaron shall bear the judgment of the children of Israel upon his heart before the Lord continually.

^31And thou shalt make the robe of the ephod all of blue. ^32And there shall be an hole in the top of it, in the midst thereof: it shall have a binding of woven work round about the hole of it, as it were the hole of an habergeon, that it be not rent. ^33And beneath upon the hem of it thou shalt make pomegranates of blue, and of purple, and of scarlet, round about the hem thereof; and bells of gold between them round about: ^34a golden bell and a pomegranate, a golden bell and a pomegranate, upon the hem of the robe round about. ^35And it shall be upon Aaron to minister: and his sound shall be heard when he goeth in unto the holy place before the Lord, and when he cometh out, that he die not.

^36And thou shalt make a plate of pure gold, and grave upon it, like the engravings of a signet, Holiness to the Lord. ^37And thou shalt put it on a blue lace, that it may be upon the mitre; upon the forefront of the mitre it shall be. ^38And it shall be upon Aaron’s forehead, that Aaron may bear the iniquity of the holy things, which the children of Israel shall hallow in all their holy gifts; and it shall be always upon his forehead, that they may be accepted before the Lord. ^39And thou shalt embroider the coat of fine linen, and thou shalt make the mitre of fine linen, and thou shalt make the girdle of needlework.

^40And for Aaron’s sons thou shalt make coats, and thou shalt make for them girdles, and bonnets shalt thou make for them, for glory and for beauty. ^41And thou shalt put them upon Aaron thy brother, and his sons with him; and shalt anoint them, and consecrate them, and sanctify them, that they may minister unto me in the priest’s office. ^42And thou shalt make them linen breeches to cover their nakedness; from the loins even unto the thighs they shall reach: ^43and they shall be upon Aaron, and upon his sons, when they come in unto the tabernacle of the congregation, or when they come near unto the altar to minister in the holy place; that they bear not iniquity, and die: it shall be a statute for ever unto him and his seed after him.

XXIX

^1And this is the thing that thou shalt do unto them to hallow them, to minister unto me in the priest’s office: Take one young bullock, and two rams without blemish, ^2and unleavened bread, and cakes unleavened tempered with oil, and wafers unleavened anointed with oil: of wheaten flour shalt thou make them. ^3And thou shalt put them into one basket, and bring them in the basket, with the bullock and the two rams. ^4And Aaron and his sons thou shalt bring unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and shalt wash them with water. ^5And thou shalt take the garments, and put upon Aaron the coat, and the robe of the ephod, and the ephod, and the breastplate, and gird him with the curious girdle of the ephod: ^6and thou shalt put the mitre upon his head, and put the holy crown upon the mitre. ^7Then shalt thou take the anointing oil, and pour it upon his head, and anoint him. ^8And thou shalt bring his sons, and put coats upon them. ^9And thou shalt gird them with girdles, Aaron and his sons, and put the bonnets on them: and the priest’s office shall be theirs for a perpetual statute: and thou shalt consecrate Aaron and his sons.

^10And thou shalt cause a bullock to be brought before the tabernacle of the congregation: and Aaron and his sons shall put their hands upon the head of the bullock. ^11And thou shalt kill the bullock before the Lord, by the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. ^12And thou shalt take of the blood of the bullock, and put it upon the horns of the altar with thy finger, and pour all the blood beside the bottom of the altar. ^13And thou shalt take all the fat that covereth the inwards, and the caul that is above the liver, and the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, and burn them upon the altar. ^14But the flesh of the bullock, and his skin, and his dung, shalt thou burn with fire without the camp: it is a sin offering.

^15Thou shalt also take one ram; and Aaron and his sons shall put their hands upon the head of the ram. ^16And thou shalt slay the ram, and thou shalt take his blood, and sprinkle it round about upon the altar. ^17And thou shalt cut the ram in pieces, and wash the inwards of him, and his legs, and put them unto his pieces, and unto his head. ^18And thou shalt burn the whole ram upon the altar: it is a burnt offering unto the Lord: it is a sweet savour, an offering made by fire unto the Lord.

^19And thou shalt take the other ram; and Aaron and his sons shall put their hands upon the head of the ram. ^20Then shalt thou kill the ram, and take of his blood, and put it upon the tip of the right ear of Aaron, and upon the tip of the right ear of his sons, and upon the thumb of their right hand, and upon the great toe of their right foot, and sprinkle the blood upon the altar round about. ^21And thou shalt take of the blood that is upon the altar, and of the anointing oil, and sprinkle it upon Aaron, and upon his garments, and upon his sons, and upon the garments of his sons with him: and he shall be hallowed, and his garments, and his sons, and his sons’ garments with him. ^22Also thou shalt take of the ram the fat and the rump, and the fat that covereth the inwards, and the caul above the liver, and the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, and the right shoulder; for it is a ram of consecration: ^23and one loaf of bread, and one cake of oiled bread, and one wafer out of the basket of the unleavened bread that is before the Lord: ^24and thou shalt put all in the hands of Aaron, and in the hands of his sons; and shalt wave them for a wave offering before the Lord. ^25And thou shalt receive them of their hands, and burn them upon the altar for a burnt offering, for a sweet savour before the Lord: it is an offering made by fire unto the Lord.

^26And thou shalt take the breast of the ram of Aaron’s consecration, and wave it for a wave offering before the Lord: and it shall be thy part. ^27And thou shalt sanctify the breast of the wave offering, and the shoulder of the heave offering, which is waved, and which is heaved up, of the ram of the consecration, even of that which is for Aaron, and of that which is for his sons: ^28and it shall be Aaron’s and his sons’ by a statute for ever from the children of Israel: for it is an heave offering: and it shall be an heave offering from the children of Israel of the sacrifice of their peace offerings, even their heave offering unto the Lord.

^29And the holy garments of Aaron shall be his sons’ after him, to be anointed therein, and to be consecrated in them. ^30And that son that is priest in his stead shall put them on seven days, when he cometh into the tabernacle of the congregation to minister in the holy place.

^31And thou shalt take the ram of the consecration, and seethe his flesh in the holy place. ^32And Aaron and his sons shall eat the flesh of the ram, and the bread that is in the basket by the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. ^33And they shall eat those things wherewith the atonement was made, to consecrate and to sanctify them: but a stranger shall not eat thereof, because they are holy. ^34And if ought of the flesh of the consecrations, or of the bread, remain unto the morning, then thou shalt burn the remainder with fire: it shall not be eaten, because it is holy.

^35And thus shalt thou do unto Aaron, and to his sons, according to all things which I have commanded thee: seven days shalt thou consecrate them. ^36And thou shalt offer every day a bullock for a sin offering for atonement: and thou shalt cleanse the altar, when thou hast made an atonement for it, and thou shalt anoint it, to sanctify it. ^37Seven days thou shalt make an atonement for the altar, and sanctify it; and it shall be an altar most holy: whatsoever toucheth the altar shall be holy.

^38Now this is that which thou shalt offer upon the altar; two lambs of the first year day by day continually. ^39The one lamb thou shalt offer in the morning; and the other lamb thou shalt offer at even: ^40and with the one lamb a tenth deal of flour mingled with the fourth part of an hin of beaten oil; and the fourth part of an hin of wine for a drink offering. ^41And the other lamb thou shalt offer at even, and shalt do thereto according to the meat offering of the morning, and according to the drink offering thereof, for a sweet savour, an offering made by fire unto the Lord. ^42This shall be a continual burnt offering throughout your generations at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation before the Lord: where I will meet you, to speak there unto thee. ^43And there I will meet with the children of Israel, and the tabernacle shall be sanctified by my glory. ^44And I will sanctify the tabernacle of the congregation, and the altar: I will sanctify also both Aaron and his sons, to minister to me in the priest’s office. ^45And I will dwell among the children of Israel, and will be their God. ^46And they shall know that I am the Lord their God, that brought them forth out of the land of Egypt, that I may dwell among them: I am the Lord their God.

XXX

^1And thou shalt make an altar to burn incense upon: of shittim wood shalt thou make it. ^2A cubit shall be the length thereof, and a cubit the breadth thereof; foursquare shall it be: and two cubits shall be the height thereof: the horns thereof shall be of the same. ^3And thou shalt overlay it with pure gold, the top thereof, and the sides thereof round about, and the horns thereof; and thou shalt make unto it a crown of gold round about. ^4And two golden rings shalt thou make to it under the crown of it, by the two corners thereof, upon the two sides of it shalt thou make it; and they shall be for places for the staves to bear it withal. ^5And thou shalt make the staves of shittim wood, and overlay them with gold. ^6And thou shalt put it before the vail that is by the ark of the testimony, before the mercy seat that is over the testimony, where I will meet with thee. ^7And Aaron shall burn thereon sweet incense every morning: when he dresseth the lamps, he shall burn incense upon it. ^8And when Aaron lighteth the lamps at even, he shall burn incense upon it, a perpetual incense before the Lord throughout your generations. ^9Ye shall offer no strange incense thereon, nor burnt sacrifice, nor meat offering; neither shall ye pour drink offering thereon. ^10And Aaron shall make an atonement upon the horns of it once in a year with the blood of the sin offering of atonements: once in the year shall he make atonement upon it throughout your generations: it is most holy unto the Lord.

^11And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^12When thou takest the sum of the children of Israel after their number, then shall they give every man a ransom for his soul unto the Lord, when thou numberest them; that there be no plague among them, when thou numberest them. ^13This they shall give, every one that passeth among them that are numbered, half a shekel after the shekel of the sanctuary: (a shekel is twenty gerahs:) an half shekel shall be the offering of the Lord. ^14Every one that passeth among them that are numbered, from twenty years old and above, shall give an offering unto the Lord. ^15The rich shall not give more, and the poor shall not give less than half a shekel, when they give an offering unto the Lord, to make an atonement for your souls. ^16And thou shalt take the atonement money of the children of Israel, and shalt appoint it for the service of the tabernacle of the congregation; that it may be a memorial unto the children of Israel before the Lord, to make an atonement for your souls.

^17And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^18Thou shalt also make a laver of brass, and his foot also of brass, to wash withal: and thou shalt put it between the tabernacle of the congregation and the altar, and thou shalt put water therein. ^19For Aaron and his sons shall wash their hands and their feet thereat: ^20when they go into the tabernacle of the congregation, they shall wash with water, that they die not; or when they come near to the altar to minister, to burn offering made by fire unto the Lord: ^21so they shall wash their hands and their feet, that they die not: and it shall be a statute for ever to them, even to him and to his seed throughout their generations.

^22Moreover the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^23Take thou also unto thee principal spices, of pure myrrh five hundred shekels, and of sweet cinnamon half so much, even two hundred and fifty shekels, and of sweet calamus two hundred and fifty shekels, ^24and of cassia five hundred shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary, and of oil olive an hin: ^25and thou shalt make it an oil of holy ointment, an ointment compound after the art of the apothecary: it shall be an holy anointing oil. ^26And thou shalt anoint the tabernacle of the congregation therewith, and the ark of the testimony, ^27and the table and all his vessels, and the candlestick and his vessels, and the altar of incense, ^28and the altar of burnt offering with all his vessels, and the laver and his foot. ^29And thou shalt sanctify them, that they may be most holy: whatsoever toucheth them shall be holy. ^30And thou shalt anoint Aaron and his sons, and consecrate them, that they may minister unto me in the priest’s office. ^31And thou shalt speak unto the children of Israel, saying, This shall be an holy anointing oil unto me throughout your generations. ^32Upon man’s flesh shall it not be poured, neither shall ye make any other like it, after the composition of it: it is holy, and it shall be holy unto you. ^33Whosoever compoundeth any like it, or whosoever putteth any of it upon a stranger, shall even be cut off from his people.

^34And the Lord said unto Moses, Take unto thee sweet spices, stacte, and onycha, and galbanum; these sweet spices with pure frankincense: of each shall there be a like weight: ^35and thou shalt make it a perfume, a confection after the art of the apothecary, tempered together, pure and holy: ^36and thou shalt beat some of it very small, and put of it before the testimony in the tabernacle of the congregation, where I will meet with thee: it shall be unto you most holy. ^37And as for the perfume which thou shalt make, ye shall not make to yourselves according to the composition thereof: it shall be unto thee holy for the Lord. ^38Whosoever shall make like unto that, to smell thereto, shall even be cut off from his people.

XXXI

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2See, I have called by name Bezaleel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah: ^3and I have filled him with the spirit of God, in wisdom, and in understanding, and in knowledge, and in all manner of workmanship, ^4to devise cunning works, to work in gold, and in silver, and in brass, ^5and in cutting of stones, to set them, and in carving of timber, to work in all manner of workmanship. ^6And I, behold, I have given with him Aholiab, the son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan: and in the hearts of all that are wise hearted I have put wisdom, that they may make all that I have commanded thee; ^7the tabernacle of the congregation, and the ark of the testimony, and the mercy seat that is thereupon, and all the furniture of the tabernacle, ^8and the table and his furniture, and the pure candlestick with all his furniture, and the altar of incense, ^9and the altar of burnt offering with all his furniture, and the laver and his foot, ^10and the cloths of service, and the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons, to minister in the priest’s office, ^11and the anointing oil, and sweet incense for the holy place: according to all that I have commanded thee shall they do.

^12And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^13Speak thou also unto the children of Israel, saying, Verily my sabbaths ye shall keep: for it is a sign between me and you throughout your generations; that ye may know that I am the Lord that doth sanctify you. ^14Ye shall keep the sabbath therefore; for it is holy unto you: every one that defileth it shall surely be put to death: for whosoever doeth any work therein, that soul shall be cut off from among his people. ^15Six days may work be done; but in the seventh is the sabbath of rest, holy to the Lord: whosoever doeth any work in the sabbath day, he shall surely be put to death. ^16Wherefore the children of Israel shall keep the sabbath, to observe the sabbath throughout their generations, for a perpetual covenant. ^17It is a sign between me and the children of Israel for ever: for in six days the Lord made heaven and earth, and on the seventh day he rested, and was refreshed.

^18And he gave unto Moses, when he had made an end of communing with him upon mount Sinai, two tables of testimony, tables of stone, written with the finger of God.

XXXII

^1And when the people saw that Moses delayed to come down out of the mount, the people gathered themselves together unto Aaron, and said unto him, Up, make us gods, which shall go before us; for as for this Moses, the man that brought us up out of the land of Egypt, we wot not what is become of him. ^2And Aaron said unto them, Break off the golden earrings, which are in the ears of your wives, of your sons, and of your daughters, and bring them unto me. ^3And all the people brake off the golden earrings which were in their ears, and brought them unto Aaron. ^4And he received them at their hand, and fashioned it with a graving tool, after he had made it a molten calf: and they said, These be thy gods, O Israel, which brought thee up out of the land of Egypt. ^5And when Aaron saw it, he built an altar before it; and Aaron made proclamation, and said, To morrow is a feast to the Lord. ^6And they rose up early on the morrow, and offered burnt offerings, and brought peace offerings; and the people sat down to eat and to drink, and rose up to play.

^7And the Lord said unto Moses, Go, get thee down; for thy people, which thou broughtest out of the land of Egypt, have corrupted themselves: ^8they have turned aside quickly out of the way which I commanded them: they have made them a molten calf, and have worshipped it, and have sacrificed thereunto, and said, These be thy gods, O Israel, which have brought thee up out of the land of Egypt. ^9And the Lord said unto Moses, I have seen this people, and, behold, it is a stiffnecked people: ^10now therefore let me alone, that my wrath may wax hot against them, and that I may consume them: and I will make of thee a great nation. ^11And Moses besought the Lord his God, and said, Lord, why doth thy wrath wax hot against thy people, which thou hast brought forth out of the land of Egypt with great power, and with a mighty hand? ^12Wherefore should the Egyptians speak, and say, For mischief did he bring them out, to slay them in the mountains, and to consume them from the face of the earth? Turn from thy fierce wrath, and repent of this evil against thy people. ^13Remember Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, thy servants, to whom thou swarest by thine own self, and saidst unto them, I will multiply your seed as the stars of heaven, and all this land that I have spoken of will I give unto your seed, and they shall inherit it for ever. ^14And the Lord repented of the evil which he thought to do unto his people.

^15And Moses turned, and went down from the mount, and the two tables of the testimony were in his hand: the tables were written on both their sides; on the one side and on the other were they written. ^16And the tables were the work of God, and the writing was the writing of God, graven upon the tables. ^17And when Joshua heard the noise of the people as they shouted, he said unto Moses, There is a noise of war in the camp. ^18And he said, It is not the voice of them that shout for mastery, neither is it the voice of them that cry for being overcome: but the noise of them that sing do I hear.

^19And it came to pass, as soon as he came nigh unto the camp, that he saw the calf, and the dancing: and Moses’ anger waxed hot, and he cast the tables out of his hands, and brake them beneath the mount. ^20And he took the calf which they had made, and burnt it in the fire, and ground it to powder, and strawed it upon the water, and made the children of Israel drink of it. ^21And Moses said unto Aaron, What did this people unto thee, that thou hast brought so great a sin upon them? ^22And Aaron said, Let not the anger of my lord wax hot: thou knowest the people, that they are set on mischief. ^23For they said unto me, Make us gods, which shall go before us: for as for this Moses, the man that brought us up out of the land of Egypt, we wot not what is become of him. ^24And I said unto them, Whosoever hath any gold, let them break it off. So they gave it me: then I cast it into the fire, and there came out this calf.

^25And when Moses saw that the people were naked; (for Aaron had made them naked unto their shame among their enemies:) ^26then Moses stood in the gate of the camp, and said, Who is on the Lord’s side? let him come unto me. And all the sons of Levi gathered themselves together unto him. ^27And he said unto them, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, Put every man his sword by his side, and go in and out from gate to gate throughout the camp, and slay every man his brother, and every man his companion, and every man his neighbour. ^28And the children of Levi did according to the word of Moses: and there fell of the people that day about three thousand men. ^29For Moses had said, Consecrate yourselves today to the Lord, even every man upon his son, and upon his brother; that he may bestow upon you a blessing this day.

^30And it came to pass on the morrow, that Moses said unto the people, Ye have sinned a great sin: and now I will go up unto the Lord; peradventure I shall make an atonement for your sin. ^31And Moses returned unto the Lord, and said, Oh, this people have sinned a great sin, and have made them gods of gold. ^32Yet now, if thou wilt forgive their sin—; and if not, blot me, I pray thee, out of thy book which thou hast written. ^33And the Lord said unto Moses, Whosoever hath sinned against me, him will I blot out of my book. ^34Therefore now go, lead the people unto the place of which I have spoken unto thee: behold, mine Angel shall go before thee: nevertheless in the day when I visit I will visit their sin upon them. ^35And the Lord plagued the people, because they made the calf, which Aaron made.

XXXIII

^1And the Lord said unto Moses, Depart, and go up hence, thou and the people which thou hast brought up out of the land of Egypt, unto the land which I sware unto Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, saying, Unto thy seed will I give it: ^2and I will send an angel before thee; and I will drive out the Canaanite, the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite: ^3unto a land flowing with milk and honey: for I will not go up in the midst of thee; for thou art a stiffnecked people: lest I consume thee in the way.

^4And when the people heard these evil tidings, they mourned: and no man did put on him his ornaments. ^5For the Lord had said unto Moses, Say unto the children of Israel, Ye are a stiffnecked people: I will come up into the midst of thee in a moment, and consume thee: therefore now put off thy ornaments from thee, that I may know what to do unto thee. ^6And the children of Israel stripped themselves of their ornaments by the mount Horeb.

^7And Moses took the tabernacle, and pitched it without the camp, afar off from the camp, and called it the Tabernacle of the congregation. And it came to pass, that every one which sought the Lord went out unto the tabernacle of the congregation, which was without the camp. ^8And it came to pass, when Moses went out unto the tabernacle, that all the people rose up, and stood every man at his tent door, and looked after Moses, until he was gone into the tabernacle. ^9And it came to pass, as Moses entered into the tabernacle, the cloudy pillar descended, and stood at the door of the tabernacle, and the Lord talked with Moses. ^10And all the people saw the cloudy pillar stand at the tabernacle door: and all the people rose up and worshipped, every man in his tent door. ^11And the Lord spake unto Moses face to face, as a man speaketh unto his friend. And he turned again into the camp: but his servant Joshua, the son of Nun, a young man, departed not out of the tabernacle.

^12And Moses said unto the Lord, See, thou sayest unto me, Bring up this people: and thou hast not let me know whom thou wilt send with me. Yet thou hast said, I know thee by name, and thou hast also found grace in my sight. ^13Now therefore, I pray thee, if I have found grace in thy sight, shew me now thy way, that I may know thee, that I may find grace in thy sight: and consider that this nation is thy people. ^14And he said, My presence shall go with thee, and I will give thee rest. ^15And he said unto him, If thy presence go not with me, carry us not up hence. ^16For wherein shall it be known here that I and thy people have found grace in thy sight? is it not in that thou goest with us? so shall we be separated, I and thy people, from all the people that are upon the face of the earth.

^17And the Lord said unto Moses, I will do this thing also that thou hast spoken: for thou hast found grace in my sight, and I know thee by name. ^18And he said, I beseech thee, shew me thy glory. ^19And he said, I will make all my goodness pass before thee, and I will proclaim the name of the Lord before thee; and will be gracious to whom I will be gracious, and will shew mercy on whom I will shew mercy. ^20And he said, Thou canst not see my face: for there shall no man see me, and live. ^21And the Lord said, Behold, there is a place by me, and thou shalt stand upon a rock: ^22and it shall come to pass, while my glory passeth by, that I will put thee in a clift of the rock, and will cover thee with my hand while I pass by: ^23and I will take away mine hand, and thou shalt see my back parts: but my face shall not be seen.

XXXIV

^1And the Lord said unto Moses, Hew thee two tables of stone like unto the first: and I will write upon these tables the words that were in the first tables, which thou brakest. ^2And be ready in the morning, and come up in the morning unto mount Sinai, and present thyself there to me in the top of the mount. ^3And no man shall come up with thee, neither let any man be seen throughout all the mount; neither let the flocks nor herds feed before that mount.

^4And he hewed two tables of stone like unto the first; and Moses rose up early in the morning, and went up unto mount Sinai, as the Lord had commanded him, and took in his hand the two tables of stone. ^5And the Lord descended in the cloud, and stood with him there, and proclaimed the name of the Lord. ^6And the Lord passed by before him, and proclaimed, The Lord, The Lord God, merciful and gracious, longsuffering, and abundant in goodness and truth, ^7keeping mercy for thousands, forgiving iniquity and transgression and sin, and that will by no means clear the guilty; visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children, and upon the children’s children, unto the third and to the fourth generation. ^8And Moses made haste, and bowed his head toward the earth, and worshipped. ^9And he said, If now I have found grace in thy sight, O Lord, let my Lord, I pray thee, go among us; for it is a stiffnecked people; and pardon our iniquity and our sin, and take us for thine inheritance.

^10And he said, Behold, I make a covenant: before all thy people I will do marvels, such as have not been done in all the earth, nor in any nation: and all the people among which thou art shall see the work of the Lord: for it is a terrible thing that I will do with thee. ^11Observe thou that which I command thee this day: behold, I drive out before thee the Amorite, and the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite. ^12Take heed to thyself, lest thou make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land whither thou goest, lest it be for a snare in the midst of thee: ^13but ye shall destroy their altars, break their images, and cut down their groves: ^14for thou shalt worship no other god: for the Lord, whose name is Jealous, is a jealous God: ^15lest thou make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land, and they go a whoring after their gods, and do sacrifice unto their gods, and one call thee, and thou eat of his sacrifice; ^16and thou take of their daughters unto thy sons, and their daughters go a whoring after their gods, and make thy sons go a whoring after their gods. ^17Thou shalt make thee no molten gods.

^18The feast of unleavened bread shalt thou keep. Seven days thou shalt eat unleavened bread, as I commanded thee, in the time of the month Abib: for in the month Abib thou camest out from Egypt. ^19All that openeth the matrix is mine; and every firstling among thy cattle, whether ox or sheep, that is male. ^20But the firstling of an ass thou shalt redeem with a lamb: and if thou redeem him not, then shalt thou break his neck. All the firstborn of thy sons thou shalt redeem. And none shall appear before me empty.

^21Six days thou shalt work, but on the seventh day thou shalt rest: in earing time and in harvest thou shalt rest. ^22And thou shalt observe the feast of weeks, of the firstfruits of wheat harvest, and the feast of ingathering at the year’s end. ^23Thrice in the year shall all your menchildren appear before the Lord God, the God of Israel. ^24For I will cast out the nations before thee, and enlarge thy borders: neither shall any man desire thy land, when thou shalt go up to appear before the Lord thy God thrice in the year.

^25Thou shalt not offer the blood of my sacrifice with leaven; neither shall the sacrifice of the feast of the passover be left unto the morning. ^26The first of the firstfruits of thy land thou shalt bring unto the house of the Lord thy God. Thou shalt not seethe a kid in his mother’s milk.

^27And the Lord said unto Moses, Write thou these words: for after the tenor of these words I have made a covenant with thee and with Israel. ^28And he was there with the Lord forty days and forty nights; he did neither eat bread, nor drink water. And he wrote upon the tables the words of the covenant, the ten commandments.

^29And it came to pass, when Moses came down from mount Sinai with the two tables of testimony in Moses’ hand, when he came down from the mount, that Moses wist not that the skin of his face shone while he talked with him. ^30And when Aaron and all the children of Israel saw Moses, behold, the skin of his face shone; and they were afraid to come nigh him. ^31And Moses called unto them; and Aaron and all the rulers of the congregation returned unto him: and Moses talked with them. ^32And afterward all the children of Israel came nigh: and he gave them in commandment all that the Lord had spoken with him in mount Sinai. ^33And till Moses had done speaking with them, he put a vail on his face. ^34But when Moses went in before the Lord to speak with him, he took the vail off, until he came out. And he came out, and spake unto the children of Israel that which he was commanded. ^35And the children of Israel saw the face of Moses, that the skin of Moses’ face shone: and Moses put the vail upon his face again, until he went in to speak with him.

XXXV

^1And Moses gathered all the congregation of the children of Israel together, and said unto them, These are the words which the Lord hath commanded, that ye should do them. ^2Six days shall work be done, but on the seventh day there shall be to you an holy day, a sabbath of rest to the Lord: whosoever doeth work therein shall be put to death. ^3Ye shall kindle no fire throughout your habitations upon the sabbath day.

^4And Moses spake unto all the congregation of the children of Israel, saying, This is the thing which the Lord commanded, saying, ^5Take ye from among you an offering unto the Lord: whosoever is of a willing heart, let him bring it, an offering of the Lord; gold, and silver, and brass, ^6and blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine linen, and goats’ hair, ^7and rams’ skins dyed red, and badgers’ skins, and shittim wood, ^8and oil for the light, and spices for anointing oil, and for the sweet incense, ^9and onyx stones, and stones to be set for the ephod, and for the breastplate.

^10And every wise hearted among you shall come, and make all that the Lord hath commanded; ^11the tabernacle, his tent, and his covering, his taches, and his boards, his bars, his pillars, and his sockets, ^12the ark, and the staves thereof, with the mercy seat, and the vail of the covering, ^13the table, and his staves, and all his vessels, and the shewbread, ^14the candlestick also for the light, and his furniture, and his lamps, with the oil for the light, ^15and the incense altar, and his staves, and the anointing oil, and the sweet incense, and the hanging for the door at the entering in of the tabernacle, ^16the altar of burnt offering, with his brasen grate, his staves, and all his vessels, the laver and his foot, ^17the hangings of the court, his pillars, and their sockets, and the hanging for the door of the court, ^18the pins of the tabernacle, and the pins of the court, and their cords, ^19the cloths of service, to do service in the holy place, the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons, to minister in the priest’s office.

^20And all the congregation of the children of Israel departed from the presence of Moses. ^21And they came, every one whose heart stirred him up, and every one whom his spirit made willing, and they brought the Lord’s offering to the work of the tabernacle of the congregation, and for all his service, and for the holy garments. ^22And they came, both men and women, as many as were willing hearted, and brought bracelets, and earrings, and rings, and tablets, all jewels of gold: and every man that offered offered an offering of gold unto the Lord. ^23And every man, with whom was found blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine linen, and goats’ hair, and red skins of rams, and badgers’ skins, brought them. ^24Every one that did offer an offering of silver and brass brought the Lord’s offering: and every man, with whom was found shittim wood for any work of the service, brought it. ^25And all the women that were wise hearted did spin with their hands, and brought that which they had spun, both of blue, and of purple, and of scarlet, and of fine linen. ^26And all the women whose heart stirred them up in wisdom spun goats’ hair. ^27And the rulers brought onyx stones, and stones to be set, for the ephod, and for the breastplate; ^28and spice, and oil for the light, and for the anointing oil, and for the sweet incense. ^29The children of Israel brought a willing offering unto the Lord, every man and woman, whose heart made them willing to bring for all manner of work, which the Lord had commanded to be made by the hand of Moses.

^30And Moses said unto the children of Israel, See, the Lord hath called by name Bezaleel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah; ^31and he hath filled him with the spirit of God, in wisdom, in understanding, and in knowledge, and in all manner of workmanship; ^32and to devise curious works, to work in gold, and in silver, and in brass, ^33and in the cutting of stones, to set them, and in carving of wood, to make any manner of cunning work. ^34And he hath put in his heart that he may teach, both he, and Aholiab, the son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan. ^35Them hath he filled with wisdom of heart, to work all manner of work, of the engraver, and of the cunning workman, and of the embroiderer, in blue, and in purple, in scarlet, and in fine linen, and of the weaver, even of them that do any work, and of those that devise cunning work.

XXXVI

^1Then wrought Bezaleel and Aholiab, and every wise hearted man, in whom the Lord put wisdom and understanding to know how to work all manner of work for the service of the sanctuary, according to all that the Lord had commanded.

^2And Moses called Bezaleel and Aholiab, and every wise hearted man, in whose heart the Lord had put wisdom, even every one whose heart stirred him up to come unto the work to do it: ^3and they received of Moses all the offering, which the children of Israel had brought for the work of the service of the sanctuary, to make it withal. And they brought yet unto him free offerings every morning. ^4And all the wise men, that wrought all the work of the sanctuary, came every man from his work which they made; ^5and they spake unto Moses, saying, The people bring much more than enough for the service of the work, which the Lord commanded to make. ^6And Moses gave commandment, and they caused it to be proclaimed throughout the camp, saying, Let neither man nor woman make any more work for the offering of the sanctuary. So the people were restrained from bringing. ^7For the stuff they had was sufficient for all the work to make it, and too much.

^8And every wise hearted man among them that wrought the work of the tabernacle made ten curtains of fine twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet: with cherubims of cunning work made he them. ^9The length of one curtain was twenty and eight cubits, and the breadth of one curtain four cubits: the curtains were all of one size. ^10And he coupled the five curtains one unto another: and the other five curtains he coupled one unto another. ^11And he made loops of blue on the edge of one curtain from the selvedge in the coupling: likewise he made in the uttermost side of another curtain, in the coupling of the second. ^12Fifty loops made he in one curtain, and fifty loops made he in the edge of the curtain which was in the coupling of the second: the loops held one curtain to another. ^13And he made fifty taches of gold, and coupled the curtains one unto another with the taches: so it became one tabernacle.

^14And he made curtains of goats’ hair for the tent over the tabernacle: eleven curtains he made them. ^15The length of one curtain was thirty cubits, and four cubits was the breadth of one curtain: the eleven curtains were of one size. ^16And he coupled five curtains by themselves, and six curtains by themselves. ^17And he made fifty loops upon the uttermost edge of the curtain in the coupling, and fifty loops made he upon the edge of the curtain which coupleth the second. ^18And he made fifty taches of brass to couple the tent together, that it might be one. ^19And he made a covering for the tent of rams’ skins dyed red, and a covering of badgers’ skins above that.

^20And he made boards for the tabernacle of shittim wood, standing up. ^21The length of a board was ten cubits, and the breadth of a board one cubit and a half. ^22One board had two tenons, equally distant one from another: thus did he make for all the boards of the tabernacle. ^23And he made boards for the tabernacle; twenty boards for the south side southward: ^24and forty sockets of silver he made under the twenty boards; two sockets under one board for his two tenons, and two sockets under another board for his two tenons. ^25And for the other side of the tabernacle, which is toward the north corner, he made twenty boards, ^26and their forty sockets of silver; two sockets under one board, and two sockets under another board. ^27And for the sides of the tabernacle westward he made six boards. ^28And two boards made he for the corners of the tabernacle in the two sides. ^29And they were coupled beneath, and coupled together at the head thereof, to one ring: thus he did to both of them in both the corners. ^30And there were eight boards; and their sockets were sixteen sockets of silver, under every board two sockets.

^31And he made bars of shittim wood; five for the boards of the one side of the tabernacle, ^32and five bars for the boards of the other side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the boards of the tabernacle for the sides westward. ^33And he made the middle bar to shoot through the boards from the one end to the other. ^34And he overlaid the boards with gold, and made their rings of gold to be places for the bars, and overlaid the bars with gold.

^35And he made a vail of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen: with cherubims made he it of cunning work. ^36And he made thereunto four pillars of shittim wood, and overlaid them with gold: their hooks were of gold; and he cast for them four sockets of silver. ^37And he made an hanging for the tabernacle door of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen, of needlework; ^38and the five pillars of it with their hooks: and he overlaid their chapiters and their fillets with gold: but their five sockets were of brass.

XXXVII

^1And Bezaleel made the ark of shittim wood: two cubits and a half was the length of it, and a cubit and a half the breadth of it, and a cubit and a half the height of it: ^2and he overlaid it with pure gold within and without, and made a crown of gold to it round about. ^3And he cast for it four rings of gold, to be set by the four corners of it; even two rings upon the one side of it, and two rings upon the other side of it. ^4And he made staves of shittim wood, and overlaid them with gold. ^5And he put the staves into the rings by the sides of the ark, to bear the ark.

^6And he made the mercy seat of pure gold: two cubits and a half was the length thereof, and one cubit and a half the breadth thereof. ^7And he made two cherubims of gold, beaten out of one piece made he them, on the two ends of the mercy seat; ^8one cherub on the end on this side, and another cherub on the other end on that side: out of the mercy seat made he the cherubims on the two ends thereof. ^9And the cherubims spread out their wings on high, and covered with their wings over the mercy seat, with their faces one to another; even to the mercy seatward were the faces of the cherubims.

^10And he made the table of shittim wood: two cubits was the length thereof, and a cubit the breadth thereof, and a cubit and a half the height thereof: ^11and he overlaid it with pure gold, and made thereunto a crown of gold round about. ^12Also he made thereunto a border of an handbreadth round about; and made a crown of gold for the border thereof round about. ^13And he cast for it four rings of gold, and put the rings upon the four corners that were in the four feet thereof. ^14Over against the border were the rings, the places for the staves to bear the table. ^15And he made the staves of shittim wood, and overlaid them with gold, to bear the table. ^16And he made the vessels which were upon the table, his dishes, and his spoons, and his bowls, and his covers to cover withal, of pure gold.

^17And he made the candlestick of pure gold: of beaten work made he the candlestick; his shaft, and his branch, his bowls, his knops, and his flowers, were of the same: ^18and six branches going out of the sides thereof; three branches of the candlestick out of the one side thereof, and three branches of the candlestick out of the other side thereof: ^19three bowls made after the fashion of almonds in one branch, a knop and a flower; and three bowls made like almonds in another branch, a knop and a flower: so throughout the six branches going out of the candlestick. ^20And in the candlestick were four bowls made like almonds, his knops, and his flowers: ^21and a knop under two branches of the same, and a knop under two branches of the same, and a knop under two branches of the same, according to the six branches going out of it. ^22Their knops and their branches were of the same: all of it was one beaten work of pure gold. ^23And he made his seven lamps, and his snuffers, and his snuffdishes, of pure gold. ^24Of a talent of pure gold made he it, and all the vessels thereof.

^25And he made the incense altar of shittim wood: the length of it was a cubit, and the breadth of it a cubit; it was foursquare; and two cubits was the height of it; the horns thereof were of the same. ^26And he overlaid it with pure gold, both the top of it, and the sides thereof round about, and the horns of it: also he made unto it a crown of gold round about. ^27And he made two rings of gold for it under the crown thereof, by the two corners of it, upon the two sides thereof, to be places for the staves to bear it withal. ^28And he made the staves of shittim wood, and overlaid them with gold.

^29And he made the holy anointing oil, and the pure incense of sweet spices, according to the work of the apothecary.

XXXVIII

^1And he made the altar of burnt offering of shittim wood: five cubits was the length thereof, and five cubits the breadth thereof; it was foursquare; and three cubits the height thereof. ^2And he made the horns thereof on the four corners of it; the horns thereof were of the same: and he overlaid it with brass. ^3And he made all the vessels of the altar, the pots, and the shovels, and the basons, and the fleshhooks, and the firepans: all the vessels thereof made he of brass. ^4And he made for the altar a brasen grate of network under the compass thereof beneath unto the midst of it. ^5And he cast four rings for the four ends of the grate of brass, to be places for the staves. ^6And he made the staves of shittim wood, and overlaid them with brass. ^7And he put the staves into the rings on the sides of the altar, to bear it withal; he made the altar hollow with boards.

^8And he made the laver of brass, and the foot of it of brass, of the lookingglasses of the women assembling, which assembled at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.

^9And he made the court: on the south side southward the hangings of the court were of fine twined linen, an hundred cubits: ^10their pillars were twenty, and their brasen sockets twenty; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets were of silver. ^11And for the north side the hangings were an hundred cubits, their pillars were twenty, and their sockets of brass twenty; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets of silver. ^12And for the west side were hangings of fifty cubits, their pillars ten, and their sockets ten; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets of silver. ^13And for the east side eastward fifty cubits. ^14The hangings of the one side of the gate were fifteen cubits; their pillars three, and their sockets three. ^15And for the other side of the court gate, on this hand and that hand, were hangings of fifteen cubits; their pillars three, and their sockets three. ^16All the hangings of the court round about were of fine twined linen. ^17And the sockets for the pillars were of brass; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets of silver; and the overlaying of their chapiters of silver; and all the pillars of the court were filleted with silver. ^18And the hanging for the gate of the court was needlework, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen: and twenty cubits was the length, and the height in the breadth was five cubits, answerable to the hangings of the court. ^19And their pillars were four, and their sockets of brass four; their hooks of silver, and the overlaying of their chapiters and their fillets of silver. ^20And all the pins of the tabernacle, and of the court round about, were of brass.

^21This is the sum of the tabernacle, even of the tabernacle of testimony, as it was counted, according to the commandment of Moses, for the service of the Levites, by the hand of Ithamar, son to Aaron the priest. ^22And Bezaleel the son Uri, the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah, made all that the Lord commanded Moses. ^23And with him was Aholiab, son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan, an engraver, and a cunning workman, and an embroiderer in blue, and in purple, and in scarlet, and fine linen.

^24All the gold that was occupied for the work in all the work of the holy place, even the gold of the offering, was twenty and nine talents, and seven hundred and thirty shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary. ^25And the silver of them that were numbered of the congregation was an hundred talents, and a thousand seven hundred and threescore and fifteen shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary: ^26a bekah for every man, that is, half a shekel, after the shekel of the sanctuary, for every one that went to be numbered, from twenty years old and upward, for six hundred thousand and three thousand and five hundred and fifty men. ^27And of the hundred talents of silver were cast the sockets of the sanctuary, and the sockets of the vail; an hundred sockets of the hundred talents, a talent for a socket. ^28And of the thousand seven hundred seventy and five shekels he made hooks for the pillars, and overlaid their chapiters, and filleted them. ^29And the brass of the offering was seventy talents, and two thousand and four hundred shekels. ^30And therewith he made the sockets to the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and the brasen altar, and the brasen grate for it, and all the vessels of the altar, ^31and the sockets of the court round about, and the sockets of the court gate, and all the pins of the tabernacle, and all the pins of the court round about.

XXXIX

^1And of the blue, and purple, and scarlet, they made cloths of service, to do service in the holy place, and made the holy garments for Aaron; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^2And he made the ephod of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen. ^3And they did beat the gold into thin plates, and cut it into wires, to work it in the blue, and in the purple, and in the scarlet, and in the fine linen, with cunning work. ^4They made shoulderpieces for it, to couple it together: by the two edges was it coupled together. ^5And the curious girdle of his ephod, that was upon it, was of the same, according to the work thereof; of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^6And they wrought onyx stones inclosed in ouches of gold, graven, as signets are graven, with the names of the children of Israel. ^7And he put them on the shoulders of the ephod, that they should be stones for a memorial to the children of Israel; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^8And he made the breastplate of cunning work, like the work of the ephod; of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen. ^9It was foursquare; they made the breastplate double: a span was the length thereof, and a span the breadth thereof, being doubled. ^10And they set in it four rows of stones: the first row was a sardius, a topaz, and a carbuncle: this was the first row. ^11And the second row, an emerald, a sapphire, and a diamond. ^12And the third row, a ligure, an agate, and an amethyst. ^13And the fourth row, a beryl, an onyx, and a jasper: they were inclosed in ouches of gold in their inclosings. ^14And the stones were according to the names of the children of Israel, twelve, according to their names, like the engravings of a signet, every one with his name, according to the twelve tribes. ^15And they made upon the breastplate chains at the ends, of wreathen work of pure gold. ^16And they made two ouches of gold, and two gold rings; and put the two rings in the two ends of the breastplate. ^17And they put the two wreathen chains of gold in the two rings on the ends of the breastplate. ^18And the two ends of the two wreathen chains they fastened in the two ouches, and put them on the shoulderpieces of the ephod, before it. ^19And they made two rings of gold, and put them on the two ends of the breastplate, upon the border of it, which was on the side of the ephod inward. ^20And they made two other golden rings, and put them on the two sides of the ephod underneath, toward the forepart of it, over against the other coupling thereof, above the curious girdle of the ephod. ^21And they did bind the breastplate by his rings unto the rings of the ephod with a lace of blue, that it might be above the curious girdle of the ephod, and that the breastplate might not be loosed from the ephod; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^22And he made the robe of the ephod of woven work, all of blue. ^23And there was an hole in the midst of the robe, as the hole of an habergeon, with a band round about the hole, that it should not rend. ^24And they made upon the hems of the robe pomegranates of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen. ^25And they made bells of pure gold, and put the bells between the pomegranates upon the hem of the robe, round about between the pomegranates; ^26a bell and a pomegranate, a bell and a pomegranate, round about the hem of the robe to minister in; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^27And they made coats of fine linen of woven work for Aaron, and for his sons, ^28and a mitre of fine linen, and goodly bonnets of fine linen, and linen breeches of fine twined linen, ^29and a girdle of fine twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet, of needlework; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^30And they made the plate of the holy crown of pure gold, and wrote upon it a writing, like to the engravings of a signet, Holiness to the Lord. ^31And they tied unto it a lace of blue, to fasten it on high upon the mitre; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^32Thus was all the work of the tabernacle of the tent of the congregation finished: and the children of Israel did according to all that the Lord commanded Moses, so did they.

^33And they brought the tabernacle unto Moses, the tent, and all his furniture, his taches, his boards, his bars, and his pillars, and his sockets, ^34and the covering of rams’ skins dyed red, and the covering of badgers’ skins, and the vail of the covering, ^35the ark of the testimony, and the staves thereof, and the mercy seat, ^36the table, and all the vessels thereof, and the shewbread, ^37the pure candlestick, with the lamps thereof, even with the lamps to be set in order, and all the vessels thereof, and the oil for light, ^38and the golden altar, and the anointing oil, and the sweet incense, and the hanging for the tabernacle door, ^39the brasen altar, and his grate of brass, his staves, and all his vessels, the laver and his foot, ^40the hangings of the court, his pillars, and his sockets, and the hanging for the court gate, his cords, and his pins, and all the vessels of the service of the tabernacle, for the tent of the congregation, ^41the cloths of service to do service in the holy place, and the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and his sons’ garments, to minister in the priest’s office. ^42According to all that the Lord commanded Moses, so the children of Israel made all the work. ^43And Moses did look upon all the work, and, behold, they had done it as the Lord had commanded, even so had they done it: and Moses blessed them.

XL

^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ^2On the first day of the first month shalt thou set up the tabernacle of the tent of the congregation. ^3And thou shalt put therein the ark of the testimony, and cover the ark with the vail. ^4And thou shalt bring in the table, and set in order the things that are to be set in order upon it; and thou shalt bring in the candlestick, and light the lamps thereof. ^5And thou shalt set the altar of gold for the incense before the ark of the testimony, and put the hanging of the door to the tabernacle. ^6And thou shalt set the altar of the burnt offering before the door of the tabernacle of the tent of the congregation. ^7And thou shalt set the laver between the tent of the congregation and the altar, and shalt put water therein. ^8And thou shalt set up the court round about, and hang up the hanging at the court gate. ^9And thou shalt take the anointing oil, and anoint the tabernacle, and all that is therein, and shalt hallow it, and all the vessels thereof: and it shall be holy. ^10And thou shalt anoint the altar of the burnt offering, and all his vessels, and sanctify the altar: and it shall be an altar most holy. ^11And thou shalt anoint the laver and his foot, and sanctify it. ^12And thou shalt bring Aaron and his sons unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and wash them with water. ^13And thou shalt put upon Aaron the holy garments, and anoint him, and sanctify him; that he may minister unto me in the priest’s office. ^14And thou shalt bring his sons, and clothe them with coats: ^15and thou shalt anoint them, as thou didst anoint their father, that they may minister unto me in the priest’s office: for their anointing shall surely be an everlasting priesthood throughout their generations. ^16Thus did Moses: according to all that the Lord commanded him, so did he.

^17And it came to pass in the first month in the second year, on the first day of the month, that the tabernacle was reared up. ^18And Moses reared up the tabernacle, and fastened his sockets, and set up the boards thereof, and put in the bars thereof, and reared up his pillars. ^19And he spread abroad the tent over the tabernacle, and put the covering of the tent above upon it; as the Lord commanded Moses. ^20And he took and put the testimony into the ark, and set the staves on the ark, and put the mercy seat above upon the ark: ^21and he brought the ark into the tabernacle, and set up the vail of the covering, and covered the ark of the testimony; as the Lord commanded Moses. ^22And he put the table in the tent of the congregation, upon the side of the tabernacle northward, without the vail. ^23And he set the bread in order upon it before the Lord; as the Lord had commanded Moses. ^24And he put the candlestick in the tent of the congregation, over against the table, on the side of the tabernacle southward. ^25And he lighted the lamps before the Lord; as the Lord commanded Moses. ^26And he put the golden altar in the tent of the congregation before the vail: ^27and he burnt sweet incense thereon; as the Lord commanded Moses. ^28And he set up the hanging at the door of the tabernacle. ^29And he put the altar of burnt offering by the door of the tabernacle of the tent of the congregation, and offered upon it the burnt offering and the meat offering; as the Lord commanded Moses. ^30And he set the laver between the tent of the congregation and the altar, and put water there, to wash withal. ^31And Moses and Aaron and his sons washed their hands and their feet thereat: ^32when they went into the tent of the congregation, and when they came near unto the altar, they washed; as the Lord commanded Moses. ^33And he reared up the court round about the tabernacle and the altar, and set up the hanging of the court gate. So Moses finished the work.

^34Then a cloud covered the tent of the congregation, and the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle. ^35And Moses was not able to enter into the tent of the congregation, because the cloud abode thereon, and the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle. ^36And when the cloud was taken up from over the tabernacle, the children of Israel went onward in all their journeys: ^37but if the cloud were not taken up, then they journeyed not till the day that it was taken up. ^38For the cloud of the Lord was upon the tabernacle by day, and fire was on it by night, in the sight of all the house of Israel, throughout all their journeys.

Leviticus

The Third Book of Moses Called

Leviticus

I

1^1And the Lord called unto Moses, and spake unto him out of the tabernacle of the congregation, saying,

^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, If any man of you bring an offering unto the Lord, ye shall bring your offering of the cattle, even of the herd, and of the flock.

^3If his offering be a burnt sacrifice of the herd, let him offer a male without blemish: he shall offer it of his own voluntary will at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation before the Lord.

^4And he shall put his hand upon the head of the burnt offering; and it shall be accepted for him to make atonement for him.

^5And he shall kill the bullock before the Lord: and the priests, Aaron’s sons, shall bring the blood, and sprinkle the blood round about upon the altar that is by the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.

^6And he shall flay the burnt offering, and cut it into his pieces.

^7And the sons of Aaron the priest shall put fire upon the altar, and lay the wood in order upon the fire:

^8And the priests, Aaron’s sons, shall lay the parts, the head, and the fat, in order upon the wood that is on the fire which is upon the altar:

^9But his inwards and his legs shall he wash in water: and the priest shall burn all on the altar, to be a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the Lord.

^10And if his offering be of the flocks, namely, of the sheep, or of the goats, for a burnt sacrifice; he shall bring it a male without blemish.

^11And he shall kill it on the side of the altar northward before the Lord: and the priests, Aaron’s sons, shall sprinkle his blood round about upon the altar.

^12And he shall cut it into his pieces, with his head and his fat: and the priest shall lay them in order on the wood that is on the fire which is upon the altar:

^13But he shall wash the inwards and the legs with water: and the priest shall bring it all, and burn it upon the altar: it is a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the Lord.

^14And if the burnt sacrifice for his offering to the Lord be of fowls, then he shall bring his offering of turtledoves, or of young pigeons.

^15And the priest shall bring it unto the altar, and wring off his head, and burn it on the altar; and the blood thereof shall be wrung out at the side of the altar:

^16And he shall pluck away his crop with his feathers, and cast it beside the altar on the east part, by the place of the ashes:

^17And he shall cleave it with the wings thereof, but shall not divide it asunder: and the priest shall burn it upon the altar, upon the wood that is upon the fire: it is a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the Lord.

II

2^1And when any will offer a meat offering unto the Lord, his offering shall be of fine flour; and he shall pour oil upon it, and put frankincense thereon:

^2And he shall bring it to Aaron’s sons the priests: and he shall take thereout his handful of the flour thereof, and of the oil thereof, with all the frankincense thereof; and the priest shall burn the memorial of it upon the altar, to be an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the Lord:

^3And the remnant of the meat offering shall be Aaron’s and his sons’: it is a thing most holy of the offerings of the Lord made by fire.

^4And if thou bring an oblation of a meat offering baken in the oven, it shall be unleavened cakes of fine flour mingled with oil, or unleavened wafers anointed with oil.

^5And if thy oblation be a meat offering baken in a pan, it shall be of fine flour unleavened, mingled with oil.

^6Thou shalt part it in pieces, and pour oil thereon: it is a meat offering.

^7And if thy oblation be a meat offering baken in the fryingpan, it shall be made of fine flour with oil.

^8And thou shalt bring the meat offering that is made of these things unto the Lord: and when it is presented unto the priest, he shall bring it unto the altar.

^9And the priest shall take from the meat offering a memorial thereof, and shall burn it upon the altar: it is an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the Lord.

^10And that which is left of the meat offering shall be Aaron’s and his sons’: it is a thing most holy of the offerings of the Lord made by fire.

^11No meat offering, which ye shall bring unto the Lord, shall be made with leaven: for ye shall burn no leaven, nor any honey, in any offering of the Lord made by fire.

^12As for the oblation of the firstfruits, ye shall offer them unto the Lord: but they shall not be burnt on the altar for a sweet savour.

^13And every oblation of thy meat offering shalt thou season with salt; neither shalt thou suffer the salt of the covenant of thy God to be lacking from thy meat offering: with all thine offerings thou shalt offer salt.

^14And if thou offer a meat offering of thy firstfruits unto the Lord, thou shalt offer for the meat offering of thy firstfruits green ears of corn dried by the fire, even corn beaten out of full ears.

^15And thou shalt put oil upon it, and lay frankincense thereon: it is a meat offering.

^16And the priest shall burn the memorial of it, part of the beaten corn thereof, and part of the oil thereof, with all the frankincense thereof: it is an offering made by fire unto the Lord.

III

3^1And if his oblation be a sacrifice of peace offering, if he offer it of the herd; whether it be a male or female, he shall offer it without blemish before the Lord.

^2And he shall lay his hand upon the head of his offering, and kill it at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation: and Aaron’s sons the priests shall sprinkle the blood upon the altar round about.

^3And he shall offer of the sacrifice of the peace offering an offering made by fire unto the Lord; the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that is upon the inwards,

^4And the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the flanks, and the caul above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away.

^5And Aaron’s sons shall burn it on the altar upon the burnt sacrifice, which is upon the wood that is on the fire: it is an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the Lord.

^6And if his offering for a sacrifice of peace offering unto the Lord be of the flock; male or female, he shall offer it without blemish.

^7If he offer a lamb for his offering, then shall he offer it before the Lord.

^8And he shall lay his hand upon the head of his offering, and kill it before the tabernacle of the congregation: and Aaron’s sons shall sprinkle the blood thereof round about upon the altar.

^9And he shall offer of the sacrifice of the peace offering an offering made by fire unto the Lord; the fat thereof, and the whole rump, it shall he take off hard by the backbone; and the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that is upon the inwards,

^10And the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, which is by the flanks, and the caul above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away.

^11And the priest shall burn it upon the altar: it is the food of the offering made by fire unto the Lord.

^12And if his offering be a goat, then he shall offer it before the Lord.

^13And he shall lay his hand upon the head of it, and kill it before the tabernacle of the congregation: and the sons of Aaron shall sprinkle the blood thereof upon the altar round about.

^14And he shall offer thereof his offering, even an offering made by fire unto the Lord; the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that is upon the inwards,

^15And the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, which is by the flanks, and the caul above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away.

^16And the priest shall burn them upon the altar: it is the food of the offering made by fire for a sweet savour: all the fat is the Lord’s.

^17It shall be a perpetual statute for your generations throughout all your dwellings, that ye eat neither fat nor blood.

IV

4^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, If a soul shall sin through ignorance against any of the commandments of the Lord concerning things which ought not to be done, and shall do against any of them:

^3If the priest that is anointed do sin according to the sin of the people; then let him bring for his sin, which he hath sinned, a young bullock without blemish unto the Lord for a sin offering.

^4And he shall bring the bullock unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation before the Lord; and shall lay his hand upon the bullock’s head, and kill the bullock before the Lord.

^5And the priest that is anointed shall take of the bullock’s blood, and bring it to the tabernacle of the congregation:

^6And the priest shall dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle of the blood seven times before the Lord, before the vail of the sanctuary.

^7And the priest shall put some of the blood upon the horns of the altar of sweet incense before the Lord, which is in the tabernacle of the congregation; and shall pour all the blood of the bullock at the bottom of the altar of the burnt offering, which is at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.

^8And he shall take off from it all the fat of the bullock for the sin offering; the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that is upon the inwards,

^9And the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, which is by the flanks, and the caul above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away,

^10As it was taken off from the bullock of the sacrifice of peace offerings: and the priest shall burn them upon the altar of the burnt offering.

^11And the skin of the bullock, and all his flesh, with his head, and with his legs, and his inwards, and his dung,

^12Even the whole bullock shall he carry forth without the camp unto a clean place, where the ashes are poured out, and burn him on the wood with fire: where the ashes are poured out shall he be burnt.

^13And if the whole congregation of Israel sin through ignorance, and the thing be hid from the eyes of the assembly, and they have done somewhat against any of the commandments of the Lord concerning things which should not be done, and are guilty;

^14When the sin, which they have sinned against it, is known, then the congregation shall offer a young bullock for the sin, and bring him before the tabernacle of the congregation.

^15And the elders of the congregation shall lay their hands upon the head of the bullock before the Lord: and the bullock shall be killed before the Lord.

^16And the priest that is anointed shall bring of the bullock’s blood to the tabernacle of the congregation:

^17And the priest shall dip his finger in some of the blood, and sprinkle it seven times before the Lord, even before the vail.

^18And he shall put some of the blood upon the horns of the altar which is before the Lord, that is in the tabernacle of the congregation, and shall pour out all the blood at the bottom of the altar of the burnt offering, which is at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.

^19And he shall take all his fat from him, and burn it upon the altar.

^20And he shall do with the bullock as he did with the bullock for a sin offering, so shall he do with this: and the priest shall make an atonement for them, and it shall be forgiven them.

^21And he shall carry forth the bullock without the camp, and burn him as he burned the first bullock: it is a sin offering for the congregation.

^22When a ruler hath sinned, and done somewhat through ignorance against any of the commandments of the Lord his God concerning things which should not be done, and is guilty;

^23Or if his sin, wherein he hath sinned, come to his knowledge; he shall bring his offering, a kid of the goats, a male without blemish:

^24And he shall lay his hand upon the head of the goat, and kill it in the place where they kill the burnt offering before the Lord: it is a sin offering.

^25And the priest shall take of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, and put it upon the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and shall pour out his blood at the bottom of the altar of burnt offering.

^26And he shall burn all his fat upon the altar, as the fat of the sacrifice of peace offerings: and the priest shall make an atonement for him as concerning his sin, and it shall be forgiven him.

^27And if any one of the common people sin through ignorance, while he doeth somewhat against any of the commandments of the Lord concerning things which ought not to be done, and be guilty;

^28Or if his sin, which he hath sinned, come to his knowledge: then he shall bring his offering, a kid of the goats, a female without blemish, for his sin which he hath sinned.

^29And he shall lay his hand upon the head of the sin offering, and slay the sin offering in the place of the burnt offering.

^30And the priest shall take of the blood thereof with his finger, and put it upon the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and shall pour out all the blood thereof at the bottom of the altar.

^31And he shall take away all the fat thereof, as the fat is taken away from off the sacrifice of peace offerings; and the priest shall burn it upon the altar for a sweet savour unto the Lord; and the priest shall make an atonement for him, and it shall be forgiven him.

^32And if he bring a lamb for a sin offering, he shall bring it a female without blemish.

^33And he shall lay his hand upon the head of the sin offering, and slay it for a sin offering in the place where they kill the burnt offering.

^34And the priest shall take of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, and put it upon the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and shall pour out all the blood thereof at the bottom of the altar:

^35And he shall take away all the fat thereof, as the fat of the lamb is taken away from the sacrifice of the peace offerings; and the priest shall burn them upon the altar, according to the offerings made by fire unto the Lord: and the priest shall make an atonement for his sin that he hath committed, and it shall be forgiven him.

V

5^1And if a soul sin, and hear the voice of swearing, and is a witness, whether he hath seen or known of it; if he do not utter it, then he shall bear his iniquity.

^2Or if a soul touch any unclean thing, whether it be a carcase of an unclean beast, or a carcase of unclean cattle, or the carcase of unclean creeping things, and if it be hidden from him; he also shall be unclean, and guilty.

^3Or if he touch the uncleanness of man, whatsoever uncleanness it be that a man shall be defiled withal, and it be hid from him; when he knoweth of it, then he shall be guilty.

^4Or if a soul swear, pronouncing with his lips to do evil, or to do good, whatsoever it be that a man shall pronounce with an oath, and it be hid from him; when he knoweth of it, then he shall be guilty in one of these.

^5And it shall be, when he shall be guilty in one of these things, that he shall confess that he hath sinned in that thing:

^6And he shall bring his trespass offering unto the Lord for his sin which he hath sinned, a female from the flock, a lamb or a kid of the goats, for a sin offering; and the priest shall make an atonement for him concerning his sin.

^7And if he be not able to bring a lamb, then he shall bring for his trespass, which he hath committed, two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, unto the Lord; one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering.

^8And he shall bring them unto the priest, who shall offer that which is for the sin offering first, and wring off his head from his neck, but shall not divide it asunder:

^9And he shall sprinkle of the blood of the sin offering upon the side of the altar; and the rest of the blood shall be wrung out at the bottom of the altar: it is a sin offering.

^10And he shall offer the second for a burnt offering, according to the manner: and the priest shall make an atonement for him for his sin which he hath sinned, and it shall be forgiven him.

^11But if he be not able to bring two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, then he that sinned shall bring for his offering the tenth part of an ephah of fine flour for a sin offering; he shall put no oil upon it, neither shall he put any frankincense thereon: for it is a sin offering.

^12Then shall he bring it to the priest, and the priest shall take his handful of it, even a memorial thereof, and burn it on the altar, according to the offerings made by fire unto the Lord: it is a sin offering.

^13And the priest shall make an atonement for him as touching his sin that he hath sinned in one of these, and it shall be forgiven him: and the remnant shall be the priest’s, as a meat offering.

^14And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^15If a soul commit a trespass, and sin through ignorance, in the holy things of the Lord; then he shall bring for his trespass unto the Lord a ram without blemish out of the flocks, with thy estimation by shekels of silver, after the shekel of the sanctuary, for a trespass offering.

^16And he shall make amends for the harm that he hath done in the holy thing, and shall add the fifth part thereto, and give it unto the priest: and the priest shall make an atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering, and it shall be forgiven him.

^17And if a soul sin, and commit any of these things which are forbidden to be done by the commandments of the Lord; though he wist it not, yet is he guilty, and shall bear his iniquity.

^18And he shall bring a ram without blemish out of the flock, with thy estimation, for a trespass offering, unto the priest: and the priest shall make an atonement for him concerning his ignorance wherein he erred and wist it not, and it shall be forgiven him.

^19It is a trespass offering: he hath certainly trespassed against the Lord.

VI

6^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2If a soul sin, and commit a trespass against the Lord, and lie unto his neighbour in that which was delivered him to keep, or in fellowship, or in a thing taken away by violence, or hath deceived his neighbour;

^3Or have found that which was lost, and lieth concerning it, and sweareth falsely; in any of all these that a man doeth, sinning therein:

^4Then it shall be, because he hath sinned, and is guilty, that he shall restore that which he took violently away, or the thing which he hath deceitfully gotten, or that which was delivered him to keep, or the lost thing which he found,

^5Or all that about which he hath sworn falsely; he shall even restore it in the principal, and shall add the fifth part more thereto, and give it unto him to whom it appertaineth, in the day of his trespass offering.

^6And he shall bring his trespass offering unto the Lord, a ram without blemish out of the flock, with thy estimation, for a trespass offering, unto the priest:

^7And the priest shall make an atonement for him before the Lord: and it shall be forgiven him for any thing of all that he hath done in trespassing therein.

^8And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^9Command Aaron and his sons, saying, This is the law of the burnt offering: It is the burnt offering, because of the burning upon the altar all night unto the morning, and the fire of the altar shall be burning in it.

^10And the priest shall put on his linen garment, and his linen breeches shall he put upon his flesh, and take up the ashes which the fire hath consumed with the burnt offering on the altar, and he shall put them beside the altar.

^11And he shall put off his garments, and put on other garments, and carry forth the ashes without the camp unto a clean place.

^12And the fire upon the altar shall be burning in it; it shall not be put out: and the priest shall burn wood on it every morning, and lay the burnt offering in order upon it; and he shall burn thereon the fat of the peace offerings.

^13The fire shall ever be burning upon the altar; it shall never go out.

^14And this is the law of the meat offering: the sons of Aaron shall offer it before the Lord, before the altar.

^15And he shall take of it his handful, of the flour of the meat offering, and of the oil thereof, and all the frankincense which is upon the meat offering, and shall burn it upon the altar for a sweet savour, even the memorial of it, unto the Lord.

^16And the remainder thereof shall Aaron and his sons eat: with unleavened bread shall it be eaten in the holy place; in the court of the tabernacle of the congregation they shall eat it.

^17It shall not be baken with leaven. I have given it unto them for their portion of my offerings made by fire; it is most holy, as is the sin offering, and as the trespass offering.

^18All the males among the children of Aaron shall eat of it. It shall be a statute for ever in your generations concerning the offerings of the Lord made by fire: every one that toucheth them shall be holy.

^19And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^20This is the offering of Aaron and of his sons, which they shall offer unto the Lord in the day when he is anointed; the tenth part of an ephah of fine flour for a meat offering perpetual, half of it in the morning, and half thereof at night.

^21In a pan it shall be made with oil; and when it is baken, thou shalt bring it in: and the baken pieces of the meat offering shalt thou offer for a sweet savour unto the Lord.

^22And the priest of his sons that is anointed in his stead shall offer it: it is a statute for ever unto the Lord; it shall be wholly burnt.

^23For every meat offering for the priest shall be wholly burnt: it shall not be eaten.

^24And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^25Speak unto Aaron and to his sons, saying, This is the law of the sin offering: In the place where the burnt offering is killed shall the sin offering be killed before the Lord: it is most holy.

^26The priest that offereth it for sin shall eat it: in the holy place shall it be eaten, in the court of the tabernacle of the congregation.

^27Whatsoever shall touch the flesh thereof shall be holy: and when there is sprinkled of the blood thereof upon any garment, thou shalt wash that whereon it was sprinkled in the holy place.

^28But the earthen vessel wherein it is sodden shall be broken: and if it be sodden in a brasen pot, it shall be both scoured, and rinsed in water.

^29All the males among the priests shall eat thereof: it is most holy.

^30And no sin offering, whereof any of the blood is brought into the tabernacle of the congregation to reconcile withal in the holy place, shall be eaten: it shall be burnt in the fire.

VII

7^1Likewise this is the law of the trespass offering: it is most holy.

^2In the place where they kill the burnt offering shall they kill the trespass offering: and the blood thereof shall he sprinkle round about upon the altar.

^3And he shall offer of it all the fat thereof; the rump, and the fat that covereth the inwards,

^4And the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the flanks, and the caul that is above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away:

^5And the priest shall burn them upon the altar for an offering made by fire unto the Lord: it is a trespass offering.

^6Every male among the priests shall eat thereof: it shall be eaten in the holy place: it is most holy.

^7As the sin offering is, so is the trespass offering: there is one law for them: the priest that maketh atonement therewith shall have it.

^8And the priest that offereth any man’s burnt offering, even the priest shall have to himself the skin of the burnt offering which he hath offered.

^9And all the meat offering that is baken in the oven, and all that is dressed in the fryingpan, and in the pan, shall be the priest’s that offereth it.

^10And every meat offering, mingled with oil, and dry, shall all the sons of Aaron have, one as much as another.

^11And this is the law of the sacrifice of peace offerings, which he shall offer unto the Lord.

^12If he offer it for a thanksgiving, then he shall offer with the sacrifice of thanksgiving unleavened cakes mingled with oil, and unleavened wafers anointed with oil, and cakes mingled with oil, of fine flour, fried.

^13Besides the cakes, he shall offer for his offering leavened bread with the sacrifice of thanksgiving of his peace offerings.

^14And of it he shall offer one out of the whole oblation for an heave offering unto the Lord, and it shall be the priest’s that sprinkleth the blood of the peace offerings.

^15And the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offerings for thanksgiving shall be eaten the same day that it is offered; he shall not leave any of it until the morning.

^16But if the sacrifice of his offering be a vow, or a voluntary offering, it shall be eaten the same day that he offereth his sacrifice: and on the morrow also the remainder of it shall be eaten:

^17But the remainder of the flesh of the sacrifice on the third day shall be burnt with fire.

^18And if any of the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offerings be eaten at all on the third day, it shall not be accepted, neither shall it be imputed unto him that offereth it: it shall be an abomination, and the soul that eateth of it shall bear his iniquity.

^19And the flesh that toucheth any unclean thing shall not be eaten; it shall be burnt with fire: and as for the flesh, all that be clean shall eat thereof.

^20But the soul that eateth of the flesh of the sacrifice of peace offerings, that pertain unto the Lord, having his uncleanness upon him, even that soul shall be cut off from his people.

^21Moreover the soul that shall touch any unclean thing, as the uncleanness of man, or any unclean beast, or any abominable unclean thing, and eat of the flesh of the sacrifice of peace offerings, which pertain unto the Lord, even that soul shall be cut off from his people.

^22And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^23Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, Ye shall eat no manner of fat, of ox, or of sheep, or of goat.

^24And the fat of the beast that dieth of itself, and the fat of that which is torn with beasts, may be used in any other use: but ye shall in no wise eat of it.

^25For whosoever eateth the fat of the beast, of which men offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord, even the soul that eateth it shall be cut off from his people.

^26Moreover ye shall eat no manner of blood, whether it be of fowl or of beast, in any of your dwellings.

^27Whatsoever soul it be that eateth any manner of blood, even that soul shall be cut off from his people.

^28And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^29Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, He that offereth the sacrifice of his peace offerings unto the Lord shall bring his oblation unto the Lord of the sacrifice of his peace offerings.

^30His own hands shall bring the offerings of the Lord made by fire, the fat with the breast, it shall he bring, that the breast may be waved for a wave offering before the Lord.

^31And the priest shall burn the fat upon the altar: but the breast shall be Aaron’s and his sons’.

^32And the right shoulder shall ye give unto the priest for an heave offering of the sacrifices of your peace offerings.

^33He among the sons of Aaron, that offereth the blood of the peace offerings, and the fat, shall have the right shoulder for his part.

^34For the wave breast and the heave shoulder have I taken of the children of Israel from off the sacrifices of their peace offerings, and have given them unto Aaron the priest and unto his sons by a statute for ever from among the children of Israel.

^35This is the portion of the anointing of Aaron, and of the anointing of his sons, out of the offerings of the Lord made by fire, in the day when he presented them to minister unto the Lord in the priest’s office;

^36Which the Lord commanded to be given them of the children of Israel, in the day that he anointed them, by a statute for ever throughout their generations.

^37This is the law of the burnt offering, of the meat offering, and of the sin offering, and of the trespass offering, and of the consecrations, and of the sacrifice of the peace offerings;

^38Which the Lord commanded Moses in mount Sinai, in the day that he commanded the children of Israel to offer their oblations unto the Lord, in the wilderness of Sinai.

VIII

8^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2Take Aaron and his sons with him, and the garments, and the anointing oil, and a bullock for the sin offering, and two rams, and a basket of unleavened bread;

^3And gather thou all the congregation together unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.

^4And Moses did as the Lord commanded him; and the assembly was gathered together unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.

^5And Moses said unto the congregation, This is the thing which the Lord commanded to be done.

^6And Moses brought Aaron and his sons, and washed them with water.

^7And he put upon him the coat, and girded him with the girdle, and clothed him with the robe, and put the ephod upon him, and he girded him with the curious girdle of the ephod, and bound it unto him therewith.

^8And he put the breastplate upon him: also he put in the breastplate the Urim and the Thummim.

^9And he put the mitre upon his head; also upon the mitre, even upon his forefront, did he put the golden plate, the holy crown; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^10And Moses took the anointing oil, and anointed the tabernacle and all that was therein, and sanctified them.

^11And he sprinkled thereof upon the altar seven times, and anointed the altar and all his vessels, both the laver and his foot, to sanctify them.

^12And he poured of the anointing oil upon Aaron’s head, and anointed him, to sanctify him.

^13And Moses brought Aaron’s sons, and put coats upon them, and girded them with girdles, and put bonnets upon them; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^14And he brought the bullock for the sin offering: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the bullock for the sin offering.

^15And he slew it; and Moses took the blood, and put it upon the horns of the altar round about with his finger, and purified the altar, and poured the blood at the bottom of the altar, and sanctified it, to make reconciliation upon it.

^16And he took all the fat that was upon the inwards, and the caul above the liver, and the two kidneys, and their fat, and Moses burned it upon the altar.

^17But the bullock, and his hide, his flesh, and his dung, he burnt with fire without the camp; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^18And he brought the ram for the burnt offering: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the ram.

^19And he killed it; and Moses sprinkled the blood upon the altar round about.

^20And he cut the ram into pieces; and Moses burnt the head, and the pieces, and the fat.

^21And he washed the inwards and the legs in water; and Moses burnt the whole ram upon the altar: it was a burnt sacrifice for a sweet savour, and an offering made by fire unto the Lord; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^22And he brought the other ram, the ram of consecration: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the ram.

^23And he slew it; and Moses took of the blood of it, and put it upon the tip of Aaron’s right ear, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot.

^24And he brought Aaron’s sons, and Moses put of the blood upon the tip of their right ear, and upon the thumbs of their right hands, and upon the great toes of their right feet: and Moses sprinkled the blood upon the altar round about.

^25And he took the fat, and the rump, and all the fat that was upon the inwards, and the caul above the liver, and the two kidneys, and their fat, and the right shoulder:

^26And out of the basket of unleavened bread, that was before the Lord, he took one unleavened cake, and a cake of oiled bread, and one wafer, and put them on the fat, and upon the right shoulder:

^27And he put all upon Aaron’s hands, and upon his sons’ hands, and waved them for a wave offering before the Lord.

^28And Moses took them from off their hands, and burnt them on the altar upon the burnt offering: they were consecrations for a sweet savour: it is an offering made by fire unto the Lord.

^29And Moses took the breast, and waved it for a wave offering before the Lord: for of the ram of consecration it was Moses’ part; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^30And Moses took of the anointing oil, and of the blood which was upon the altar, and sprinkled it upon Aaron, and upon his garments, and upon his sons, and upon his sons’ garments with him; and sanctified Aaron, and his garments, and his sons, and his sons’ garments with him.

^31And Moses said unto Aaron and to his sons, Boil the flesh at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation: and there eat it with the bread that is in the basket of consecrations, as I commanded, saying, Aaron and his sons shall eat it.

^32And that which remaineth of the flesh and of the bread shall ye burn with fire.

^33And ye shall not go out of the door of the tabernacle of the congregation in seven days, until the days of your consecration be at an end: for seven days shall he consecrate you.

^34As he hath done this day, so the Lord hath commanded to do, to make an atonement for you.

^35Therefore shall ye abide at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation day and night seven days, and keep the charge of the Lord, that ye die not: for so I am commanded.

^36So Aaron and his sons did all things which the Lord commanded by the hand of Moses.

IX

9^1And it came to pass on the eighth day, that Moses called Aaron and his sons, and the elders of Israel;

^2And he said unto Aaron, Take thee a young calf for a sin offering, and a ram for a burnt offering, without blemish, and offer them before the Lord.

^3And unto the children of Israel thou shalt speak, saying, Take ye a kid of the goats for a sin offering; and a calf and a lamb, both of the first year, without blemish, for a burnt offering;

^4Also a bullock and a ram for peace offerings, to sacrifice before the Lord; and a meat offering mingled with oil: for to day the Lord will appear unto you.

^5And they brought that which Moses commanded before the tabernacle of the congregation: and all the congregation drew near and stood before the Lord.

^6And Moses said, This is the thing which the Lord commanded that ye should do: and the glory of the Lord shall appear unto you.

^7And Moses said unto Aaron, Go unto the altar, and offer thy sin offering, and thy burnt offering, and make an atonement for thyself, and for the people: and offer the offering of the people, and make an atonement for them; as the Lord commanded.

^8Aaron therefore went unto the altar, and slew the calf of the sin offering, which was for himself.

^9And the sons of Aaron brought the blood unto him: and he dipped his finger in the blood, and put it upon the horns of the altar, and poured out the blood at the bottom of the altar:

^10But the fat, and the kidneys, and the caul above the liver of the sin offering, he burnt upon the altar; as the Lord commanded Moses.

^11And the flesh and the hide he burnt with fire without the camp.

^12And he slew the burnt offering; and Aaron’s sons presented unto him the blood, which he sprinkled round about upon the altar.

^13And they presented the burnt offering unto him, with the pieces thereof, and the head: and he burnt them upon the altar.

^14And he did wash the inwards and the legs, and burnt them upon the burnt offering on the altar.

^15And he brought the people’s offering, and took the goat, which was the sin offering for the people, and slew it, and offered it for sin, as the first.

^16And he brought the burnt offering, and offered it according to the manner.

^17And he brought the meat offering, and took an handful thereof, and burnt it upon the altar, beside the burnt sacrifice of the morning.

^18He slew also the bullock and the ram for a sacrifice of peace offerings, which was for the people: and Aaron’s sons presented unto him the blood, which he sprinkled upon the altar round about,

^19And the fat of the bullock and of the ram, the rump, and that which covereth the inwards, and the kidneys, and the caul above the liver:

^20And they put the fat upon the breasts, and he burnt the fat upon the altar:

^21And the breasts and the right shoulder Aaron waved for a wave offering before the Lord; as Moses commanded.

^22And Aaron lifted up his hand toward the people, and blessed them, and came down from offering of the sin offering, and the burnt offering, and peace offerings.

^23And Moses and Aaron went into the tabernacle of the congregation, and came out, and blessed the people: and the glory of the Lord appeared unto all the people.

^24And there came a fire out from before the Lord, and consumed upon the altar the burnt offering and the fat: which when all the people saw, they shouted, and fell on their faces.

X

10^1And Nadab and Abihu, the sons of Aaron, took either of them his censer, and put fire therein, and put incense thereon, and offered strange fire before the Lord, which he commanded them not.

^2And there went out fire from the Lord, and devoured them, and they died before the Lord.

^3Then Moses said unto Aaron, This is it that the Lord spake, saying, I will be sanctified in them that come nigh me, and before all the people I will be glorified. And Aaron held his peace.

^4And Moses called Mishael and Elzaphan, the sons of Uzziel the uncle of Aaron, and said unto them, Come near, carry your brethren from before the sanctuary out of the camp.

^5So they went near, and carried them in their coats out of the camp; as Moses had said.

^6And Moses said unto Aaron, and unto Eleazar and unto Ithamar, his sons, Uncover not your heads, neither rend your clothes; lest ye die, and lest wrath come upon all the people: but let your brethren, the whole house of Israel, bewail the burning which the Lord hath kindled.

^7And ye shall not go out from the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, lest ye die: for the anointing oil of the Lord is upon you. And they did according to the word of Moses.

^8And the Lord spake unto Aaron, saying,

^9Do not drink wine nor strong drink, thou, nor thy sons with thee, when ye go into the tabernacle of the congregation, lest ye die: it shall be a statute for ever throughout your generations:

^10And that ye may put difference between holy and unholy, and between unclean and clean;

^11And that ye may teach the children of Israel all the statutes which the Lord hath spoken unto them by the hand of Moses.

^12And Moses spake unto Aaron, and unto Eleazar and unto Ithamar, his sons that were left, Take the meat offering that remaineth of the offerings of the Lord made by fire, and eat it without leaven beside the altar: for it is most holy:

^13And ye shall eat it in the holy place, because it is thy due, and thy sons’ due, of the sacrifices of the Lord made by fire: for so I am commanded.

^14And the wave breast and heave shoulder shall ye eat in a clean place; thou, and thy sons, and thy daughters with thee: for they be thy due, and thy sons’ due, which are given out of the sacrifices of peace offerings of the children of Israel.

^15The heave shoulder and the wave breast shall they bring with the offerings made by fire of the fat, to wave it for a wave offering before the Lord; and it shall be thine, and thy sons’ with thee, by a statute for ever; as the Lord hath commanded.

^16And Moses diligently sought the goat of the sin offering, and, behold, it was burnt: and he was angry with Eleazar and Ithamar, the sons of Aaron which were left alive, saying,

^17Wherefore have ye not eaten the sin offering in the holy place, seeing it is most holy, and God hath given it you to bear the iniquity of the congregation, to make atonement for them before the Lord?

^18Behold, the blood of it was not brought in within the holy place: ye should indeed have eaten it in the holy place, as I commanded.

^19And Aaron said unto Moses, Behold, this day have they offered their sin offering and their burnt offering before the Lord; and such things have befallen me: and if I had eaten the sin offering to day, should it have been accepted in the sight of the Lord?

^20And when Moses heard that, he was content.

XI

11^1And the Lord spake unto Moses and to Aaron, saying unto them,

^2Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, These are the beasts which ye shall eat among all the beasts that are on the earth.

^3Whatsoever parteth the hoof, and is clovenfooted, and cheweth the cud, among the beasts, that shall ye eat.

^4Nevertheless these shall ye not eat of them that chew the cud, or of them that divide the hoof: as the camel, because he cheweth the cud, but divideth not the hoof; he is unclean unto you.

^5And the coney, because he cheweth the cud, but divideth not the hoof; he is unclean unto you.

^6And the hare, because he cheweth the cud, but divideth not the hoof; he is unclean unto you.

^7And the swine, though he divide the hoof, and be clovenfooted, yet he cheweth not the cud; he is unclean to you.

^8Of their flesh shall ye not eat, and their carcase shall ye not touch; they are unclean to you.

^9These shall ye eat of all that are in the waters: whatsoever hath fins and scales in the waters, in the seas, and in the rivers, them shall ye eat.

^10And all that have not fins and scales in the seas, and in the rivers, of all that move in the waters, and of any living thing which is in the waters, they shall be an abomination unto you:

^11They shall be even an abomination unto you; ye shall not eat of their flesh, but ye shall have their carcases in abomination.

^12Whatsoever hath no fins nor scales in the waters, that shall be an abomination unto you.

^13And these are they which ye shall have in abomination among the fowls; they shall not be eaten, they are an abomination: the eagle, and the ossifrage, and the ospray,

^14And the vulture, and the kite after his kind;

^15Every raven after his kind;

^16And the owl, and the night hawk, and the cuckow, and the hawk after his kind,

^17And the little owl, and the cormorant, and the great owl,

^18And the swan, and the pelican, and the gier eagle,

^19And the stork, the heron after her kind, and the lapwing, and the bat.

^20All fowls that creep, going upon all four, shall be an abomination unto you.

^21Yet these may ye eat of every flying creeping thing that goeth upon all four, which have legs above their feet, to leap withal upon the earth;

^22Even these of them ye may eat; the locust after his kind, and the bald locust after his kind, and the beetle after his kind, and the grasshopper after his kind.

^23But all other flying creeping things, which have four feet, shall be an abomination unto you.

^24And for these ye shall be unclean: whosoever toucheth the carcase of them shall be unclean until the even.

^25And whosoever beareth ought of the carcase of them shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even.

^26The carcases of every beast which divideth the hoof, and is not clovenfooted, nor cheweth the cud, are unclean unto you: every one that toucheth them shall be unclean.

^27And whatsoever goeth upon his paws, among all manner of beasts that go on all four, those are unclean unto you: whoso toucheth their carcase shall be unclean until the even.

^28And he that beareth the carcase of them shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even: they are unclean unto you.

^29These also shall be unclean unto you among the creeping things that creep upon the earth; the weasel, and the mouse, and the tortoise after his kind,

^30And the ferret, and the chameleon, and the lizard, and the snail, and the mole.

^31These are unclean to you among all that creep: whosoever doth touch them, when they be dead, shall be unclean until the even.

^32And upon whatsoever any of them, when they are dead, doth fall, it shall be unclean; whether it be any vessel of wood, or raiment, or skin, or sack, whatsoever vessel it be, wherein any work is done, it must be put into water, and it shall be unclean until the even; so it shall be cleansed.

^33And every earthen vessel, whereinto any of them falleth, whatsoever is in it shall be unclean; and ye shall break it.

^34Of all meat which may be eaten, that on which such water cometh shall be unclean: and all drink that may be drunk in every such vessel shall be unclean.

^35And every thing whereupon any part of their carcase falleth shall be unclean; whether it be oven, or ranges for pots, they shall be broken down: for they are unclean and shall be unclean unto you.

^36Nevertheless a fountain or pit, wherein there is plenty of water, shall be clean: but that which toucheth their carcase shall be unclean.

^37And if any part of their carcase fall upon any sowing seed which is to be sown, it shall be clean.

^38But if any water be put upon the seed, and any part of their carcase fall thereon, it shall be unclean unto you.

^39And if any beast, of which ye may eat, die; he that toucheth the carcase thereof shall be unclean until the even.

^40And he that eateth of the carcase of it shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even: he also that beareth the carcase of it shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even.

^41And every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth shall be an abomination; it shall not be eaten.

^42Whatsoever goeth upon the belly, and whatsoever goeth upon all four, or whatsoever hath more feet among all creeping things that creep upon the earth, them ye shall not eat; for they are an abomination.

^43Ye shall not make yourselves abominable with any creeping thing that creepeth, neither shall ye make yourselves unclean with them, that ye should be defiled thereby.

^44For I am the Lord your God: ye shall therefore sanctify yourselves, and ye shall be holy; for I am holy: neither shall ye defile yourselves with any manner of creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth.

^45For I am the Lord that bringeth you up out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: ye shall therefore be holy, for I am holy.

^46This is the law of the beasts, and of the fowl, and of every living creature that moveth in the waters, and of every creature that creepeth upon the earth:

^47To make a difference between the unclean and the clean, and between the beast that may be eaten and the beast that may not be eaten.

XII

12^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, If a woman have conceived seed, and born a man child: then she shall be unclean seven days; according to the days of the separation for her infirmity shall she be unclean.

^3And in the eighth day the flesh of his foreskin shall be circumcised.

^4And she shall then continue in the blood of her purifying three and thirty days; she shall touch no hallowed thing, nor come into the sanctuary, until the days of her purifying be fulfilled.

^5But if she bear a maid child, then she shall be unclean two weeks, as in her separation: and she shall continue in the blood of her purifying threescore and six days.

^6And when the days of her purifying are fulfilled, for a son, or for a daughter, she shall bring a lamb of the first year for a burnt offering, and a young pigeon, or a turtledove, for a sin offering, unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, unto the priest:

^7Who shall offer it before the Lord, and make an atonement for her; and she shall be cleansed from the issue of her blood. This is the law for her that hath born a male or a female.

^8And if she be not able to bring a lamb, then she shall bring two turtles, or two young pigeons; the one for the burnt offering, and the other for a sin offering: and the priest shall make an atonement for her, and she shall be clean.

XIII

13^1And the Lord spake unto Moses and Aaron, saying,

^2When a man shall have in the skin of his flesh a rising, a scab, or bright spot, and it be in the skin of his flesh like the plague of leprosy; then he shall be brought unto Aaron the priest, or unto one of his sons the priests:

^3And the priest shall look on the plague in the skin of the flesh: and when the hair in the plague is turned white, and the plague in sight be deeper than the skin of his flesh, it is a plague of leprosy: and the priest shall look on him, and pronounce him unclean.

^4If the bright spot be white in the skin of his flesh, and in sight be not deeper than the skin, and the hair thereof be not turned white; then the priest shall shut up him that hath the plague seven days:

^5And the priest shall look on him the seventh day: and, behold, if the plague in his sight be at a stay, and the plague spread not in the skin; then the priest shall shut him up seven days more:

^6And the priest shall look on him again the seventh day: and, behold, if the plague be somewhat dark, and the plague spread not in the skin, the priest shall pronounce him clean: it is but a scab: and he shall wash his clothes, and be clean.

^7But if the scab spread much abroad in the skin, after that he hath been seen of the priest for his cleansing, he shall be seen of the priest again.

^8And if the priest see that, behold, the scab spreadeth in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is a leprosy.

^9When the plague of leprosy is in a man, then he shall be brought unto the priest;

^10And the priest shall see him: and, behold, if the rising be white in the skin, and it have turned the hair white, and there be quick raw flesh in the rising;

^11It is an old leprosy in the skin of his flesh, and the priest shall pronounce him unclean, and shall not shut him up: for he is unclean.

^12And if a leprosy break out abroad in the skin, and the leprosy cover all the skin of him that hath the plague from his head even to his foot, wheresoever the priest looketh;

^13Then the priest shall consider: and, behold, if the leprosy have covered all his flesh, he shall pronounce him clean that hath the plague: it is all turned white: he is clean.

^14But when raw flesh appeareth in him, he shall be unclean.

^15And the priest shall see the raw flesh, and pronounce him to be unclean: for the raw flesh is unclean: it is a leprosy.

^16Or if the raw flesh turn again, and be changed unto white, he shall come unto the priest;

^17And the priest shall see him: and, behold, if the plague be turned into white; then the priest shall pronounce him clean that hath the plague: he is clean.

^18The flesh also, in which, even in the skin thereof, was a boil, and is healed,

^19And in the place of the boil there be a white rising, or a bright spot, white, and somewhat reddish, and it be shewed to the priest;

^20And if, when the priest seeth it, behold, it be in sight lower than the skin, and the hair thereof be turned white; the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is a plague of leprosy broken out of the boil.

^21But if the priest look on it, and, behold, there be no white hairs therein, and if it be not lower than the skin, but be somewhat dark; then the priest shall shut him up seven days:

^22And if it spread much abroad in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is a plague.

^23But if the bright spot stay in his place, and spread not, it is a burning boil; and the priest shall pronounce him clean.

^24Or if there be any flesh, in the skin whereof there is a hot burning, and the quick flesh that burneth have a white bright spot, somewhat reddish, or white;

^25Then the priest shall look upon it: and, behold, if the hair in the bright spot be turned white, and it be in sight deeper than the skin; it is a leprosy broken out of the burning: wherefore the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is the plague of leprosy.

^26But if the priest look on it, and, behold, there be no white hair in the bright spot, and it be no lower than the other skin, but be somewhat dark; then the priest shall shut him up seven days:

^27And the priest shall look upon him the seventh day: and if it be spread much abroad in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is the plague of leprosy.

^28And if the bright spot stay in his place, and spread not in the skin, but it be somewhat dark; it is a rising of the burning, and the priest shall pronounce him clean: for it is an inflammation of the burning.

^29If a man or woman have a plague upon the head or the beard;

^30Then the priest shall see the plague: and, behold, if it be in sight deeper than the skin; and there be in it a yellow thin hair; then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is a dry scall, even a leprosy upon the head or beard.

^31And if the priest look on the plague of the scall, and, behold, it be not in sight deeper than the skin, and that there is no black hair in it; then the priest shall shut up him that hath the plague of the scall seven days:

^32And in the seventh day the priest shall look on the plague: and, behold, if the scall spread not, and there be in it no yellow hair, and the scall be not in sight deeper than the skin;

^33He shall be shaven, but the scall shall he not shave; and the priest shall shut up him that hath the scall seven days more:

^34And in the seventh day the priest shall look on the scall: and, behold, if the scall be not spread in the skin, nor be in sight deeper than the skin; then the priest shall pronounce him clean: and he shall wash his clothes, and be clean.

^35But if the scall spread much in the skin after his cleansing;

^36Then the priest shall look on him: and, behold, if the scall be spread in the skin, the priest shall not seek for yellow hair; he is unclean.

^37But if the scall be in his sight at a stay, and that there is black hair grown up therein; the scall is healed, he is clean: and the priest shall pronounce him clean.

^38If a man also or a woman have in the skin of their flesh bright spots, even white bright spots;

^39Then the priest shall look: and, behold, if the bright spots in the skin of their flesh be darkish white; it is a freckled spot that groweth in the skin; he is clean.

^40And the man whose hair is fallen off his head, he is bald; yet is he clean.

^41And he that hath his hair fallen off from the part of his head toward his face, he is forehead bald: yet is he clean.

^42And if there be in the bald head, or bald forehead, a white reddish sore; it is a leprosy sprung up in his bald head, or his bald forehead.

^43Then the priest shall look upon it: and, behold, if the rising of the sore be white reddish in his bald head, or in his bald forehead, as the leprosy appeareth in the skin of the flesh;

^44He is a leprous man, he is unclean: the priest shall pronounce him utterly unclean; his plague is in his head.

^45And the leper in whom the plague is, his clothes shall be rent, and his head bare, and he shall put a covering upon his upper lip, and shall cry, Unclean, unclean.

^46All the days wherein the plague shall be in him he shall be defiled; he is unclean: he shall dwell alone; without the camp shall his habitation be.

^47The garment also that the plague of leprosy is in, whether it be a woollen garment, or a linen garment;

^48Whether it be in the warp, or woof; of linen, or of woollen; whether in a skin, or in any thing made of skin;

^49And if the plague be greenish or reddish in the garment, or in the skin, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in any thing of skin; it is a plague of leprosy, and shall be shewed unto the priest:

^50And the priest shall look upon the plague, and shut up it that hath the plague seven days:

^51And he shall look on the plague on the seventh day: if the plague be spread in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in a skin, or in any work that is made of skin; the plague is a fretting leprosy; it is unclean.

^52He shall therefore burn that garment, whether warp or woof, in woollen or in linen, or any thing of skin, wherein the plague is: for it is a fretting leprosy; it shall be burnt in the fire.

^53And if the priest shall look, and, behold, the plague be not spread in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in any thing of skin;

^54Then the priest shall command that they wash the thing wherein the plague is, and he shall shut it up seven days more:

^55And the priest shall look on the plague, after that it is washed: and, behold, if the plague have not changed his colour, and the plague be not spread; it is unclean; thou shalt burn it in the fire; it is fret inward, whether it be bare within or without.

^56And if the priest look, and, behold, the plague be somewhat dark after the washing of it; then he shall rend it out of the garment, or out of the skin, or out of the warp, or out of the woof:

^57And if it appear still in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in any thing of skin; it is a spreading plague: thou shalt burn that wherein the plague is with fire.

^58And the garment, either warp, or woof, or whatsoever thing of skin it be, which thou shalt wash, if the plague be departed from them, then it shall be washed the second time, and shall be clean.

^59This is the law of the plague of leprosy in a garment of woollen or linen, either in the warp, or woof, or any thing of skins, to pronounce it clean, or to pronounce it unclean.

XIV

14^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2This shall be the law of the leper in the day of his cleansing: He shall be brought unto the priest:

^3And the priest shall go forth out of the camp; and the priest shall look, and, behold, if the plague of leprosy be healed in the leper;

^4Then shall the priest command to take for him that is to be cleansed two birds alive and clean, and cedar wood, and scarlet, and hyssop:

^5And the priest shall command that one of the birds be killed in an earthen vessel over running water:

^6As for the living bird, he shall take it, and the cedar wood, and the scarlet, and the hyssop, and shall dip them and the living bird in the blood of the bird that was killed over the running water:

^7And he shall sprinkle upon him that is to be cleansed from the leprosy seven times, and shall pronounce him clean, and shall let the living bird loose into the open field.

^8And he that is to be cleansed shall wash his clothes, and shave off all his hair, and wash himself in water, that he may be clean: and after that he shall come into the camp, and shall tarry abroad out of his tent seven days.

^9But it shall be on the seventh day, that he shall shave all his hair off his head and his beard and his eyebrows, even all his hair he shall shave off: and he shall wash his clothes, also he shall wash his flesh in water, and he shall be clean.

^10And on the eighth day he shall take two he lambs without blemish, and one ewe lamb of the first year without blemish, and three tenth deals of fine flour for a meat offering, mingled with oil, and one log of oil.

^11And the priest that maketh him clean shall present the man that is to be made clean, and those things, before the Lord, at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation:

^12And the priest shall take one he lamb, and offer him for a trespass offering, and the log of oil, and wave them for a wave offering before the Lord:

^13And he shall slay the lamb in the place where he shall kill the sin offering and the burnt offering, in the holy place: for as the sin offering is the priest’s, so is the trespass offering: it is most holy:

^14And the priest shall take some of the blood of the trespass offering, and the priest shall put it upon the tip of the right ear of him that is to be cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot:

^15And the priest shall take some of the log of oil, and pour it into the palm of his own left hand:

^16And the priest shall dip his right finger in the oil that is in his left hand, and shall sprinkle of the oil with his finger seven times before the Lord:

^17And of the rest of the oil that is in his hand shall the priest put upon the tip of the right ear of him that is to be cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot, upon the blood of the trespass offering:

^18And the remnant of the oil that is in the priest’s hand he shall pour upon the head of him that is to be cleansed: and the priest shall make an atonement for him before the Lord.

^19And the priest shall offer the sin offering, and make an atonement for him that is to be cleansed from his uncleanness; and afterward he shall kill the burnt offering:

^20And the priest shall offer the burnt offering and the meat offering upon the altar: and the priest shall make an atonement for him, and he shall be clean.

^21And if he be poor, and cannot get so much; then he shall take one lamb for a trespass offering to be waved, to make an atonement for him, and one tenth deal of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering, and a log of oil;

^22And two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, such as he is able to get; and the one shall be a sin offering, and the other a burnt offering.

^23And he shall bring them on the eighth day for his cleansing unto the priest, unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, before the Lord.

^24And the priest shall take the lamb of the trespass offering, and the log of oil, and the priest shall wave them for a wave offering before the Lord:

^25And he shall kill the lamb of the trespass offering, and the priest shall take some of the blood of the trespass offering, and put it upon the tip of the right ear of him that is to be cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot:

^26And the priest shall pour of the oil into the palm of his own left hand:

^27And the priest shall sprinkle with his right finger some of the oil that is in his left hand seven times before the Lord:

^28And the priest shall put of the oil that is in his hand upon the tip of the right ear of him that is to be cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot, upon the place of the blood of the trespass offering:

^29And the rest of the oil that is in the priest’s hand he shall put upon the head of him that is to be cleansed, to make an atonement for him before the Lord.

^30And he shall offer the one of the turtledoves, or of the young pigeons, such as he can get;

^31Even such as he is able to get, the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering, with the meat offering: and the priest shall make an atonement for him that is to be cleansed before the Lord.

^32This is the law of him in whom is the plague of leprosy, whose hand is not able to get that which pertaineth to his cleansing.

^33And the Lord spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying,

^34When ye be come into the land of Canaan, which I give to you for a possession, and I put the plague of leprosy in a house of the land of your possession;

^35And he that owneth the house shall come and tell the priest, saying, It seemeth to me there is as it were a plague in the house:

^36Then the priest shall command that they empty the house, before the priest go into it to see the plague, that all that is in the house be not made unclean: and afterward the priest shall go in to see the house:

^37And he shall look on the plague, and, behold, if the plague be in the walls of the house with hollow strakes, greenish or reddish, which in sight are lower than the wall;

^38Then the priest shall go out of the house to the door of the house, and shut up the house seven days:

^39And the priest shall come again the seventh day, and shall look: and, behold, if the plague be spread in the walls of the house;

^40Then the priest shall command that they take away the stones in which the plague is, and they shall cast them into an unclean place without the city:

^41And he shall cause the house to be scraped within round about, and they shall pour out the dust that they scrape off without the city into an unclean place:

^42And they shall take other stones, and put them in the place of those stones; and he shall take other morter, and shall plaister the house.

^43And if the plague come again, and break out in the house, after that he hath taken away the stones, and after he hath scraped the house, and after it is plaistered;

^44Then the priest shall come and look, and, behold, if the plague be spread in the house, it is a fretting leprosy in the house; it is unclean.

^45And he shall break down the house, the stones of it, and the timber thereof, and all the morter of the house; and he shall carry them forth out of the city into an unclean place.

^46Moreover he that goeth into the house all the while that it is shut up shall be unclean until the even.

^47And he that lieth in the house shall wash his clothes; and he that eateth in the house shall wash his clothes.

^48And if the priest shall come in, and look upon it, and, behold, the plague hath not spread in the house, after the house was plaistered: then the priest shall pronounce the house clean, because the plague is healed.

^49And he shall take to cleanse the house two birds, and cedar wood, and scarlet, and hyssop:

^50And he shall kill the one of the birds in an earthen vessel over running water:

^51And he shall take the cedar wood, and the hyssop, and the scarlet, and the living bird, and dip them in the blood of the slain bird, and in the running water, and sprinkle the house seven times:

^52And he shall cleanse the house with the blood of the bird, and with the running water, and with the living bird, and with the cedar wood, and with the hyssop, and with the scarlet:

^53But he shall let go the living bird out of the city into the open fields, and make an atonement for the house: and it shall be clean.

^54This is the law for all manner of plague of leprosy, and scall,

^55And for the leprosy of a garment, and of a house,

^56And for a rising, and for a scab, and for a bright spot:

^57To teach when it is unclean, and when it is clean: this is the law of leprosy.

XV

15^1And the Lord spake unto Moses and to Aaron, saying,

^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When any man hath a running issue out of his flesh, because of his issue he is unclean.

^3And this shall be his uncleanness in his issue: whether his flesh run with his issue, or his flesh be stopped from his issue, it is his uncleanness.

^4Every bed, whereon he lieth that hath the issue, is unclean: and every thing, whereon he sitteth, shall be unclean.

^5And whosoever toucheth his bed shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even.

^6And he that sitteth on any thing whereon he sat that hath the issue shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even.

^7And he that toucheth the flesh of him that hath the issue shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even.

^8And if he that hath the issue spit upon him that is clean; then he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even.

^9And what saddle soever he rideth upon that hath the issue shall be unclean.

^10And whosoever toucheth any thing that was under him shall be unclean until the even: and he that beareth any of those things shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even.

^11And whomsoever he toucheth that hath the issue, and hath not rinsed his hands in water, he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even.

^12And the vessel of earth, that he toucheth which hath the issue, shall be broken: and every vessel of wood shall be rinsed in water.

^13And when he that hath an issue is cleansed of his issue; then he shall number to himself seven days for his cleansing, and wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in running water, and shall be clean.

^14And on the eighth day he shall take to him two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, and come before the Lord unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and give them unto the priest:

^15And the priest shall offer them, the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering; and the priest shall make an atonement for him before the Lord for his issue.

^16And if any man’s seed of copulation go out from him, then he shall wash all his flesh in water, and be unclean until the even.

^17And every garment, and every skin, whereon is the seed of copulation, shall be washed with water, and be unclean until the even.

^18The woman also with whom man shall lie with seed of copulation, they shall both bathe themselves in water, and be unclean until the even.

^19And if a woman have an issue, and her issue in her flesh be blood, she shall be put apart seven days: and whosoever toucheth her shall be unclean until the even.

^20And every thing that she lieth upon in her separation shall be unclean: every thing also that she sitteth upon shall be unclean.

^21And whosoever toucheth her bed shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even.

^22And whosoever toucheth any thing that she sat upon shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even.

^23And if it be on her bed, or on any thing whereon she sitteth, when he toucheth it, he shall be unclean until the even.

^24And if any man lie with her at all, and her flowers be upon him, he shall be unclean seven days; and all the bed whereon he lieth shall be unclean.

^25And if a woman have an issue of her blood many days out of the time of her separation, or if it run beyond the time of her separation; all the days of the issue of her uncleanness shall be as the days of her separation: she shall be unclean.

^26Every bed whereon she lieth all the days of her issue shall be unto her as the bed of her separation: and whatsoever she sitteth upon shall be unclean, as the uncleanness of her separation.

^27And whosoever toucheth those things shall be unclean, and shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even.

^28But if she be cleansed of her issue, then she shall number to herself seven days, and after that she shall be clean.

^29And on the eighth day she shall take unto her two turtles, or two young pigeons, and bring them unto the priest, to the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.

^30And the priest shall offer the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering; and the priest shall make an atonement for her before the Lord for the issue of her uncleanness.

^31Thus shall ye separate the children of Israel from their uncleanness; that they die not in their uncleanness, when they defile my tabernacle that is among them.

^32This is the law of him that hath an issue, and of him whose seed goeth from him, and is defiled therewith;

^33And of her that is sick of her flowers, and of him that hath an issue, of the man, and of the woman, and of him that lieth with her that is unclean.

XVI

16^1And the Lord spake unto Moses after the death of the two sons of Aaron, when they offered before the Lord, and died;

^2And the Lord said unto Moses, Speak unto Aaron thy brother, that he come not at all times into the holy place within the vail before the mercy seat, which is upon the ark; that he die not: for I will appear in the cloud upon the mercy seat.

^3Thus shall Aaron come into the holy place: with a young bullock for a sin offering, and a ram for a burnt offering.

^4He shall put on the holy linen coat, and he shall have the linen breeches upon his flesh, and shall be girded with a linen girdle, and with the linen mitre shall he be attired: these are holy garments; therefore shall he wash his flesh in water, and so put them on.

^5And he shall take of the congregation of the children of Israel two kids of the goats for a sin offering, and one ram for a burnt offering.

^6And Aaron shall offer his bullock of the sin offering, which is for himself, and make an atonement for himself, and for his house.

^7And he shall take the two goats, and present them before the Lord at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.

^8And Aaron shall cast lots upon the two goats; one lot for the Lord, and the other lot for the scapegoat.

^9And Aaron shall bring the goat upon which the Lord’s lot fell, and offer him for a sin offering.

^10But the goat, on which the lot fell to be the scapegoat, shall be presented alive before the Lord, to make an atonement with him, and to let him go for a scapegoat into the wilderness.

^11And Aaron shall bring the bullock of the sin offering, which is for himself, and shall make an atonement for himself, and for his house, and shall kill the bullock of the sin offering which is for himself:

^12And he shall take a censer full of burning coals of fire from off the altar before the Lord, and his hands full of sweet incense beaten small, and bring it within the vail:

^13And he shall put the incense upon the fire before the Lord, that the cloud of the incense may cover the mercy seat that is upon the testimony, that he die not:

^14And he shall take of the blood of the bullock, and sprinkle it with his finger upon the mercy seat eastward; and before the mercy seat shall he sprinkle of the blood with his finger seven times.

^15Then shall he kill the goat of the sin offering, that is for the people, and bring his blood within the vail, and do with that blood as he did with the blood of the bullock, and sprinkle it upon the mercy seat, and before the mercy seat:

^16And he shall make an atonement for the holy place, because of the uncleanness of the children of Israel, and because of their transgressions in all their sins: and so shall he do for the tabernacle of the congregation, that remaineth among them in the midst of their uncleanness.

^17And there shall be no man in the tabernacle of the congregation when he goeth in to make an atonement in the holy place, until he come out, and have made an atonement for himself, and for his household, and for all the congregation of Israel.

^18And he shall go out unto the altar that is before the Lord, and make an atonement for it; and shall take of the blood of the bullock, and of the blood of the goat, and put it upon the horns of the altar round about.

^19And he shall sprinkle of the blood upon it with his finger seven times, and cleanse it, and hallow it from the uncleanness of the children of Israel.

^20And when he hath made an end of reconciling the holy place, and the tabernacle of the congregation, and the altar, he shall bring the live goat:

^21And Aaron shall lay both his hands upon the head of the live goat, and confess over him all the iniquities of the children of Israel, and all their transgressions in all their sins, putting them upon the head of the goat, and shall send him away by the hand of a fit man into the wilderness:

^22And the goat shall bear upon him all their iniquities unto a land not inhabited: and he shall let go the goat in the wilderness.

^23And Aaron shall come into the tabernacle of the congregation, and shall put off the linen garments, which he put on when he went into the holy place, and shall leave them there:

^24And he shall wash his flesh with water in the holy place, and put on his garments, and come forth, and offer his burnt offering, and the burnt offering of the people, and make an atonement for himself, and for the people.

^25And the fat of the sin offering shall he burn upon the altar.

^26And he that let go the goat for the scapegoat shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward come into the camp.

^27And the bullock for the sin offering, and the goat for the sin offering, whose blood was brought in to make atonement in the holy place, shall one carry forth without the camp; and they shall burn in the fire their skins, and their flesh, and their dung.

^28And he that burneth them shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he shall come into the camp.

^29And this shall be a statute for ever unto you: that in the seventh month, on the tenth day of the month, ye shall afflict your souls, and do no work at all, whether it be one of your own country, or a stranger that sojourneth among you:

^30For on that day shall the priest make an atonement for you, to cleanse you, that ye may be clean from all your sins before the Lord.

^31It shall be a sabbath of rest unto you, and ye shall afflict your souls, by a statute for ever.

^32And the priest, whom he shall anoint, and whom he shall consecrate to minister in the priest’s office in his father’s stead, shall make the atonement, and shall put on the linen clothes, even the holy garments:

^33And he shall make an atonement for the holy sanctuary, and he shall make an atonement for the tabernacle of the congregation, and for the altar, and he shall make an atonement for the priests, and for all the people of the congregation.

^34And this shall be an everlasting statute unto you, to make an atonement for the children of Israel for all their sins once a year. And he did as the Lord commanded Moses.

XVII

17^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2Speak unto Aaron, and unto his sons, and unto all the children of Israel, and say unto them; This is the thing which the Lord hath commanded, saying,

^3What man soever there be of the house of Israel, that killeth an ox, or lamb, or goat, in the camp, or that killeth it out of the camp,

^4And bringeth it not unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, to offer an offering unto the Lord before the tabernacle of the Lord; blood shall be imputed unto that man; he hath shed blood; and that man shall be cut off from among his people:

^5To the end that the children of Israel may bring their sacrifices, which they offer in the open field, even that they may bring them unto the Lord, unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, unto the priest, and offer them for peace offerings unto the Lord.

^6And the priest shall sprinkle the blood upon the altar of the Lord at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and burn the fat for a sweet savour unto the Lord.

^7And they shall no more offer their sacrifices unto devils, after whom they have gone a whoring. This shall be a statute for ever unto them throughout their generations.

^8And thou shalt say unto them, Whatsoever man there be of the house of Israel, or of the strangers which sojourn among you, that offereth a burnt offering or sacrifice,

^9And bringeth it not unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, to offer it unto the Lord; even that man shall be cut off from among his people.

^10And whatsoever man there be of the house of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn among you, that eateth any manner of blood; I will even set my face against that soul that eateth blood, and will cut him off from among his people.

^11For the life of the flesh is in the blood: and I have given it to you upon the altar to make an atonement for your souls: for it is the blood that maketh an atonement for the soul.

^12Therefore I said unto the children of Israel, No soul of you shall eat blood, neither shall any stranger that sojourneth among you eat blood.

^13And whatsoever man there be of the children of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn among you, which hunteth and catcheth any beast or fowl that may be eaten; he shall even pour out the blood thereof, and cover it with dust.

^14For it is the life of all flesh; the blood of it is for the life thereof: therefore I said unto the children of Israel, Ye shall eat the blood of no manner of flesh: for the life of all flesh is the blood thereof: whosoever eateth it shall be cut off.

^15And every soul that eateth that which died of itself, or that which was torn with beasts, whether it be one of your own country, or a stranger, he shall both wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the even: then shall he be clean.

^16But if he wash them not, nor bathe his flesh; then he shall bear his iniquity.

XVIII

18^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, I am the Lord your God.

^3After the doings of the land of Egypt, wherein ye dwelt, shall ye not do: and after the doings of the land of Canaan, whither I bring you, shall ye not do: neither shall ye walk in their ordinances.

^4Ye shall do my judgments, and keep mine ordinances, to walk therein: I am the Lord your God.

^5Ye shall therefore keep my statutes, and my judgments: which if a man do, he shall live in them: I am the Lord.

^6None of you shall approach to any that is near of kin to him, to uncover their nakedness: I am the Lord.

^7The nakedness of thy father, or the nakedness of thy mother, shalt thou not uncover: she is thy mother; thou shalt not uncover her nakedness.

^8The nakedness of thy father’s wife shalt thou not uncover: it is thy father’s nakedness.

^9The nakedness of thy sister, the daughter of thy father, or daughter of thy mother, whether she be born at home, or born abroad, even their nakedness thou shalt not uncover.

^10The nakedness of thy son’s daughter, or of thy daughter’s daughter, even their nakedness thou shalt not uncover: for theirs is thine own nakedness.

^11The nakedness of thy father’s wife’s daughter, begotten of thy father, she is thy sister, thou shalt not uncover her nakedness.

^12Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy father’s sister: she is thy father’s near kinswoman.

^13Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy mother’s sister: for she is thy mother’s near kinswoman.

^14Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy father’s brother, thou shalt not approach to his wife: she is thine aunt.

^15Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy daughter in law: she is thy son’s wife; thou shalt not uncover her nakedness.

^16Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy brother’s wife: it is thy brother’s nakedness.

^17Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of a woman and her daughter, neither shalt thou take her son’s daughter, or her daughter’s daughter, to uncover her nakedness; for they are her near kinswomen: it is wickedness.

^18Neither shalt thou take a wife to her sister, to vex her, to uncover her nakedness, beside the other in her life time.

^19Also thou shalt not approach unto a woman to uncover her nakedness, as long as she is put apart for her uncleanness.

^20Moreover thou shalt not lie carnally with thy neighbour’s wife, to defile thyself with her.

^21And thou shalt not let any of thy seed pass through the fire to Molech, neither shalt thou profane the name of thy God: I am the Lord.

^22Thou shalt not lie with mankind, as with womankind: it is abomination.

^23Neither shalt thou lie with any beast to defile thyself therewith: neither shall any woman stand before a beast to lie down thereto: it is confusion.

^24Defile not ye yourselves in any of these things: for in all these the nations are defiled which I cast out before you:

^25And the land is defiled: therefore I do visit the iniquity thereof upon it, and the land itself vomiteth out her inhabitants.

^26Ye shall therefore keep my statutes and my judgments, and shall not commit any of these abominations; neither any of your own nation, nor any stranger that sojourneth among you:

^27(For all these abominations have the men of the land done, which were before you, and the land is defiled;)

^28That the land spue not you out also, when ye defile it, as it spued out the nations that were before you.

^29For whosoever shall commit any of these abominations, even the souls that commit them shall be cut off from among their people.

^30Therefore shall ye keep mine ordinance, that ye commit not any one of these abominable customs, which were committed before you, and that ye defile not yourselves therein: I am the Lord your God.

XIX

19^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2Speak unto all the congregation of the children of Israel, and say unto them, Ye shall be holy: for I the Lord your God am holy.

^3Ye shall fear every man his mother, and his father, and keep my sabbaths: I am the Lord your God.

^4Turn ye not unto idols, nor make to yourselves molten gods: I am the Lord your God.

^5And if ye offer a sacrifice of peace offerings unto the Lord, ye shall offer it at your own will.

^6It shall be eaten the same day ye offer it, and on the morrow: and if ought remain until the third day, it shall be burnt in the fire.

^7And if it be eaten at all on the third day, it is abominable; it shall not be accepted.

^8Therefore every one that eateth it shall bear his iniquity, because he hath profaned the hallowed thing of the Lord: and that soul shall be cut off from among his people.

^9And when ye reap the harvest of your land, thou shalt not wholly reap the corners of thy field, neither shalt thou gather the gleanings of thy harvest.

^10And thou shalt not glean thy vineyard, neither shalt thou gather every grape of thy vineyard; thou shalt leave them for the poor and stranger: I am the Lord your God.

^11Ye shall not steal, neither deal falsely, neither lie one to another.

^12And ye shall not swear by my name falsely, neither shalt thou profane the name of thy God: I am the Lord.

^13Thou shalt not defraud thy neighbour, neither rob him: the wages of him that is hired shall not abide with thee all night until the morning.

^14Thou shalt not curse the deaf, nor put a stumblingblock before the blind, but shalt fear thy God: I am the Lord.

^15Ye shall do no unrighteousness in judgment: thou shalt not respect the person of the poor, nor honor the person of the mighty: but in righteousness shalt thou judge thy neighbour.

^16Thou shalt not go up and down as a talebearer among thy people: neither shalt thou stand against the blood of thy neighbour; I am the Lord.

^17Thou shalt not hate thy brother in thine heart: thou shalt in any wise rebuke thy neighbour, and not suffer sin upon him.

^18Thou shalt not avenge, nor bear any grudge against the children of thy people, but thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself: I am the Lord.

^19Ye shall keep my statutes. Thou shalt not let thy cattle gender with a diverse kind: thou shalt not sow thy field with mingled seed: neither shall a garment mingled of linen and woollen come upon thee.

^20And whosoever lieth carnally with a woman, that is a bondmaid, betrothed to an husband, and not at all redeemed, nor freedom given her; she shall be scourged; they shall not be put to death, because she was not free.

^21And he shall bring his trespass offering unto the Lord, unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, even a ram for a trespass offering.

^22And the priest shall make an atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering before the Lord for his sin which he hath done: and the sin which he hath done shall be forgiven him.

^23And when ye shall come into the land, and shall have planted all manner of trees for food, then ye shall count the fruit thereof as uncircumcised: three years shall it be as uncircumcised unto you: it shall not be eaten of.

^24But in the fourth year all the fruit thereof shall be holy to praise the Lord withal.

^25And in the fifth year shall ye eat of the fruit thereof, that it may yield unto you the increase thereof: I am the Lord your God.

^26Ye shall not eat any thing with the blood: neither shall ye use enchantment, nor observe times.

^27Ye shall not round the corners of your heads, neither shalt thou mar the corners of thy beard.

^28Ye shall not make any cuttings in your flesh for the dead, nor print any marks upon you: I am the Lord.

^29Do not prostitute thy daughter, to cause her to be a whore; lest the land fall to whoredom, and the land become full of wickedness.

^30Ye shall keep my sabbaths, and reverence my sanctuary: I am the Lord.

^31Regard not them that have familiar spirits, neither seek after wizards, to be defiled by them: I am the Lord your God.

^32Thou shalt rise up before the hoary head, and honour the face of the old man, and fear thy God: I am the Lord.

^33And if a stranger sojourn with thee in your land, ye shall not vex him.

^34But the stranger that dwelleth with you shall be unto you as one born among you, and thou shalt love him as thyself; for ye were strangers in the land of Egypt: I am the Lord your God.

^35Ye shall do no unrighteousness in judgment, in meteyard, in weight, or in measure.

^36Just balances, just weights, a just ephah, and a just hin, shall ye have: I am the Lord your God, which brought you out of the land of Egypt.

^37Therefore shall ye observe all my statutes, and all my judgments, and do them: I am the Lord.

XX

20^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2Again, thou shalt say to the children of Israel, Whosoever he be of the children of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn in Israel, that giveth any of his seed unto Molech; he shall surely be put to death: the people of the land shall stone him with stones.

^3And I will set my face against that man, and will cut him off from among his people; because he hath given of his seed unto Molech, to defile my sanctuary, and to profane my holy name.

^4And if the people of the land do any ways hide their eyes from the man, when he giveth of his seed unto Molech, and kill him not:

^5Then I will set my face against that man, and against his family, and will cut him off, and all that go a whoring after him, to commit whoredom with Molech, from among their people.

^6And the soul that turneth after such as have familiar spirits, and after wizards, to go a whoring after them, I will even set my face against that soul, and will cut him off from among his people.

^7Sanctify yourselves therefore, and be ye holy: for I am the Lord your God.

^8And ye shall keep my statutes, and do them: I am the Lord which sanctify you.

^9For every one that curseth his father or his mother shall be surely put to death: he hath cursed his father or his mother; his blood shall be upon him.

^10And the man that committeth adultery with another man’s wife, even he that committeth adultery with his neighbour’s wife, the adulterer and the adulteress shall surely be put to death.

^11And the man that lieth with his father’s wife hath uncovered his father’s nakedness: both of them shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be upon them.

^12And if a man lie with his daughter in law, both of them shall surely be put to death: they have wrought confusion; their blood shall be upon them.

^13If a man also lie with mankind, as he lieth with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination: they shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be upon them.

^14And if a man take a wife and her mother, it is wickedness: they shall be burnt with fire, both he and they; that there be no wickedness among you.

^15And if a man lie with a beast, he shall surely be put to death: and ye shall slay the beast.

^16And if a woman approach unto any beast, and lie down thereto, thou shalt kill the woman, and the beast: they shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be upon them.

^17And if a man shall take his sister, his father’s daughter, or his mother’s daughter, and see her nakedness, and she see his nakedness; it is a wicked thing; and they shall be cut off in the sight of their people: he hath uncovered his sister’s nakedness; he shall bear his iniquity.

^18And if a man shall lie with a woman having her sickness, and shall uncover her nakedness; he hath discovered her fountain, and she hath uncovered the fountain of her blood: and both of them shall be cut off from among their people.

^19And thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy mother’s sister, nor of thy father’s sister: for he uncovereth his near kin: they shall bear their iniquity.

^20And if a man shall lie with his uncle’s wife, he hath uncovered his uncle’s nakedness: they shall bear their sin; they shall die childless.

^21And if a man shall take his brother’s wife, it is an unclean thing: he hath uncovered his brother’s nakedness; they shall be childless.

^22Ye shall therefore keep all my statutes, and all my judgments, and do them: that the land, whither I bring you to dwell therein, spue you not out.

^23And ye shall not walk in the manners of the nation, which I cast out before you: for they committed all these things, and therefore I abhorred them.

^24But I have said unto you, Ye shall inherit their land, and I will give it unto you to possess it, a land that floweth with milk and honey: I am the Lord your God, which have separated you from other people.

^25Ye shall therefore put difference between clean beasts and unclean, and between unclean fowls and clean: and ye shall not make your souls abominable by beast, or by fowl, or by any manner of living thing that creepeth on the ground, which I have separated from you as unclean.

^26And ye shall be holy unto me: for I the Lord am holy, and have severed you from other people, that ye should be mine.

^27A man also or woman that hath a familiar spirit, or that is a wizard, shall surely be put to death: they shall stone them with stones: their blood shall be upon them.

XXI

21^1And the Lord said unto Moses, Speak unto the priests the sons of Aaron, and say unto them, There shall none be defiled for the dead among his people:

^2But for his kin, that is near unto him, that is, for his mother, and for his father, and for his son, and for his daughter, and for his brother.

^3And for his sister a virgin, that is nigh unto him, which hath had no husband; for her may he be defiled.

^4But he shall not defile himself, being a chief man among his people, to profane himself.

^5They shall not make baldness upon their head, neither shall they shave off the corner of their beard, nor make any cuttings in their flesh.

^6They shall be holy unto their God, and not profane the name of their God: for the offerings of the Lord made by fire, and the bread of their God, they do offer: therefore they shall be holy.

^7They shall not take a wife that is a whore, or profane; neither shall they take a woman put away from her husband: for he is holy unto his God.

^8Thou shalt sanctify him therefore; for he offereth the bread of thy God: he shall be holy unto thee: for I the Lord, which sanctify you, am holy.

^9And the daughter of any priest, if she profane herself by playing the whore, she profaneth her father: she shall be burnt with fire.

^10And he that is the high priest among his brethren, upon whose head the anointing oil was poured, and that is consecrated to put on the garments, shall not uncover his head, nor rend his clothes;

^11Neither shall he go in to any dead body, nor defile himself for his father, or for his mother;

^12Neither shall he go out of the sanctuary, nor profane the sanctuary of his God; for the crown of the anointing oil of his God is upon him: I am the Lord.

^13And he shall take a wife in her virginity.

^14A widow, or a divorced woman, or profane, or an harlot, these shall he not take: but he shall take a virgin of his own people to wife.

^15Neither shall he profane his seed among his people: for I the Lord do sanctify him.

^16And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^17Speak unto Aaron, saying, Whosoever he be of thy seed in their generations that hath any blemish, let him not approach to offer the bread of his God.

^18For whatsoever man he be that hath a blemish, he shall not approach: a blind man, or a lame, or he that hath a flat nose, or any thing superfluous,

^19Or a man that is brokenfooted, or brokenhanded,

^20Or crookbackt, or a dwarf, or that hath a blemish in his eye, or be scurvy, or scabbed, or hath his stones broken;

^21No man that hath a blemish of the seed of Aaron the priest shall come nigh to offer the offerings of the Lord made by fire: he hath a blemish; he shall not come nigh to offer the bread of his God.

^22He shall eat the bread of his God, both of the most holy, and of the holy.

^23Only he shall not go in unto the vail, nor come nigh unto the altar, because he hath a blemish; that he profane not my sanctuaries: for I the Lord do sanctify them.

^24And Moses told it unto Aaron, and to his sons, and unto all the children of Israel.

XXII

22^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2Speak unto Aaron and to his sons, that they separate themselves from the holy things of the children of Israel, and that they profane not my holy name in those things which they hallow unto me: I am the Lord.

^3Say unto them, Whosoever he be of all your seed among your generations, that goeth unto the holy things, which the children of Israel hallow unto the Lord, having his uncleanness upon him, that soul shall be cut off from my presence: I am the Lord.

^4What man soever of the seed of Aaron is a leper, or hath a running issue; he shall not eat of the holy things, until he be clean. And whoso toucheth any thing that is unclean by the dead, or a man whose seed goeth from him;

^5Or whosoever toucheth any creeping thing, whereby he may be made unclean, or a man of whom he may take uncleanness, whatsoever uncleanness he hath;

^6The soul which hath touched any such shall be unclean until even, and shall not eat of the holy things, unless he wash his flesh with water.

^7And when the sun is down, he shall be clean, and shall afterward eat of the holy things; because it is his food.

^8That which dieth of itself, or is torn with beasts, he shall not eat to defile himself therewith; I am the Lord.

^9They shall therefore keep mine ordinance, lest they bear sin for it, and die therefore, if they profane it: I the Lord do sanctify them.

^10There shall no stranger eat of the holy thing: a sojourner of the priest, or an hired servant, shall not eat of the holy thing.

^11But if the priest buy any soul with his money, he shall eat of it, and he that is born in his house: they shall eat of his meat.

^12If the priest’s daughter also be married unto a stranger, she may not eat of an offering of the holy things.

^13But if the priest’s daughter be a widow, or divorced, and have no child, and is returned unto her father’s house, as in her youth, she shall eat of her father’s meat: but there shall be no stranger eat thereof.

^14And if a man eat of the holy thing unwittingly, then he shall put the fifth part thereof unto it, and shall give it unto the priest with the holy thing.

^15And they shall not profane the holy things of the children of Israel, which they offer unto the Lord;

^16Or suffer them to bear the iniquity of trespass, when they eat their holy things: for I the Lord do sanctify them.

^17And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^18Speak unto Aaron, and to his sons, and unto all the children of Israel, and say unto them, Whatsoever he be of the house of Israel, or of the strangers in Israel, that will offer his oblation for all his vows, and for all his freewill offerings, which they will offer unto the Lord for a burnt offering;

^19Ye shall offer at your own will a male without blemish, of the beeves, of the sheep, or of the goats.

^20But whatsoever hath a blemish, that shall ye not offer: for it shall not be acceptable for you.

^21And whosoever offereth a sacrifice of peace offerings unto the Lord to accomplish his vow, or a freewill offering in beeves or sheep, it shall be perfect to be accepted; there shall be no blemish therein.

^22Blind, or broken, or maimed, or having a wen, or scurvy, or scabbed, ye shall not offer these unto the Lord, nor make an offering by fire of them upon the altar unto the Lord.

^23Either a bullock or a lamb that hath any thing superfluous or lacking in his parts, that mayest thou offer for a freewill offering; but for a vow it shall not be accepted.

^24Ye shall not offer unto the Lord that which is bruised, or crushed, or broken, or cut; neither shall ye make any offering thereof in your land.

^25Neither from a stranger’s hand shall ye offer the bread of your God of any of these; because their corruption is in them, and blemishes be in them: they shall not be accepted for you.

^26And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^27When a bullock, or a sheep, or a goat, is brought forth, then it shall be seven days under the dam; and from the eighth day and thenceforth it shall be accepted for an offering made by fire unto the Lord.

^28And whether it be cow, or ewe, ye shall not kill it and her young both in one day.

^29And when ye will offer a sacrifice of thanksgiving unto the Lord, offer it at your own will.

^30On the same day it shall be eaten up; ye shall leave none of it until the morrow: I am the Lord.

^31Therefore shall ye keep my commandments, and do them: I am the Lord.

^32Neither shall ye profane my holy name; but I will be hallowed among the children of Israel: I am the Lord which hallow you,

^33That brought you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: I am the Lord.

XXIII

23^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, Concerning the feasts of the Lord, which ye shall proclaim to be holy convocations, even these are my feasts.

^3Six days shall work be done: but the seventh day is the sabbath of rest, an holy convocation; ye shall do no work therein: it is the sabbath of the Lord in all your dwellings.

^4These are the feasts of the Lord, even holy convocations, which ye shall proclaim in their seasons.

^5In the fourteenth day of the first month at even is the Lord’s passover.

^6And on the fifteenth day of the same month is the feast of unleavened bread unto the Lord: seven days ye must eat unleavened bread.

^7In the first day ye shall have an holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work therein.

^8But ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord seven days: in the seventh day is an holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work therein.

^9And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^10Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye be come into the land which I give unto you, and shall reap the harvest thereof, then ye shall bring a sheaf of the firstfruits of your harvest unto the priest:

^11And he shall wave the sheaf before the Lord, to be accepted for you: on the morrow after the sabbath the priest shall wave it.

^12And ye shall offer that day when ye wave the sheaf an he lamb without blemish of the first year for a burnt offering unto the Lord.

^13And the meat offering thereof shall be two tenth deals of fine flour mingled with oil, an offering made by fire unto the Lord for a sweet savour: and the drink offering thereof shall be of wine, the fourth part of an hin.

^14And ye shall eat neither bread, nor parched corn, nor green ears, until the selfsame day that ye have brought an offering unto your God: it shall be a statute for ever throughout your generations in all your dwellings.

^15And ye shall count unto you from the morrow after the sabbath, from the day that ye brought the sheaf of the wave offering; seven sabbaths shall be complete:

^16Even unto the morrow after the seventh sabbath shall ye number fifty days; and ye shall offer a new meat offering unto the Lord.

^17Ye shall bring out of your habitations two wave loaves of two tenth deals; they shall be of fine flour; they shall be baken with leaven; they are the firstfruits unto the Lord.

^18And ye shall offer with the bread seven lambs without blemish of the first year, and one young bullock, and two rams: they shall be for a burnt offering unto the Lord, with their meat offering, and their drink offerings, even an offering made by fire, of sweet savour unto the Lord.

^19Then ye shall sacrifice one kid of the goats for a sin offering, and two lambs of the first year for a sacrifice of peace offerings.

^20And the priest shall wave them with the bread of the firstfruits for a wave offering before the Lord, with the two lambs: they shall be holy to the Lord for the priest.

^21And ye shall proclaim on the selfsame day, that it may be an holy convocation unto you: ye shall do no servile work therein: it shall be a statute for ever in all your dwellings throughout your generations.

^22And when ye reap the harvest of your land, thou shalt not make clean riddance of the corners of thy field when thou reapest, neither shalt thou gather any gleaning of thy harvest: thou shalt leave them unto the poor, and to the stranger: I am the Lord your God.

^23And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^24Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, In the seventh month, in the first day of the month, shall ye have a sabbath, a memorial of blowing of trumpets, an holy convocation.

^25Ye shall do no servile work therein: but ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord.

^26And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^27Also on the tenth day of this seventh month there shall be a day of atonement: it shall be an holy convocation unto you; and ye shall afflict your souls, and offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord.

^28And ye shall do no work in that same day: for it is a day of atonement, to make an atonement for you before the Lord your God.

^29For whatsoever soul it be that shall not be afflicted in that same day, he shall be cut off from among his people.

^30And whatsoever soul it be that doeth any work in that same day, the same soul will I destroy from among his people.

^31Ye shall do no manner of work: it shall be a statute for ever throughout your generations in all your dwellings.

^32It shall be unto you a sabbath of rest, and ye shall afflict your souls: in the ninth day of the month at even, from even unto even, shall ye celebrate your sabbath.

^33And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^34Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, The fifteenth day of this seventh month shall be the feast of tabernacles for seven days unto the Lord.

^35On the first day shall be an holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work therein.

^36Seven days ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord: on the eighth day shall be an holy convocation unto you; and ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord: it is a solemn assembly; and ye shall do no servile work therein.

^37These are the feasts of the Lord, which ye shall proclaim to be holy convocations, to offer an offering made by fire unto the Lord, a burnt offering, and a meat offering, a sacrifice, and drink offerings, every thing upon his day:

^38Beside the sabbaths of the Lord, and beside your gifts, and beside all your vows, and beside all your freewill offerings, which ye give unto the Lord.

^39Also in the fifteenth day of the seventh month, when ye have gathered in the fruit of the land, ye shall keep a feast unto the Lord seven days: on the first day shall be a sabbath, and on the eighth day shall be a sabbath.

^40And ye shall take you on the first day the boughs of goodly trees, branches of palm trees, and the boughs of thick trees, and willows of the brook; and ye shall rejoice before the Lord your God seven days.

^41And ye shall keep it a feast unto the Lord seven days in the year. It shall be a statute for ever in your generations: ye shall celebrate it in the seventh month.

^42Ye shall dwell in booths seven days; all that are Israelites born shall dwell in booths:

^43That your generations may know that I made the children of Israel to dwell in booths, when I brought them out of the land of Egypt: I am the Lord your God.

^44And Moses declared unto the children of Israel the feasts of the Lord.

XXIV

24^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2Command the children of Israel, that they bring unto thee pure oil olive beaten for the light, to cause the lamps to burn continually.

^3Without the vail of the testimony, in the tabernacle of the congregation, shall Aaron order it from the evening unto the morning before the Lord continually: it shall be a statute for ever in your generations.

^4He shall order the lamps upon the pure candlestick before the Lord continually.

^5And thou shalt take fine flour, and bake twelve cakes thereof: two tenth deals shall be in one cake.

^6And thou shalt set them in two rows, six on a row, upon the pure table before the Lord.

^7And thou shalt put pure frankincense upon each row, that it may be on the bread for a memorial, even an offering made by fire unto the Lord.

^8Every sabbath he shall set it in order before the Lord continually, being taken from the children of Israel by an everlasting covenant.

^9And it shall be Aaron’s and his sons’; and they shall eat it in the holy place: for it is most holy unto him of the offerings of the Lord made by fire by a perpetual statute.

^10And the son of an Israelitish woman, whose father was an Egyptian, went out among the children of Israel: and this son of the Israelitish woman and a man of Israel strove together in the camp;

^11And the Israelitish woman’s son blasphemed the name of the Lord, and cursed. And they brought him unto Moses: (and his mother’s name was Shelomith, the daughter of Dibri, of the tribe of Dan:)

^12And they put him in ward, that the mind of the Lord might be shewed them.

^13And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^14Bring forth him that hath cursed without the camp; and let all that heard him lay their hands upon his head, and let all the congregation stone him.

^15And thou shalt speak unto the children of Israel, saying, Whosoever curseth his God shall bear his sin.

^16And he that blasphemeth the name of the Lord, he shall surely be put to death, and all the congregation shall certainly stone him: as well the stranger, as he that is born in the land, when he blasphemeth the name of the Lord, shall be put to death.

^17And he that killeth any man shall surely be put to death.

^18And he that killeth a beast shall make it good; beast for beast.

^19And if a man cause a blemish in his neighbour; as he hath done, so shall it be done to him;

^20Breach for breach, eye for eye, tooth for tooth: as he hath caused a blemish in a man, so shall it be done to him again.

^21And he that killeth a beast, he shall restore it: and he that killeth a man, he shall be put to death.

^22Ye shall have one manner of law, as well for the stranger, as for one of your own country: for I am the Lord your God.

^23And Moses spake to the children of Israel, that they should bring forth him that had cursed out of the camp, and stone him with stones. And the children of Israel did as the Lord commanded Moses.

XXV

25^1And the Lord spake unto Moses in mount Sinai, saying,

^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye come into the land which I give you, then shall the land keep a sabbath unto the Lord.

^3Six years thou shalt sow thy field, and six years thou shalt prune thy vineyard, and gather in the fruit thereof;

^4But in the seventh year shall be a sabbath of rest unto the land, a sabbath for the Lord: thou shalt neither sow thy field, nor prune thy vineyard.

^5That which groweth of its own accord of thy harvest thou shalt not reap, neither gather the grapes of thy vine undressed: for it is a year of rest unto the land.

^6And the sabbath of the land shall be meat for you; for thee, and for thy servant, and for thy maid, and for thy hired servant, and for thy stranger that sojourneth with thee.

^7And for thy cattle, and for the beast that are in thy land, shall all the increase thereof be meat.

^8And thou shalt number seven sabbaths of years unto thee, seven times seven years; and the space of the seven sabbaths of years shall be unto thee forty and nine years.

^9Then shalt thou cause the trumpet of the jubile to sound on the tenth day of the seventh month, in the day of atonement shall ye make the trumpet sound throughout all your land.

^10And ye shall hallow the fiftieth year, and proclaim liberty throughout all the land unto all the inhabitants thereof: it shall be a jubile unto you; and ye shall return every man unto his possession, and ye shall return every man unto his family.

^11A jubile shall that fiftieth year be unto you: ye shall not sow, neither reap that which groweth of itself in it, nor gather the grapes in it of thy vine undressed.

^12For it is the jubile; it shall be holy unto you: ye shall eat the increase thereof out of the field.

^13In the year of this jubile ye shall return every man unto his possession.

^14And if thou sell ought unto thy neighbour, or buyest ought of thy neighbour’s hand, ye shall not oppress one another:

^15According to the number of years after the jubile thou shalt buy of thy neighbour, and according unto the number of years of the fruits he shall sell unto thee:

^16According to the multitude of years thou shalt increase the price thereof, and according to the fewness of years thou shalt diminish the price of it: for according to the number of the years of the fruits doth he sell unto thee.

^17Ye shall not therefore oppress one another; but thou shalt fear thy God: for I am the Lord your God.

^18Wherefore ye shall do my statutes, and keep my judgments, and do them; and ye shall dwell in the land in safety.

^19And the land shall yield her fruit, and ye shall eat your fill, and dwell therein in safety.

^20And if ye shall say, What shall we eat the seventh year? behold, we shall not sow, nor gather in our increase:

^21Then I will command my blessing upon you in the sixth year, and it shall bring forth fruit for three years.

^22And ye shall sow the eighth year, and eat yet of old fruit until the ninth year; until her fruits come in ye shall eat of the old store.

^23The land shall not be sold for ever: for the land is mine, for ye are strangers and sojourners with me.

^24And in all the land of your possession ye shall grant a redemption for the land.

^25If thy brother be waxen poor, and hath sold away some of his possession, and if any of his kin come to redeem it, then shall he redeem that which his brother sold.

^26And if the man have none to redeem it, and himself be able to redeem it;

^27Then let him count the years of the sale thereof, and restore the overplus unto the man to whom he sold it; that he may return unto his possession.

^28But if he be not able to restore it to him, then that which is sold shall remain in the hand of him that hath bought it until the year of jubile: and in the jubile it shall go out, and he shall return unto his possession.

^29And if a man sell a dwelling house in a walled city, then he may redeem it within a whole year after it is sold; within a full year may he redeem it.

^30And if it be not redeemed within the space of a full year, then the house that is in the walled city shall be established for ever to him that bought it throughout his generations: it shall not go out in the jubile.

^31But the houses of the villages which have no wall round about them shall be counted as the fields of the country: they may be redeemed, and they shall go out in the jubile.

^32Notwithstanding the cities of the Levites, and the houses of the cities of their possession, may the Levites redeem at any time.

^33And if a man purchase of the Levites, then the house that was sold, and the city of his possession, shall go out in the year of jubile: for the houses of the cities of the Levites are their possession among the children of Israel.

^34But the field of the suburbs of their cities may not be sold; for it is their perpetual possession.

^35And if thy brother be waxen poor, and fallen in decay with thee; then thou shalt relieve him: yea, though he be a stranger, or a sojourner; that he may live with thee.

^36Take thou no usury of him, or increase: but fear thy God; that thy brother may live with thee.

^37Thou shalt not give him thy money upon usury, nor lend him thy victuals for increase.

^38I am the Lord your God, which brought you forth out of the land of Egypt, to give you the land of Canaan, and to be your God.

^39And if thy brother that dwelleth by thee be waxen poor, and be sold unto thee; thou shalt not compel him to serve as a bondservant:

^40But as an hired servant, and as a sojourner, he shall be with thee, and shall serve thee unto the year of jubile.

^41And then shall he depart from thee, both he and his children with him, and shall return unto his own family, and unto the possession of his fathers shall he return.

^42For they are my servants, which I brought forth out of the land of Egypt: they shall not be sold as bondmen.

^43Thou shalt not rule over him with rigour; but shalt fear thy God.

^44Both thy bondmen, and thy bondmaids, which thou shalt have, shall be of the heathen that are round about you; of them shall ye buy bondmen and bondmaids.

^45Moreover of the children of the strangers that do sojourn among you, of them shall ye buy, and of their families that are with you, which they begat in your land: and they shall be your possession.

^46And ye shall take them as an inheritance for your children after you, to inherit them for a possession; they shall be your bondmen for ever: but over your brethren the children of Israel, ye shall not rule one over another with rigour.

^47And if a sojourner or stranger wax rich by thee, and thy brother that dwelleth by him wax poor, and sell himself unto the stranger or sojourner by thee, or to the stock of the stranger’s family:

^48After that he is sold he may be redeemed again; one of his brethren may redeem him:

^49Either his uncle, or his uncle’s son, may redeem him, or any that is nigh of kin unto him of his family may redeem him; or if he be able, he may redeem himself.

^50And he shall reckon with him that bought him from the year that he was sold to him unto the year of jubile: and the price of his sale shall be according unto the number of years, according to the time of an hired servant shall it be with him.

^51If there be yet many years behind, according unto them he shall give again the price of his redemption out of the money that he was bought for.

^52And if there remain but few years unto the year of jubile, then he shall count with him, and according unto his years shall he give him again the price of his redemption.

^53And as a yearly hired servant shall he be with him: and the other shall not rule with rigour over him in thy sight.

^54And if he be not redeemed in these years, then he shall go out in the year of jubile, both he, and his children with him.

^55For unto me the children of Israel are servants; they are my servants whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt: I am the Lord your God.

XXVI

26^1Ye shall make you no idols nor graven image, neither rear you up a standing image, neither shall ye set up any image of stone in your land, to bow down unto it: for I am the Lord your God.

^2Ye shall keep my sabbaths, and reverence my sanctuary: I am the Lord.

^3If ye walk in my statutes, and keep my commandments, and do them;

^4Then I will give you rain in due season, and the land shall yield her increase, and the trees of the field shall yield their fruit.

^5And your threshing shall reach unto the vintage, and the vintage shall reach unto the sowing time: and ye shall eat your bread to the full, and dwell in your land safely.

^6And I will give peace in the land, and ye shall lie down, and none shall make you afraid: and I will rid evil beasts out of the land, neither shall the sword go through your land.

^7And ye shall chase your enemies, and they shall fall before you by the sword.

^8And five of you shall chase an hundred, and an hundred of you shall put ten thousand to flight: and your enemies shall fall before you by the sword.

^9For I will have respect unto you, and make you fruitful, and multiply you, and establish my covenant with you.

^10And ye shall eat old store, and bring forth the old because of the new.

^11And I set my tabernacle among you: and my soul shall not abhor you.

^12And I will walk among you, and will be your God, and ye shall be my people.

^13I am the Lord your God, which brought you forth out of the land of Egypt, that ye should not be their bondmen; and I have broken the bands of your yoke, and made you go upright.

^14But if ye will not hearken unto me, and will not do all these commandments;

^15And if ye shall despise my statutes, or if your soul abhor my judgments, so that ye will not do all my commandments, but that ye break my covenant:

^16I also will do this unto you; I will even appoint over you terror, consumption, and the burning ague, that shall consume the eyes, and cause sorrow of heart: and ye shall sow your seed in vain, for your enemies shall eat it.

^17And I will set my face against you, and ye shall be slain before your enemies: they that hate you shall reign over you; and ye shall flee when none pursueth you.

^18And if ye will not yet for all this hearken unto me, then I will punish you seven times more for your sins.

^19And I will break the pride of your power; and I will make your heaven as iron, and your earth as brass:

^20And your strength shall be spent in vain: for your land shall not yield her increase, neither shall the trees of the land yield their fruits.

^21And if ye walk contrary unto me, and will not hearken unto me; I will bring seven times more plagues upon you according to your sins.

^22I will also send wild beasts among you, which shall rob you of your children, and destroy your cattle, and make you few in number; and your high ways shall be desolate.

^23And if ye will not be reformed by me by these things, but will walk contrary unto me;

^24Then will I also walk contrary unto you, and will punish you yet seven times for your sins.

^25And I will bring a sword upon you, that shall avenge the quarrel of my covenant: and when ye are gathered together within your cities, I will send the pestilence among you; and ye shall be delivered into the hand of the enemy.

^26And when I have broken the staff of your bread, ten women shall bake your bread in one oven, and they shall deliver you your bread again by weight: and ye shall eat, and not be satisfied.

^27And if ye will not for all this hearken unto me, but walk contrary unto me;

^28Then I will walk contrary unto you also in fury; and I, even I, will chastise you seven times for your sins.

^29And ye shall eat the flesh of your sons, and the flesh of your daughters shall ye eat.

^30And I will destroy your high places, and cut down your images, and cast your carcases upon the carcases of your idols, and my soul shall abhor you.

^31And I will make your cities waste, and bring your sanctuaries unto desolation, and I will not smell the savour of your sweet odours.

^32And I will bring the land into desolation: and your enemies which dwell therein shall be astonished at it.

^33And I will scatter you among the heathen, and will draw out a sword after you: and your land shall be desolate, and your cities waste.

^34Then shall the land enjoy her sabbaths, as long as it lieth desolate, and ye be in your enemies’ land; even then shall the land rest, and enjoy her sabbaths.

^35As long as it lieth desolate it shall rest; because it did not rest in your sabbaths, when ye dwelt upon it.

^36And upon them that are left alive of you I will send a faintness into their hearts in the lands of their enemies; and the sound of a shaken leaf shall chase them; and they shall flee, as fleeing from a sword; and they shall fall when none pursueth.

^37And they shall fall one upon another, as it were before a sword, when none pursueth: and ye shall have no power to stand before your enemies.

^38And ye shall perish among the heathen, and the land of your enemies shall eat you up.

^39And they that are left of you shall pine away in their iniquity in your enemies’ lands; and also in the iniquities of their fathers shall they pine away with them.

^40If they shall confess their iniquity, and the iniquity of their fathers, with their trespass which they trespassed against me, and that also they have walked contrary unto me;

^41And that I also have walked contrary unto them, and have brought them into the land of their enemies; if then their uncircumcised hearts be humbled, and they then accept of the punishment of their iniquity:

^42Then will I remember my covenant with Jacob, and also my covenant with Isaac, and also my covenant with Abraham will I remember; and I will remember the land.

^43The land also shall be left of them, and shall enjoy her sabbaths, while she lieth desolate without them: and they shall accept of the punishment of their iniquity: because, even because they despised my judgments, and because their soul abhorred my statutes.

^44And yet for all that, when they be in the land of their enemies, I will not cast them away, neither will I abhor them, to destroy them utterly, and to break my covenant with them: for I am the Lord their God.

^45But I will for their sakes remember the covenant of their ancestors, whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt in the sight of the heathen, that I might be their God: I am the Lord.

^46These are the statutes and judgments and laws, which the Lord made between him and the children of Israel in mount Sinai by the hand of Moses.

XXVII

27^1And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,

^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When a man shall make a singular vow, the persons shall be for the Lord by thy estimation.

^3And thy estimation shall be of the male from twenty years old even unto sixty years old, even thy estimation shall be fifty shekels of silver, after the shekel of the sanctuary.

^4And if it be a female, then thy estimation shall be thirty shekels.

^5And if it be from five years old even unto twenty years old, then thy estimation shall be of the male twenty shekels, and for the female ten shekels.

^6And if it be from a month old even unto five years old, then thy estimation shall be of the male five shekels of silver, and for the female thy estimation shall be three shekels of silver.

^7And if it be from sixty years old and above; if it be a male, then thy estimation shall be fifteen shekels, and for the female ten shekels.

^8But if he be poorer than thy estimation, then he shall present himself before the priest, and the priest shall value him; according to his ability that vowed shall the priest value him.

^9And if it be a beast, whereof men bring an offering unto the Lord, all that any man giveth of such unto the Lord shall be holy.

^10He shall not alter it, nor change it, a good for a bad, or a bad for a good: and if he shall at all change beast for beast, then it and the exchange thereof shall be holy.

^11And if it be any unclean beast, of which they do not offer a sacrifice unto the Lord, then he shall present the beast before the priest:

^12And the priest shall value it, whether it be good or bad: as thou valuest it, who art the priest, so shall it be.

^13But if he will at all redeem it, then he shall add a fifth part thereof unto thy estimation.

^14And when a man shall sanctify his house to be holy unto the Lord, then the priest shall estimate it, whether it be good or bad: as the priest shall estimate it, so shall it stand.

^15And if he that sanctified it will redeem his house, then he shall add the fifth part of the money of thy estimation unto it, and it shall be his.

^16And if a man shall sanctify unto the Lord some part of a field of his possession, then thy estimation shall be according to the seed thereof: an homer of barley seed shall be valued at fifty shekels of silver.

^17If he sanctify his field from the year of jubile, according to thy estimation it shall stand.

^18But if he sanctify his field after the jubile, then the priest shall reckon unto him the money according to the years that remain, even unto the year of the jubile, and it shall be abated from thy estimation.

^19And if he that sanctified the field will in any wise redeem it, then he shall add the fifth part of the money of thy estimation unto it, and it shall be assured to him.

^20And if he will not redeem the field, or if he have sold the field to another man, it shall not be redeemed any more.

^21But the field, when it goeth out in the jubile, shall be holy unto the Lord, as a field devoted; the possession thereof shall be the priest’s.

^22And if a man sanctify unto the Lord a field which he hath bought, which is not of the fields of his possession;

^23Then the priest shall reckon unto him the worth of thy estimation, even unto the year of the jubile: and he shall give thine estimation in that day, as a holy thing unto the Lord.

^24In the year of the jubile the field shall return unto him of whom it was bought, even to him to whom the possession of the land did belong.

^25And all thy estimations shall be according to the shekel of the sanctuary: twenty gerahs shall be the shekel.

^26Only the firstling of the beasts, which should be the Lord’s firstling, no man shall sanctify it; whether it be ox, or sheep: it is the Lord’s.

^27And if it be of an unclean beast, then he shall redeem it according to thine estimation, and shall add a fifth part of it thereto: or if it be not redeemed, then it shall be sold according to thy estimation.

^28Notwithstanding no devoted thing, that a man shall devote unto the Lord of all that he hath, both of man and beast, and of the field of his possession, shall be sold or redeemed: every devoted thing is most holy unto the Lord.

^29None devoted, which shall be devoted of men, shall be redeemed; but shall surely be put to death.

^30And all the tithe of the land, whether of the seed of the land, or of the fruit of the tree, is the Lord’s: it is holy unto the Lord.

^31And if a man will at all redeem ought of his tithes, he shall add thereto the fifth part thereof.

^32And concerning the tithe of the herd, or of the flock, even of whatsoever passeth under the rod, the tenth shall be holy unto the Lord.

^33He shall not search whether it be good or bad, neither shall he change it: and if he change it at all, then both it and the change thereof shall be holy; it shall not be redeemed.

^34These are the commandments, which the Lord commanded Moses for the children of Israel in mount Sinai.

Joshua

The Book of

Joshua

I

^1Now after the death of Moses the servant of the Lord it came to pass, that the Lord spake unto Joshua the son of Nun, Moses’ minister, saying, ^2Moses my servant is dead; now therefore arise, go over this Jordan, thou, and all this people, unto the land which I do give to them, even to the children of Israel. ^3Every place that the sole of your foot shall tread upon, that have I given unto you, as I said unto Moses. ^4From the wilderness and this Lebanon even unto the great river, the river Euphrates, all the land of the Hittites, and unto the great sea toward the going down of the sun, shall be your coast. ^5There shall not any man be able to stand before thee all the days of thy life: as I was with Moses, so I will be with thee: I will not fail thee, nor forsake thee. ^6Be strong and of a good courage: for unto this people shalt thou divide for an inheritance the land, which I sware unto their fathers to give them. ^7Only be thou strong and very courageous, that thou mayest observe to do according to all the law, which Moses my servant commanded thee: turn not from it to the right hand or to the left, that thou mayest prosper withersoever thou goest. ^8This book of the law shall not depart out of thy mouth; but thou shalt meditate therein day and night, that thou mayest observe to do according to all that is written therein: for then thou shalt make thy way prosperous, and then thou shalt have good success. ^9Have not I commanded thee? Be strong and of a good courage; be not afraid, neither be thou dismayed: for the Lord thy God is with thee whithersoever thou goest.

^10Then Joshua commanded the officers of the people, saying, ^11Pass through the host, and command the people, saying, Prepare you victuals; for within three days ye shall pass over this Jordan, to go in to possess the land, which the Lord your God giveth you to possess it.

^12And to the Reubenites, and to the Gadites, and to half the tribe of Manasseh, spake Joshua, saying, ^13Remember the word which Moses the servant of the Lord commanded you, saying, The Lord your God hath given you rest, and hath given you this land. ^14Your wives, your little ones, and your cattle, shall remain in the land which Moses gave you on this side Jordan; but ye shall pass before your brethren armed, all the mighty men of valour, and help them; ^15until the Lord have given your brethren rest, as he hath given you, and they also have possessed the land which the Lord your God giveth them: then ye shall return unto the land of your possession, and enjoy it, which Moses the Lord’s servant gave you on this side Jordan toward the sunrising. ^16And they answered Joshua, saying, All that thou commandest us we will do, and whithersoever thou sendest us, we will go. ^17According as we hearkened unto Moses in all things, so will we hearken unto thee: only the Lord thy God be with thee, as he was with Moses. ^18Whosoever he be that doth rebel against thy commandment, and will not hearken unto thy words in all that thou commandest him, he shall be put to death: only be strong and of a good courage.

II

^1And Joshua the son of Nun sent out of Shittim two men to spy secretly, saying, Go view the land, even Jericho. And they went, and came into an harlot’s house, named Rahab, and lodged there. ^2And it was told the king of Jericho, saying, Behold, there came men in hither to night of the children of Israel to search out the country. ^3And the king of Jericho sent unto Rahab, saying, Bring forth the men that are come to thee, which are entered into thine house: for they be come to search out all the country. ^4And the woman took the two men, and hid them, and said thus, There came men unto me, but I wist not whence they were: ^5and it came to pass about the time of shutting of the gate, when it was dark, that the men went out: whither the men went I wot not: pursue after them quickly; for ye shall overtake them. ^6But she had brought them up to the roof of the house, and hid them with the stalks of flax, which she had laid in order upon the roof. ^7And the men pursued after them the way to Jordan unto the fords: and as soon as they which pursued after them were gone out, they shut the gate.

^8And before they were laid down, she came up unto them upon the roof; ^9and she said unto the men, I know that the Lord hath given you the land, and that your terror is fallen upon us, and that all the inhabitants of the land faint because of you. ^10For we have heard how the Lord dried up the water of the Red sea for you, when ye came out of Egypt; and what ye did unto the two kings of the Amorites, that were on the other side Jordan, Sihon and Og, whom ye utterly destroyed. ^11And as soon as we had heard these things, our hearts did melt, neither did there remain any more courage in any man, because of you: for the Lord your God, he is God in heaven above, and in earth beneath. ^12Now therefore, I pray you, swear unto me by the Lord, since I have shewed you kindness, that ye will also shew kindness unto my father’s house, and give me a true token: ^13and that ye will save alive my father, and my mother, and my brethren, and my sisters, and all that they have, and deliver our lives from death. ^14And the men answered her, Our life for yours, if ye utter not this our business. And it shall be, when the Lord hath given us the land, that we will deal kindly and truly with thee.

^15Then she let them down by a cord through the window: for her house was upon the town wall, and she dwelt upon the wall. ^16And she said unto them, Get you to the mountain, lest the pursuers meet you; and hide yourselves there three days, until the pursuers be returned: and afterward may ye go your way. ^17And the men said unto her, We will be blameless of this thine oath which thou hast made us swear. ^18Behold, when we come into the land, thou shalt bind this line of scarlet thread in the window which thou didst let us down by: and thou shalt bring thy father, and thy mother, and thy brethren, and all thy father’s household, home unto thee. ^19And it shall be, that whosoever shall go out of the doors of thy house into the street, his blood shall be upon his head, and we will be guiltless: and whosoever shall be with thee in the house, his blood shall be on our head, if any hand be upon him. ^20And if thou utter this our business, then we will be quit of thine oath which thou hast made us to swear. ^21And she said, According unto your words, so be it. And she sent them away, and they departed: and she bound the scarlet line in the window.

^22And they went, and came unto the mountain, and abode there three days, until the pursuers were returned: and the pursuers sought them throughout all the way, but found them not. ^23So the two men returned, and descended from the mountain, and passed over, and came to Joshua the son of Nun, and told him all things that befell them: ^24and they said unto Joshua, Truly the Lord hath delivered into our hands all the land; for even all the inhabitants of the country do faint because of us.

III

^1And Joshua rose early in the morning; and they removed from Shittim, and came to Jordan, he and all the children of Israel, and lodged there before they passed over. ^2And it came to pass after three days, that the officers went through the host; ^3and they commanded the people, saying, When ye see the ark of the covenant of the Lord your God, and the priests the Levites bearing it, then ye shall remove from your place, and go after it. ^4Yet there shall be a space between you and it, about two thousand cubits by measure: come not near unto it, that ye may know the way by which ye must go: for ye have not passed this way heretofore. ^5And Joshua said unto the people, Sanctify yourselves: for to morrow the Lord will do wonders among you. ^6And Joshua spake unto the priests, saying, Take up the ark of the covenant, and pass over before the people. And they took up the ark of the covenant, and went before the people.

^7And the Lord said unto Joshua, This day will I begin to magnify thee in the sight of all Israel, that they may know that, as I was with Moses, so I will be with thee. ^8And thou shalt command the priests that bear the ark of the covenant, saying, When ye are come to the brink of the water of Jordan, ye shall stand still in Jordan. ^9And Joshua said unto the children of Israel, Come hither, and hear the words of the Lord your God. ^10And Joshua said, Hereby ye shall know that the living God is among you, and that he will without fail drive out from before you the Canaanites, and the Hittites, and the Hivites, and the Perizzites, and the Girgashites, and the Amorites, and the Jebusites. ^11Behold, the ark of the covenant of the Lord of all the earth passeth over before you into Jordan. ^12Now therefore take you twelve men out of the tribes of Israel, out of every tribe a man. ^13And it shall come to pass, as soon as the soles of the feet of the priests that bear the ark of the Lord, the Lord of all the earth, shall rest in the waters of Jordan, that the waters of Jordan shall be cut off from the waters that come down from above; and they shall stand upon an heap.

^14And it came to pass, when the people removed from their tents, to pass over Jordan, and the priests bearing the ark of the covenant before the people; ^15and as they that bare the ark were come unto Jordan, and the feet of the priests that bare the ark were dipped in the brim of the water, (for Jordan overfloweth all his banks all the time of harvest,) ^16that the waters which came down from above stood and rose up upon an heap very far from the city Adam, that is beside Zaretan: and those that came down toward the sea of the plain, even the salt sea, failed, and were cut off: and the people passed over right against Jericho. ^17And the priests that bare the ark of the covenant of the Lord stood firm on dry ground in the midst of Jordan, and all the Israelites passed over on dry ground, until all the people were passed clean over Jordan.

IV

^1And it came to pass, when all the people were clean passed over Jordan, that the Lord spake unto Joshua, saying, ^2Take you twelve men out of the people, out of every tribe a man, ^3and command ye them, saying, Take you hence out of the midst of Jordan, out of the place where the priests’ feet stood firm, twelve stones, and ye shall carry them over with you, and leave them in the lodging place, where ye shall lodge this night. ^4Then Joshua called the twelve men, whom he had prepared of the children of Israel, out of every tribe a man: ^5and Joshua said unto them, Pass over before the ark of the Lord your God into the midst of Jordan, and take you up every man of you a stone upon his shoulder, according unto the number of the tribes of the children of Israel: ^6that this may be a sign among you, that when your children ask their fathers in time to come, saying, What mean ye by these stones? ^7Then ye shall answer them, That the waters of Jordan were cut off before the ark of the covenant of the Lord; when it passed over Jordan, the waters of Jordan were cut off: and these stones shall be for a memorial unto the children of Israel for ever.

^8And the children of Israel did so as Joshua commanded, and took up twelve stones out of the midst of Jordan, as the Lord spake unto Joshua, according to the number of the tribes of the children of Israel, and carried them over with them unto the place where they lodged, and laid them down there. ^9And Joshua set up twelve stones in the midst of Jordan, in the place where the feet of the priests which bare the ark of the covenant stood: and they are there unto this day. ^10For the priests which bare the ark stood in the midst of Jordan, until everything was finished that the Lord commanded Joshua to speak unto the people, according to all that Moses commanded Joshua: and the people hasted and passed over. ^11And it came to pass, when all the people were clean passed over, that the ark of the Lord passed over, and the priests, in the presence of the people. ^12And the children of Reuben, and the children of Gad, and half the tribe of Manasseh, passed over armed before the children of Israel, as Moses spake unto them: ^13about forty thousand prepared for war passed over before the Lord unto battle, to the plains of Jericho. ^14On that day the Lord magnified Joshua in the sight of all Israel; and they feared him, as they feared Moses, all the days of his life.

^15And the Lord spake unto Joshua, saying, ^16Command the priests that bear the ark of the testimony, that they come up out of Jordan. ^17Joshua therefore commanded the priests, saying, Come ye up out of Jordan. ^18And it came to pass, when the priests that bare the ark of the covenant of the Lord were come up out of the midst of Jordan, and the soles of the priests’ feet were lifted up unto the dry land, that the waters of Jordan returned unto their place, and flowed over all his banks, as they did before.

^19And the people came up out of Jordan on the tenth day of the first month, and encamped in Gilgal, in the east border of Jericho. ^20And those twelve stones, which they took out of Jordan, did Joshua pitch in Gilgal. ^21And he spake unto the children of Israel, saying, When your children shall ask their fathers in time to come, saying, What mean these stones? ^22Then ye shall let your children know, saying, Israel came over this Jordan on dry land. ^23For the Lord your God dried up the waters of Jordan from before you, until ye were passed over, as the Lord your God did to the Red sea, which he dried up from before us, until we were gone over: ^24that all the people of the earth might know the hand of the Lord, that it is mighty: that ye might fear the Lord your God for ever.

V

^1And it came to pass, when all the kings of the Amorites, which were on the side of Jordan westward, and all the kings of the Canaanites, which were by the sea, heard that the Lord had dried up the waters of Jordan from before the children of Israel, until we were passed over, that their heart melted, neither was there spirit in them any more, because of the children of Israel.

^2At that time the Lord said unto Joshua, Make thee sharp knives, and circumcise again the children of Israel the second time. ^3And Joshua made him sharp knives, and circumcised the children of Israel at the hill of the foreskins. ^4And this is the cause why Joshua did circumcise: All the people that came out of Egypt, that were males, even all the men of war, died in the wilderness by the way, after they came out of Egypt. ^5Now all the people that came out were circumcised: but all the people that were born in the wilderness by the way as they came forth out of Egypt, them they had not circumcised. ^6For the children of Israel walked forty years in the wilderness, till all the people that were men of war, which came out of Egypt, were consumed, because they obeyed not the voice of the Lord: unto whom the Lord sware that he would not shew them the land, which the Lord sware unto their fathers that he would give us, a land that floweth with milk and honey. ^7And their children, whom he raised up in their stead, them Joshua circumcised: for they were uncircumcised, because they had not circumcised them by the way. ^8And it came to pass, when they had done circumcising all the people, that they abode in their places in the camp, till they were whole. ^9And the Lord said unto Joshua, This day have I rolled away the reproach of Egypt from off you. Wherefore the name of the place is called Gilgal unto this day.

^10And the children of Israel encamped in Gilgal, and kept the passover on the fourteenth day of the month at even in the plains of Jericho. ^11And they did eat of the old corn of the land on the morrow after the passover, unleavened cakes, and parched corn in the selfsame day. ^12And the manna ceased on the morrow after they had eaten of the old corn of the land; neither had the children of Israel manna any more; but they did eat of the fruit of the land of Canaan that year.

^13And it came to pass, when Joshua was by Jericho, that he lifted up his eyes and looked, and, behold, there stood a man over against him with his sword drawn in his hand: and Joshua went unto him, and said unto him, Art thou for us, or for our adversaries? ^14And he said, Nay; but as captain of the host of the Lord am I now come. And Joshua fell on his face to the earth, and did worship, and said unto him, What saith my Lord unto his servant? ^15And the captain of the Lord’s host said unto Joshua, Loose thy shoe from off thy foot; for the place whereon thou standest is holy. And Joshua did so.

VI

^1Now Jericho was straitly shut up because of the children of Israel: none went out, and none came in. ^2And the Lord said unto Joshua, See, I have given into thine hand Jericho, and the king thereof, and the mighty men of valour. ^3And ye shall compass the city, all ye men of war, and go round about the city once. Thus shalt thou do six days. ^4And seven priests shall bear before the ark seven trumpets of rams’ horns: and the seventh day ye shall compass the city seven times, and the priests shall blow with the trumpets. ^5And it shall come to pass, that when they make a long blast with the ram’s horn, and when ye hear the sound of the trumpet, all the people shall shout with a great shout; and the wall of the city shall fall down flat, and the people shall ascend up every man straight before him. ^6And Joshua the son of Nun called the priests, and said unto them, Take up the ark of the covenant, and let seven priests bear seven trumpets of rams’ horns before the ark of the Lord. ^7And he said unto the people, Pass on, and compass the city, and let him that is armed pass on before the ark of the Lord.

^8And it came to pass, when Joshua had spoken unto the people, that the seven priests bearing the seven trumpets of rams’ horns passed on before the Lord, and blew with the trumpets: and the ark of the covenant of the Lord followed them. ^9And the armed men went before the priests that blew with the trumpets, and the rereward came after the ark, the priests going on, and blowing with the trumpets. ^10And Joshua had commanded the people, saying, Ye shall not shout, nor make any noise with your voice, neither shall any word proceed out of your mouth, until the day I bid you shout; then shall ye shout. ^11So the ark of the Lord compassed the city, going about it once: and they came into the camp, and lodged in the camp.

^12And Joshua rose early in the morning, and the priests took up the ark of the Lord. ^13And seven priests bearing seven trumpets of rams’ horns before the ark of the Lord went on continually, and blew with the trumpets: and the armed men went before them; but the rereward came after the ark of the Lord, the priests going on, and blowing with the trumpets. ^14And the second day they compassed the city once, and returned into the camp: so they did six days.

^15And it came to pass on the seventh day, that they rose early about the dawning of the day, and compassed the city after the same manner seven times: only on that day they compassed the city seven times. ^16And it came to pass at the seventh time, when the priests blew with the trumpets, Joshua said unto the people, Shout; for the Lord hath given you the city. ^17And the city shall be accursed, even it, and all that are therein, to the Lord: only Rahab the harlot shall live, she and all that are with her in the house, because she hid the messengers that we sent. ^18And ye, in any wise keep yourselves from the accursed thing, lest ye make yourselves accursed, when ye take of the accursed thing, and make the camp of Israel a curse, and trouble it. ^19But all the silver, and gold, and vessels of brass and iron, are consecrated unto the Lord: they shall come into the treasury of the Lord. ^20So the people shouted when the priests blew with the trumpets: and it came to pass, when the people heard the sound of the trumpet, and the people shouted with a great shout, that the wall fell down flat, so that the people went up into the city, every man straight before him, and they took the city. ^21And they utterly destroyed all that was in the city, both man and woman, young and old, and ox, and sheep, and ass, with the edge of the sword.

^22But Joshua had said unto the two men that had spied out the country, Go into the harlot’s house, and bring out thence the woman, and all that she hath, as ye sware unto her. ^23And the young men that were spies went in, and brought out Rahab, and her father, and her mother, and her brethren, and all that she had; and they brought out all her kindred, and left them without the camp of Israel. ^24And they burnt the city with fire, and all that was therein: only the silver, and the gold, and the vessels of brass and of iron, they put into the treasury of the house of the Lord. ^25And Joshua saved Rahab the harlot alive, and her father’s household, and all that she had; and she dwelleth in Israel even unto this day; because she hid the messengers, which Joshua sent to spy out Jericho. ^26And Joshua adjured them at that time, saying, Cursed be the man before the Lord, that riseth up and buildeth this city Jericho: he shall lay the foundation thereof in his firstborn, and in his youngest son shall he set up the gates of it. ^27So the Lord was with Joshua; and his fame was noised throughout all the country.

VII

^1But the children of Israel committed a trespass in the accursed thing: for Achan, the son of Carmi, the son of Zabdi, the son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, took of the accursed thing: and the anger of the Lord was kindled against the children of Israel.

^2And Joshua sent men from Jericho to Ai, which is beside Bethaven, on the east of Bethel, and spake unto them, saying, Go up and view the country. And the men went up and viewed Ai. ^3And they returned to Joshua, and said unto him, Let not all the people go up; but let about two or three thousand men go up and smite Ai; and make not all the people to labour thither; for they are but few. ^4So there went up thither of the people about three thousand men: and they fled before the men of Ai. ^5And the men of Ai smote of them about thirty and six men: for they chased them from before the gate even unto Shebarim, and smote them in the going down: wherefore the hearts of the people melted, and became as water.

^6And Joshua rent his clothes, and fell to the earth upon his face before the ark of the Lord until the eventide, he and the elders of Israel, and put dust upon their heads. ^7And Joshua said, Alas, O Lord God, wherefore hast thou at all brought this people over Jordan, to deliver us into the hand of the Amorites, to destroy us? would to God we had been content, and dwelt on the other side Jordan! ^8O Lord, what shall I say, when Israel turneth their backs before their enemies! ^9For the Canaanites and all the inhabitants of the land shall hear of it, and shall environ us round, and cut off our name from the earth: and what wilt thou do unto thy great name?

^10And the Lord said unto Joshua, Get thee up; wherefore liest thou thus upon thy face? ^11Israel hath sinned, and they have also transgressed my covenant which I commanded them: for they have even taken of the accursed thing, and have also stolen, and dissembled also, and they have put it even among their own stuff. ^12Therefore the children of Israel could not stand before their enemies, but turned their backs before their enemies, because they were accursed: neither will I be with you any more, except ye destroy the accursed from among you. ^13Up, sanctify the people, and say, Sanctify yourselves against to morrow: for thus saith the Lord God of Israel, There is an accursed thing in the midst of thee, O Israel: thou canst not stand before thine enemies, until ye take away the accursed thing from among you. ^14In the morning therefore ye shall be brought according to your tribes: and it shall be, that the tribe which the Lord taketh shall come according to the families thereof; and the family which the Lord shall take shall come by households; and the household which the Lord shall take shall come man by man. ^15And it shall be, that he that is taken with the accursed thing shall be burnt with fire, he and all that he hath: because he hath transgressed the covenant of the Lord, and because he hath wrought folly in Israel.

^16So Joshua rose up early in the morning, and brought Israel by their tribes; and the tribe of Judah was taken: ^17and he brought the family of Judah; and he took the family of the Zarhites: and he brought the family of the Zarhites man by man; and Zabdi was taken: ^18and he brought his household man by man; and Achan, the son of Carmi, the son of Zabdi, the son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, was taken. ^19And Joshua said unto Achan, My son, give, I pray thee, glory to the Lord God of Israel, and make confession unto him; and tell me now what thou hast done; hide it not from me. ^20And Achan answered Joshua, and said, Indeed I have sinned against the Lord God of Israel, and thus and thus have I done: ^21when I saw among the spoils a goodly Babylonish garment, and two hundred shekels of silver, and a wedge of gold of fifty shekels weight, then I coveted them, and took them; and, behold, they are hid in the earth in the midst of my tent, and the silver under it.

^22So Joshua sent messengers, and they ran unto the tent; and, behold, it was hid in his tent, and the silver under it. ^23And they took them out of the midst of the tent, and brought them unto Joshua, and unto all the children of Israel, and laid them out before the Lord. ^24And Joshua, and all Israel with him, took Achan the son of Zerah, and the silver, and the garment, and the wedge of gold, and his sons, and his daughters, and his oxen, and his asses, and his sheep, and his tent, and all that he had: and they brought them unto the valley of Achor. ^25And Joshua said, Why hast thou troubled us? the Lord shall trouble thee this day. And all Israel stoned him with stones, and burned them with fire, after they had stoned them with stones. ^26And they raised over him a great heap of stones unto this day. So the Lord turned from the fierceness of his anger. Wherefore the name of that place was called, The valley of Achor, unto this day.

VIII

^1And the Lord said unto Joshua, Fear not, neither be thou dismayed: take all the people of war with thee, and arise, go up to Ai: see, I have given into thy hand the king of Ai, and his people, and his city, and his land: ^2and thou shalt do to Ai and her king as thou didst unto Jericho and her king: only the spoil thereof, and the cattle thereof, shall ye take for a prey unto yourselves: lay thee an ambush for the city behind it.

^3So Joshua arose, and all the people of war, to go up against Ai: and Joshua chose out thirty thousand mighty men of valour, and sent them away by night. ^4And he commanded them, saying, Behold, ye shall lie in wait against the city, even behind the city: go not very far from the city, but be ye all ready: ^5and I, and all the people that are with me, will approach unto the city: and it shall come to pass, when they come out against us, as at the first, that we will flee before them, ^6(for they will come out after us) till we have drawn them from the city; for they will say, They flee before us, as at the first: therefore we will flee before them. ^7Then ye shall rise up from the ambush, and seize upon the city: for the Lord your God will deliver it into your hand. ^8And it shall be, when ye have taken the city, that ye shall set the city on fire: according to the commandment of the Lord shall ye do. See, I have commanded you. ^9Joshua therefore sent them forth: and they went to lie in ambush, and abode between Bethel and Ai, on the west side of Ai: but Joshua lodged that night among the people.

^10And Joshua rose up early in the morning, and numbered the people, and went up, he and the elders of Israel, before the people to Ai. ^11And all the people, even the people of war that were with him, went up, and drew nigh, and came before the city, and pitched on the north side of Ai: now there was a valley between them and Ai. ^12And he took about five thousand men, and set them to lie in ambush between Bethel and Ai, on the west side of the city. ^13And when they had set the people, even all the host that was on the north of the city, and their liers in wait on the west of the city, Joshua went that night into the midst of the valley. ^14And it came to pass, when the king of Ai saw it, that they hasted and rose up early, and the men of the city went out against Israel to battle, he and all his people, at a time appointed, before the plain; but he wist not that there were liers in ambush against him behind the city. ^15And Joshua and all Israel made as if they were beaten before them, and fled by the way of the wilderness. ^16And all the people that were in Ai were called together to pursue after them: and they pursued after Joshua, and were drawn away from the city. ^17And there was not a man left in Ai or Bethel, that went not out after Israel: and they left the city open, and pursued after Israel.

^18And the Lord said unto Joshua, Stretch out the spear that is in thy hand toward Ai; for I will give it into thine hand. And Joshua stretched out the spear that he had in his hand toward the city. ^19And the ambush arose quickly out of their place, and they ran as soon as he had stretched out his hand: and they entered into the city, and took it, and hasted and set the city on fire. ^20And when the men of Ai looked behind them, they saw, and, behold, the smoke of the city ascended up to heaven, and they had no power to flee this way or that way: and the people that fled to the wilderness turned back upon the pursuers. ^21And when Joshua and all Israel saw that the ambush had taken the city, and that the smoke of the city ascended, then they turned again, and slew the men of Ai. ^22And the other issued out of the city against them; so they were in the midst of Israel, some on this side, and some on that side: and they smote them, so that they let none of them remain or escape. ^23And the king of Ai they took alive, and brought him to Joshua.

^24And it came to pass, when Israel had made an end of slaying all the inhabitants of Ai in the field, in the wilderness wherein they chased them, and when they were all fallen on the edge of the sword, until they were consumed, that all the Israelites returned unto Ai, and smote it with the edge of the sword. ^25And so it was, that all that fell that day, both of men and women, were twelve thousand, even all the men of Ai. ^26For Joshua drew not his hand back, wherewith he stretched out the spear, until he had utterly destroyed all the inhabitants of Ai. ^27Only the cattle and the spoil of that city Israel took for a prey unto themselves, according unto the word of the Lord which he commanded Joshua. ^28And Joshua burnt Ai, and made it an heap for ever, even a desolation unto this day. ^29And the king of Ai he hanged on a tree until eventide: and as soon as the sun was down, Joshua commanded that they should take his carcase down from the tree, and cast it at the entering of the gate of the city, and raise thereon a great heap of stones, that remaineth unto this day.

^30Then Joshua built an altar unto the Lord God of Israel in mount Ebal, ^31as Moses the servant of the Lord commanded the children of Israel, as it is written in the book of the law of Moses, an altar of whole stones, over which no man hath lift up any iron: and they offered thereon burnt offerings unto the Lord, and sacrificed peace offerings. ^32And he wrote there upon the stones a copy of the law of Moses, which he wrote in the presence of the children of Israel. ^33And all Israel, and their elders, and officers, and their judges, stood on this side the ark and on that side before the priests the Levites, which bare the ark of the covenant of the Lord, as well the stranger, as he that was born among them; half of them over against mount Gerizim, and half of them over against mount Ebal; as Moses the servant of the Lord had commanded before, that they should bless the people of Israel. ^34And afterward he read all the words of the law, the blessings and cursings, according to all that is written in the book of the law. ^35There was not a word of all that Moses commanded, which Joshua read not before all the congregation of Israel, with the women, and the little ones, and the strangers that were conversant among them.

IX

^1And it came to pass, when all the kings which were on this side Jordan, in the hills, and in the valleys, and in all the coasts of the great sea over against Lebanon, the Hittite, and the Amorite, the Canaanite, the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite, heard thereof; ^2that they gathered themselves together, to fight with Joshua and with Israel, with one accord.

^3And when the inhabitants of Gibeon heard what Joshua had done unto Jericho and to Ai, ^4they did work wilily, and went and made as if they had been ambassadors, and took old sacks upon their asses, and wine bottles, old, and rent, and bound up; ^5and old shoes and clouted upon their feet, and old garments upon them; and all the bread of their provision was dry and mouldy. ^6And they went to Joshua unto the camp at Gilgal, and said unto him, and to the men of Israel, We be come from a far country: now therefore make ye a league with us. ^7And the men of Israel said unto the Hivites, Peradventure ye dwell among us; and how shall we make a league with you? ^8And they said unto Joshua, We are thy servants. And Joshua said unto them, Who are ye? and from whence come ye? ^9And they said unto him, From a very far country thy servants are come because of the name of the Lord thy God: for we have heard the fame of him, and all that he did in Egypt, ^10and all that he did to the two kings of the Amorites, that were beyond Jordan, to Sihon king of Heshbon, and to Og king of Bashan, which was at Ashtaroth. ^11Wherefore our elders and all the inhabitants of our country spake to us, saying, Take victuals with you for the journey, and go to meet them, and say unto them, We are your servants: therefore now make ye a league with us. ^12This our bread we took hot for our provision out of our houses on the day we came forth to go unto you; but now, behold, it is dry, and it is mouldy: ^13and these bottles of wine, which we filled, were new; and, behold, they be rent: and these our garments and our shoes are become old by reason of the very long journey. ^14And the men took of their victuals, and asked not counsel at the mouth of the Lord. ^15And Joshua made peace with them, and made a league with them, to let them live: and the princes of the congregation sware unto them.

^16And it came to pass at the end of three days after they had made a league with them, that they heard that they were their neighbours, and that they dwelt among them. ^17And the children of Israel journeyed, and came unto their cities on the third day. Now their cities were Gibeon, and Chephirah, and Beeroth, and Kirjathjearim. ^18And the children of Israel smote them not, because the princes of the congregation had sworn unto them by the Lord God of Israel. And all the congregation murmured against the princes. ^19But all the princes said unto all the congregation, We have sworn unto them by the Lord God of Israel: now therefore we may not touch them. ^20This we will do to them; we will even let them live, lest wrath be upon us, because of the oath which we sware unto them. ^21And the princes said unto them, Let them live; but let them be hewers of wood and drawers of water unto all the congregation; as the princes had promised them.

^22And Joshua called for them, and he spake unto them, saying, Wherefore have ye beguiled us, saying, We are very far from you; when ye dwell among us? ^23Now therefore ye are cursed, and there shall none of you be freed from being bondmen, and hewers of wood and drawers of water for the house of my God. ^24And they answered Joshua, and said, Because it was certainly told thy servants, how that the Lord thy God commanded his servant Moses to give you all the land, and to destroy all the inhabitants of the land from before you, therefore we were sore afraid of our lives because of you, and have done this thing. ^25And now, behold, we are in thine hand: as it seemeth good and right unto thee to do unto us, do. ^26And so did he unto them, and delivered them out of the hand of the children of Israel, that they slew them not. ^27And Joshua made them that day hewers of wood and drawers of water for the congregation, and for the altar of the Lord, even unto this day, in the place which he should choose.

X

^1Now it came to pass, when Adonizedec king of Jerusalem had heard how Joshua had taken Ai, and had utterly destroyed it; as he had done to Jericho and her king, so he had done to Ai and her king; and how the inhabitants of Gibeon had made peace with Israel, and were among them; ^2that they feared greatly, because Gibeon was a great city, as one of the royal cities, and because it was greater than Ai, and all the men thereof were mighty. ^3Wherefore Adonizedec king of Jerusalem, sent unto Hoham king of Hebron, and unto Piram king of Jarmuth, and unto Japhia king of Lachish, and unto Debir king of Eglon, saying, ^4Come up unto me, and help me, that we may smite Gibeon: for it hath made peace with Joshua and with the children of Israel. ^5Therefore the five kings of the Amorites, the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, the king of Eglon, gathered themselves together, and went up, they and all their hosts, and encamped before Gibeon, and made war against it.

^6And the men of Gibeon sent unto Joshua to the camp to Gilgal, saying, Slack not thy hand from thy servants; come up to us quickly, and save us, and help us: for all the kings of the Amorites that dwell in the mountains are gathered together against us. ^7So Joshua ascended from Gilgal, he, and all the people of war with him, and all the mighty men of valour. ^8And the Lord said unto Joshua, Fear them not: for I have delivered them into thine hand; there shall not a man of them stand before thee. ^9Joshua therefore came unto them suddenly, and went up from Gilgal all night. ^10And the Lord discomfited them before Israel, and slew them with a great slaughter at Gibeon, and chased them along the way that goeth up to Bethhoron, and smote them to Azekah, and unto Makkedah. ^11And it came to pass, as they fled from before Israel, and were in the going down to Bethhoron, that the Lord cast down great stones from heaven upon them unto Azekah, and they died: they were more which died with hailstones than they whom the children of Israel slew with the sword.

^12Then spake Joshua to the Lord in the day when the Lord delivered up the Amorites before the children of Israel, and he said in the sight of Israel,

Sun, stand thou still upon Gibeon;
And thou, Moon, in the valley of Ajalon.
^13And the sun stood still, and the moon stayed,
Until the people had avenged themselves upon their enemies.

Is not this written in the book of Jasher? So the sun stood still in the midst of heaven, and hasted not to go down about a whole day. ^14And there was no day like that before it or after it, that the Lord hearkened unto the voice of a man: for the Lord fought for Israel.

^15And Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, unto the camp to Gilgal.

^16But these five kings fled, and hid themselves in a cave at Makkedah. ^17And it was told Joshua, saying, The five kings are found hid in a cave at Makkedah. ^18And Joshua said, Roll great stones upon the mouth of the cave, and set men by it for to keep them: ^19and stay ye not, but pursue after your enemies, and smite the hindmost of them; suffer them not to enter into their cities: for the Lord your God hath delivered them into your hand. ^20And it came to pass, when Joshua and the children of Israel had made an end of slaying them with a very great slaughter, till they were consumed, that the rest which remained of them entered into fenced cities. ^21And all the people returned to the camp to Joshua at Makkedah in peace: none moved his tongue against any of the children of Israel.

^22Then said Joshua, Open the mouth of the cave, and bring out those five kings unto me out of the cave. ^23And they did so, and brought forth those five kings unto him out of the cave, the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, and the king of Eglon. ^24And it came to pass, when they brought out those kings unto Joshua, that Joshua called for all the men of Israel, and said unto the captains of the men of war which went with him, Come near, put your feet upon the necks of these kings. And they came near, and put their feet upon the necks of them. ^25And Joshua said unto them, Fear not, nor be dismayed, be strong and of good courage: for thus shall the Lord do to all your enemies against whom ye fight. ^26And afterward Joshua smote them, and slew them, and hanged them on five trees: and they were hanging upon the trees until the evening. ^27And it came to pass at the time of the going down of the sun, that Joshua commanded, and they took them down off the trees, and cast them into the cave wherein they had been hid, and laid great stones in the cave’s mouth, which remain until this very day.

^28And that day Joshua took Makkedah, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and the king thereof he utterly destroyed, them, and all the souls that were therein; he let none remain: and he did to the king of Makkedah as he did unto the king of Jericho.

^29Then Joshua passed from Makkedah, and all Israel with him, unto Libnah, and fought against Libnah: ^30and the Lord delivered it also, and the king thereof, into the hand of Israel; and he smote it with the edge of the sword, and all the souls that were therein; he let none remain in it; but did unto the king thereof as he did unto the king of Jericho.

^31And Joshua passed from Libnah, and all Israel with him, unto Lachish, and encamped against it, and fought against it: ^32and the Lord delivered Lachish into the hand of Israel, which took it on the second day, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and all the souls that were therein, according to all that he had done to Libnah.

^33Then Horam king of Gezer came up to help Lachish; and Joshua smote him and his people, until he had left him none remaining.

^34And from Lachish Joshua passed unto Eglon, and all Israel with him; and they encamped against it, and fought against it: ^35and they took it on that day, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and all the souls that were therein he utterly destroyed that day, according to all that he had done to Lachish.

^36And Joshua went up from Eglon, and all Israel with him, unto Hebron; and they fought against it: ^37and they took it, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and the king thereof, and all the cities thereof, and all the souls that were therein; he left none remaining, according to all that he had done to Eglon; but destroyed it utterly, and all the souls that were therein.

^38And Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, to Debir; and fought against it: ^39and he took it, and the king thereof, and all the cities thereof; and they smote them with the edge of the sword, and utterly destroyed all the souls that were therein; he left none remaining: as he had done to Hebron, so he did to Debir, and to the king thereof; as he had done also to Libnah, and to her king.

^40So Joshua smote all the country of the hills, and of the south, and of the vale, and of the springs, and all their kings: he left none remaining, but utterly destroyed all that breathed, as the Lord God of Israel commanded. ^41And Joshua smote them from Kadeshbarnea even unto Gaza, and all the country of Goshen, even unto Gibeon. ^42And all these kings and their land did Joshua take at one time, because the Lord God of Israel fought for Israel. ^43And Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, unto the camp to Gilgal.

XI

^1And it came to pass, when Jabin king of Hazor had heard those things, that he sent to Jobab king of Madon, and to the king of Shimron, and to the king of Achshaph, ^2and to the kings that were on the north of the mountains, and of the plains south of Chinneroth, and in the valley, and in the borders of Dor on the west, ^3and to the Canaanite on the east and on the west, and to the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Jebusite in the mountains, and to the Hivite under Hermon in the land of Mizpeh. ^4And they went out, they and all their hosts with them, much people, even as the sand that is upon the sea shore in multitude, with horses and chariots very many. ^5And when all these kings were met together, they came and pitched together at the waters of Merom, to fight against Israel.

^6And the Lord said unto Joshua, Be not afraid because of them: for to morrow about this time will I deliver them up all slain before Israel: thou shalt hough their horses, and burn their chariots with fire. ^7So Joshua came, and all the people of war with him, against them by the waters of Merom suddenly; and they fell upon them. ^8And the Lord delivered them into the hand of Israel, who smote them, and chased them unto great Zidon, and unto Misrephothmaim, and unto the valley of Mizpeh eastward; and they smote them, until they left them none remaining. ^9And Joshua did unto them as the Lord bade him: he houghed their horses, and burnt their chariots with fire.

^10And Joshua at that time turned back, and took Hazor, and smote the king thereof with the sword: for Hazor beforetime was the head of all those kingdoms. ^11And they smote all the souls that were therein with the edge of the sword, utterly destroying them: there was not any left to breathe: and he burnt Hazor with fire. ^12And all the cities of those kings, and all the kings of them, did Joshua take, and smote them with the edge of the sword, and he utterly destroyed them, as Moses the servant of the Lord commanded. ^13But as for the cities that stood still in their strength, Israel burned none of them, save Hazor only; that did Joshua burn. ^14And all the spoil of these cities, and the cattle, the children of Israel took for a prey unto themselves; but every man they smote with the edge of the sword, until they had destroyed them, neither left they any to breathe. ^15As the Lord commanded Moses his servant, so did Moses command Joshua, and so did Joshua; he left nothing undone of all that the Lord commanded Moses.

^16So Joshua took all that land, the hills, and all the south country, and all the land of Goshen, and the valley, and the plain, and the mountain of Israel, and the valley of the same; ^17even from the mount Halak, that goeth up to Seir, even unto Baalgad in the valley of Lebanon under mount Hermon: and all their kings he took, and smote them, and slew them. ^18Joshua made war a long time with all those kings. ^19There was not a city that made peace with the children of Israel, save the Hivites the inhabitants of Gibeon: all other they took in battle. ^20For it was of the Lord to harden their hearts, that they should come against Israel in battle, that he might destroy them utterly, and that they might have no favour, but that he might destroy them, as the Lord commanded Moses.

^21And at that time came Joshua, and cut off the Anakims from the mountains, from Hebron, from Debir, from Anab, and from all the mountains of Judah, and from all the mountains of Israel: Joshua destroyed them utterly with their cities. ^22There was none of the Anakims left in the land of the children of Israel: only in Gaza, in Gath, and in Ashdod, there remained. ^23So Joshua took the whole land, according to all that the Lord said unto Moses; and Joshua gave it for an inheritance unto Israel according to their divisions by their tribes. And the land rested from war.

XII

^1Now these are the kings of the land, which the children of Israel smote, and possessed their land on the other side Jordan toward the rising of the sun, from the river Arnon unto mount Hermon, and all the plain on the east: ^2Sihon king of the Amorites, who dwelt in Heshbon, and ruled from Aroer, which is upon the bank of the river Arnon, and from the middle of the river, and from half Gilead, even unto the river Jabbok, which is the border of the children of Ammon; ^3and from the plain to the sea of Chinneroth on the east, and unto the sea of the plain, even the salt sea on the east, the way to Bethjeshimoth; and from the south, under Ashdothpisgah: ^4and the coast of Og king of Bashan, which was of the remnant of the giants, that dwelt at Ashtaroth and at Edrei, ^5and reigned in mount Hermon, and in Salcah, and in all Bashan, unto the border of the Geshurites and the Maachathites, and half Gilead, the border of Sihon king of Heshbon. ^6Them did Moses the servant of the Lord and the children of Israel smite: and Moses the servant of the Lord gave it for a possession unto the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half tribe of Manasseh.

^7And these are the kings of the country which Joshua and the children of Israel smote on this side Jordan on the west, from Baalgad in the valley of Lebanon even unto the mount Halak, that goeth up to Seir; which Joshua gave unto the tribes of Israel for a possession according to their divisions; ^8in the mountains, and in the valleys, and in the plains, and in the springs, and in the wilderness, and in the south country; the Hittites, the Amorites, and the Canaanites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites: ^9the king of Jericho, one; the king of Ai, which is beside Bethel, one; ^10the king of Jerusalem, one; the king of Hebron, one; ^11the king of Jarmuth, one; the king of Lachish, one; ^12the king of Eglon, one; the king of Gezer, one; ^13the king of Debir, one; the king of Geder, one; ^14the king of Hormah, one; the king of Arad, one; ^15the king of Libnah, one; the king of Adullam, one; ^16the king of Makkedah, one; the king of Bethel, one; ^17the king of Tappuah, one; the king of Hepher, one; ^18the king of Aphek, one; the king of Lasharon, one; ^19the king of Madon, one; the king of Hazor, one; ^20the king of Shimronmeron, one; the king of Achshaph, one; ^21the king of Taanach, one; the king of Megiddo, one; ^22the king of Kedesh, one; the king of Jokneam of Carmel, one; ^23the king of Dor in the coast of Dor, one; the king of the nations of Gilgal, one; ^24the king of Tirzah, one: all the kings thirty and one.

XIII

^1Now Joshua was old and stricken in years; and the Lord said unto him, Thou art old and stricken in years, and there remaineth yet very much land to be possessed. ^2This is the land that yet remaineth: all the borders of the Philistines, and all Geshuri, ^3from Sihor, which is before Egypt, even unto the borders of Ekron northward, which is counted to the Canaanite: five lords of the Philistines; the Gazathites, and the Ashdothites, the Eshkalonites, the Gittites, and the Ekronites; also the Avites: ^4from the south, all the land of the Canaanites, and Mearah that is beside the Sidonians unto Aphek, to the borders of the Amorites: ^5and the land of the Giblites, and all Lebanon, toward the sunrising, from Baalgad under mount Hermon unto the entering into Hamath. ^6All the inhabitants of the hill country from Lebanon unto Misrephothmaim, and all the Sidonians, them will I drive out from before the children of Israel: only divide thou it by lot unto the Israelites for an inheritance, as I have commanded thee. ^7Now therefore divide this land for an inheritance unto the nine tribes, and the half tribe of Manasseh, ^8with whom the Reubenites and the Gadites have received their inheritance, which Moses gave them, beyond Jordan eastward, even as Moses the servant of the Lord gave them; ^9from Aroer, that is upon the bank of the river Arnon, and the city that is in the midst of the river, and all the plain of Medeba unto Dibon; ^10and all the cities of Sihon king of the Amorites, which reigned in Heshbon, unto the border of the children of Ammon; ^11and Gilead, and the border of the Geshurites and Maachathites, and all mount Hermon, and all Bashan unto Salcah; ^12all the kingdom of Og in Bashan, which reigned in Ashtaroth and in Edrei, who remained of the remnant of the giants: for these did Moses smite, and cast them out. ^13Nevertheless the children of Israel expelled not the Geshurites, nor the Maachathites: but the Geshurites and the Maachathites dwell among the Israelites until this day. ^14Only unto the tribes of Levi he gave none inheritance; the sacrifices of the Lord God of Israel made by fire are their inheritance, as he said unto them.

^15And Moses gave unto the tribe of the children of Reuben inheritance according to their families. ^16And their coast was from Aroer, that is on the bank of the river Arnon, and the city that is in the midst of the river, and all the plain by Medeba; ^17Heshbon, and all her cities that are in the plain; Dibon, and Bamothbaal, and Bethbaalmeon, ^18and Jahaza, and Kedemoth, and Mephaath, ^19and Kirjathaim, and Sibmah, and Zarethshahar in the mount of the valley, ^20and Bethpeor, and Ashdothpisgah, and Bethjeshimoth, ^21and all the cities of the plain, and all the kingdom of Sihon king of the Amorites, which reigned in Heshbon, whom Moses smote with the princes of Midian, Evi, and Rekem, and Zur, and Hur, and Reba, which were dukes of Sihon, dwelling in the country. ^22Balaam also the son of Beor, the soothsayer, did the children of Israel slay with the sword among them that were slain by them. ^23And the border of the children of Reuben was Jordan, and the border thereof. This was the inheritance of the children of Reuben after their families, the cities and the villages thereof.

^24And Moses gave inheritance unto the tribe of Gad, even unto the children of Gad according to their families. ^25And their coast was Jazer, and all the cities of Gilead, and half the land of the children of Ammon, unto Aroer that is before Rabbah; ^26and from Heshbon unto Ramathmizpeh, and Betonim; and from Mahanaim unto the border of Debir; ^27and in the valley, Betharam, and Bethnimrah, and Succoth, and Zaphon, the rest of the kingdom of Sihon king of Heshbon, Jordan and his border, even unto the edge of the sea of Chinnereth on the other side Jordan eastward. ^28This is the inheritance of the children of Gad after their families, the cities, and their villages.

^29And Moses gave inheritance unto the half tribe of Manasseh: and this was the possession of the half tribe of the children of Manasseh by their families. ^30And their coast was from Mahanaim, all Bashan, all the kingdom of Og king of Bashan, and all the towns of Jair, which are in Bashan, threescore cities: ^31and half Gilead, and Ashtaroth, and Edrei, cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan, were pertaining unto the children of Machir the son of Manasseh, even to the one half of the children of Machir by their families.

^32These are the countries which Moses did distribute for inheritance in the plains of Moab, on the other side Jordan, by Jericho, eastward. ^33But unto the tribe of Levi Moses gave not any inheritance: the Lord God of Israel was their inheritance, as he said unto them.

XIV

^1And these are the countries which the children of Israel inherited in the land of Canaan, which Eleazar the priest, and Joshua the son of Nun, and the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the children of Israel, distributed for inheritance to them. ^2By lot was their inheritance, as the Lord commanded by the hand of Moses, for the nine tribes, and for the half tribe. ^3For Moses had given the inheritance of two tribes and an half tribe on the other side Jordan: but unto the Levites he gave none inheritance among them. ^4For the children of Joseph were two tribes, Manasseh and Ephraim: therefore they gave no part unto the Levites in the land, save cities to dwell in, with their suburbs for their cattle and for their substance. ^5As the Lord commanded Moses, so the children of Israel did, and they divided the land.

^6Then the children of Judah came unto Joshua in Gilgal: and Caleb the son of Jephunneh the Kenezite said unto him, Thou knowest the thing that the Lord said unto Moses the man of God concerning me and thee in Kadeshbarnea. ^7Forty years old was I when Moses the servant of the Lord sent me from Kadeshbarnea to espy out the land; and I brought him word again as it was in mine heart. ^8Nevertheless my brethren that went up with me made the heart of the people melt: but I wholly followed the Lord my God. ^9And Moses sware on that day, saying, Surely the land whereon thy feet have trodden shall be thine inheritance, and thy children’s for ever, because thou hast wholly followed the Lord my God. ^10And now, behold, the Lord hath kept me alive, as he said, these forty and five years, even since the Lord spake this word unto Moses, while the children of Israel wandered in the wilderness: and now, lo, I am this day fourscore and five years old. ^11As yet I am as strong this day as I was in the day that Moses sent me: as my strength was then, even so is my strength now, for war, both to go out, and to come in. ^12Now therefore give me this mountain, whereof the Lord spake in that day; for thou heardest in that day how the Anakims were there, and that the cities were great and fenced: if so be the Lord will be with me, then I shall be able to drive them out, as the Lord said.

^13And Joshua blessed him, and gave unto Caleb the son of Jephunneh Hebron for an inheritance. ^14Hebron therefore became the inheritance of Caleb the son of Jephunneh the Kenezite unto this day, because that he wholly followed the Lord God of Israel. ^15And the name of Hebron before was Kirjatharba; which Arba was a great man among the Anakims. And the land had rest from war.

XV

^1This then was the lot of the tribe of the children of Judah by their families; even to the border of Edom the wilderness of Zin southward was the uttermost part of the south coast. ^2And their south border was from the shore of the salt sea, from the bay that looketh southward: ^3and it went out to the south side to Maalehacrabbim, and passed along to Zin, and ascended up on the south side unto Kadeshbarnea, and passed along to Hezron, and went up to Adar, and fetched a compass to Karkaa: ^4from thence it passed toward Azmon, and went out unto the river of Egypt; and the goings out of that coast were at the sea: this shall be your south coast. ^5And the east border was the salt sea, even unto the end of Jordan. And their border in the north quarter was from the bay of the sea at the uttermost part of Jordan: ^6and the border went up to Bethhogla, and passed along by the north of Betharabah; and the border went up to the stone of Bohan the son of Reuben: ^7and the border went up toward Debir from the valley of Achor, and so northward, looking toward Gilgal, that is before the going up to Adummim, which is on the south side of the river: and the border passed toward the waters of Enshemesh, and the goings out thereof were at Enrogel: ^8and the border went up by the valley of the son of Hinnom unto the south side of the Jebusite; the same is Jerusalem: and the border went up to the top of the mountain that lieth before the valley of Hinnom westward, which is at the end of the valley of the giants northward: ^9and the border was drawn from the top of the hill unto the fountain of the water of Nephtoah, and went out to the cities of mount Ephron; and the border was drawn to Baalah, which is Kirjathjearim: ^10and the border compassed from Baalah westward unto mount Seir, and passed along unto the side of mount Jearim, which is Chesalon, on the north side, and went down to Bethshemesh, and passed on to Timnah: ^11and the border went out unto the side of Ekron northward: and the border was drawn to Shicron, and passed along to mount Baalah, and went out unto Jabneel; and the goings out of the border were at the sea. ^12And the west border was to the great sea, and the coast thereof. This is the coast of the children of Judah round about according to their families.

^13And unto Caleb the son of Jephunneh he gave a part among the children of Judah, according to the commandment of the Lord to Joshua, even the city of Arba the father of Anak, which city is Hebron. ^14And Caleb drove thence the three sons of Anak, Sheshai, and Ahiman, and Talmai, the children of Anak. ^15And he went up thence to the inhabitants of Debir: and the name of Debir before was Kirjathsepher. ^16And Caleb said, He that smiteth Kirjathsepher, and taketh it, to him will I give Achsah my daughter to wife. ^17And Othniel the son of Kenaz, the brother of Caleb, took it: and he gave him Achsah his daughter to wife. ^18And it came to pass, as she came unto him, that she moved him to ask of her father a field: and she lighted off her ass; and Caleb said unto her, What wouldest thou? ^19Who answered, Give me a blessing; for thou hast given me a south land; give me also springs of water. And he gave her the upper springs, and the nether springs.

^20This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Judah according to their families.

^21And the uttermost cities of the tribe of the children of Judah toward the coast of Edom southward were Kabzeel, and Eder, and Jagur, ^22and Kinah, and Dimonah, and Adadah, ^23and Kedesh, and Hazor, and Ithnan, ^24Ziph, and Telem, and Bealoth, ^25and Hazor, Hadattah, and Kerioth, and Hezron, which is Hazor, ^26Amam, and Shema, and Moladah, ^27and Hazargaddah, and Heshmon, and Bethpalet, ^28and Hazarshual, and Beersheba, and Bizjothjah, ^29Baalah, and Iim, and Azem, ^30and Eltolad, and Chesil, and Hormah, ^31and Ziklag, and Madmannah, and Sansannah, ^32and Lebaoth, and Shilhim, and Ain, and Rimmon: all the cities are twenty and nine, with their villages: ^33and in the valley, Eshtaol, and Zoreah, and Ashnah, ^34and Zanoah, and Engannim, Tappuah, and Enam, ^35Jarmuth, and Adullam, Socoh, and Azekah, ^36and Sharaim, and Adithaim, and Gederah, and Gederothaim; fourteen cities with their villages: ^37Zenan, and Hadashah, and Migdalgad, ^38and Dilean, and Mizpeh, and Joktheel, ^39Lachish, and Bozkath, and Eglon, ^40and Cabbon, and Lahmam, and Kithlish, ^41and Gederoth, Bethdagon, and Naamah, and Makkedah; sixteen cities with their villages: ^42Libnah, and Ether, and Ashan, ^43and Jiphtah, and Ashnah, and Nezib, ^44and Keilah, and Achzib, and Mareshah; nine cities with their villages: ^45Ekron, with her towns and her villages: ^46from Ekron even unto the sea, all that lay near Ashdod, with their villages: ^47Ashdod with her towns and her villages, Gaza with her towns and her villages, unto the river of Egypt, and the great sea, and the border thereof:

^48and in the mountains, Shamir, and Jattir, and Socoh, ^49and Dannah, and Kirjathsannah, which is Debir, ^50and Anab, and Eshtemoh, and Anim, ^51and Goshen, and Holon, and Giloh; eleven cities with their villages: ^52Arab, and Dumah, and Eshean, ^53and Janum, and Bethtappuah, and Aphekah, ^54and Humtah, and Kirjatharba, which is Hebron, and Zior; nine cities with their villages: ^55Maon, Carmel, and Ziph, and Juttah, ^56and Jezreel, and Jokdeam, and Zanoah, ^57Cain, Gibeah, and Timnah; ten cities with their villages: ^58Halhul, Bethzur, and Gedor, ^59and Maarath, and Bethanoth, and Eltekon; six cities with their villages: ^60Kirjathbaal, which is Kirjathjearim, and Rabbah; two cities with their villages: ^61in the wilderness, Betharabah, Middin, and Secacah, ^62and Nibshan, and the city of Salt, and Engedi; six cities with their villages.

^63As for the Jebusites the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the children of Judah could not drive them out; but the Jebusites dwell with the children of Judah at Jerusalem unto this day.

XVI

^1And the lot of the children of Joseph fell from Jordan by Jericho, unto the water of Jericho on the east, to the wilderness that goeth up from Jericho throughout mount Bethel, ^2and goeth out from Bethel to Luz, and passeth along unto the borders of Archi to Ataroth, ^3and goeth down westward to the coast of Japhleti, unto the coast of Bethhoron the nether, and to Gezer; and the goings out thereof are at the sea. ^4So the children of Joseph, Manasseh and Ephraim, took their inheritance.

^5And the border of the children of Ephraim according to their families was thus: even the border of their inheritance on the east side was Atarothaddar, unto Bethhoron the upper; ^6and the border went out toward the sea to Michmethah on the north side; and the border went about eastward unto Taanathshiloh, and passed by it on the east to Janohah; ^7and it went down from Janohah to Ataroth, and to Naarath, and came to Jericho, and went out at Jordan. ^8The border went out from Tappuah westward unto the river Kanah; and the goings out thereof were at the sea. This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Ephraim by their families. ^9And the separate cities for the children of Ephraim were among the inheritance of the children of Manasseh, all the cities with their villages. ^10And they drave not out the Canaanites that dwelt in Gezer: but the Canaanites dwell among the Ephraimites unto this day, and serve under tribute.

XVII

^1There was also a lot for the tribe of Manasseh; for he was the firstborn of Joseph; to wit, for Machir the firstborn of Manasseh, the father of Gilead: because he was a man of war, therefore he had Gilead and Bashan. ^2There was also a lot for the rest of the children of Manasseh by their families; for the children of Abiezer, and for the children of Helek, and for the children of Asriel, and for the children of Shechem, and for the children of Hepher, and for the children of Shemida: these were the male children of Manasseh the son of Joseph by their families. ^3But Zelophehad, the son of Hepher, the son of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, had no sons, but daughters: and these are the names of his daughters, Mahlah, and Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah. ^4And they came near before Eleazar the priest, and before Joshua the son of Nun, and before the princes, saying, The Lord commanded Moses to give us an inheritance among our brethren. Therefore according to the commandment of the Lord he gave them an inheritance among the brethren of their father. ^5And there fell ten portions to Manasseh, beside the land of Gilead and Bashan, which were on the other side Jordan; ^6because the daughters of Manasseh had an inheritance among his sons: and the rest of Manasseh’s sons had the land of Gilead.

^7And the coast of Manasseh was from Asher to Michmethah, that lieth before Shechem; and the border went along on the right hand unto the inhabitants of Entappuah. ^8Now Manasseh had the land of Tappuah: but Tappuah on the border of Manasseh belonged to the children of Ephraim; ^9and the coast descended unto the river Kanah, southward of the river: these cities of Ephraim are among the cities of Manasseh: the coast of Manasseh also was on the north side of the river, and the outgoings of it were at the sea: ^10southward it was Ephraim’s, and northward it was Manasseh’s, and the sea is his border; and they met together in Asher on the north, and in Issachar on the east. ^11And Manasseh had in Issachar and in Asher Bethshean and her towns, and Ibleam and her towns, and the inhabitants of Dor and her towns, and the inhabitants of Endor and her towns, and the inhabitants of Taanach and her towns, and the inhabitants of Megiddo and her towns, even three countries. ^12Yet the children of Manasseh could not drive out the inhabitants of those cities; but the Canaanites would dwell in that land. ^13Yet it came to pass, when the children of Israel were waxen strong, that they put the Canaanites to tribute, but did not utterly drive them out.

^14And the children of Joseph spake unto Joshua, saying, Why hast thou given me but one lot and one portion to inherit, seeing I am a great people, forasmuch as the Lord hath blessed me hitherto? ^15And Joshua answered them, If thou be a great people, then get thee up to the wood country, and cut down for thyself there in the land of the Perizzites and of the giants, if mount Ephraim be too narrow for thee. ^16And the children of Joseph said, The hill is not enough for us: and all the Canaanites that dwell in the land of the valley have chariots of iron, both they who are of Bethshean and her towns, and they who are of the valley of Jezreel. ^17And Joshua spake unto the house of Joseph, even to Ephraim and to Manasseh, saying, Thou art a great people, and hast great power: thou shalt not have one lot only: ^18but the mountain shall be thine; for it is a wood, and thou shalt cut it down: and the outgoings of it shall be thine: for thou shalt drive out the Canaanites, though they have iron chariots, and though they be strong.

XVIII

^1And the whole congregation of the children of Israel assembled together at Shiloh, and set up the tabernacle of the congregation there. And the land was subdued before them. ^2And there remained among the children of Israel seven tribes, which had not yet received their inheritance. ^3And Joshua said unto the children of Israel, How long are ye slack to go to possess the land, which the Lord God of your fathers hath given you? ^4Give out from among you three men for each tribe: and I will send them, and they shall rise, and go through the land, and describe it according to the inheritance of them; and they shall come again to me. ^5And they shall divide it into seven parts: Judah shall abide in their coast on the south, and the house of Joseph shall abide in their coasts on the north. ^6Ye shall therefore describe the land into seven parts, and bring the description hither to me, that I may cast lots for you here before the Lord our God. ^7But the Levites have no part among you; for the priesthood of the Lord is their inheritance: and Gad, and Reuben, and half the tribe of Manasseh, have received their inheritance beyond Jordan on the east, which Moses the servant of the Lord gave them.

^8And the men arose, and went away: and Joshua charged them that went to describe the land, saying, Go and walk through the land, and describe it, and come again to me, that I may here cast lots for you before the Lord in Shiloh. ^9And the men went and passed through the land, and described it by cities into seven parts in a book, and came again to Joshua to the host at Shiloh. ^10And Joshua cast lots for them in Shiloh before the Lord: and there Joshua divided the land unto the children of Israel according to their divisions.

^11And the lot of the tribe of the children of Benjamin came up according to their families: and the coast of their lot came forth between the children of Judah and the children of Joseph. ^12And their border on the north side was from Jordan; and the border went up to the side of Jericho on the north side, and went up through the mountains westward; and the goings out thereof were at the wilderness of Bethaven. ^13And the border went over from thence toward Luz, to the side of Luz, which is Bethel, southward; and the border descended to Atarothadar, near the hill that lieth on the south side of the nether Bethhoron. ^14And the border was drawn thence, and compassed the corner of the sea southward, from the hill that lieth before Bethhoron southward; and the goings out thereof were at Kirjathbaal, which is Kirjathjearim, a city of the children of Judah: this was the west quarter. ^15And the south quarter was from the end of Kirjathjearim, and the border went out on the west, and went out to the well of waters of Nephtoah: ^16and the border came down to the end of the mountain that lieth before the valley of the son of Hinnom, and which is in the valley of the giants on the north, and descended to the valley of Hinnom, to the side of Jebusi on the south, and descended to Enrogel, ^17and was drawn from the north, and went forth to Enshemesh, and went forth toward Geliloth, which is over against the going up of Adummim, and descended to the stone of Bohan the son of Reuben, ^18and passed along toward the side over against Arabah northward, and went down unto Arabah: ^19and the border passed along to the side of Bethhoglah northward: and the outgoings of the border were at the north bay of the salt sea at the south end of Jordan: this was the south coast. ^20And Jordan was the border of it on the east side. This was the inheritance of the children of Benjamin, by the coasts thereof round about, according to their families.

^21Now the cities of the tribe of the children of Benjamin according to their families were Jericho, and Bethhoglah, and the valley of Keziz, ^22and Betharabah, and Zemaraim, and Bethel, ^23and Avim, and Pharah, and Ophrah, ^24and Chepharhaammonai, and Ophni, and Gaba; twelve cities with their villages: ^25Gibeon, and Ramah, and Beeroth, ^26and Mizpeh, and Chephirah, and Mozah, ^27and Rekem, and Irpeel, and Taralah, ^28and Zelah, Eleph, and Jebusi, which is Jerusalem, Gibeath, and Kirjath; fourteen cities with their villages. This is the inheritance of the children of Benjamin according to their families.

XIX

^1And the second lot came forth to Simeon, even for the tribe of the children of Simeon according to their families: and their inheritance was within the inheritance of the children of Judah. ^2And they had in their inheritance Beersheba, and Sheba, and Moladah, ^3and Hazarshual, and Balah, and Azem, ^4and Eltolad, and Bethul, and Hormah, ^5and Ziklag, and Bethmarcaboth, and Hazarsusah, ^6and Bethlebaoth, and Sharuhen; thirteen cities and their villages: ^7Ain, Remmon, and Ether, and Ashan; four cities and their villages: ^8and all the villages that were round about these cities to Baalathbeer, Ramath of the south. This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Simeon according to their families. ^9Out of the portion of the children of Judah was the inheritance of the children of Simeon: for the part of the children of Judah was too much for them: therefore the children of Simeon had their inheritance within the inheritance of them.

^10And the third lot came up for the children of Zebulun according to their families: and the border of their inheritance was unto Sarid: ^11and their border went up toward the sea, and Maralah, and reached to Dabbasheth, and reached to the river that is before Jokneam; ^12and turned from Sarid eastward toward the sunrising unto the border of Chislothtabor, and then goeth out to Daberath, and goeth up to Japhia, ^13and from thence passeth on along on the east to Gittahhepher, to Ittahkazin, and goeth out to Remmonmethoar to Neah; ^14and the border compasseth it on the north side to Hannathon: and the outgoings thereof are in the valley of Jiphthahel: ^15and Kattath, and Nahallal, and Shimron, and Idalah, and Bethlehem: twelve cities with their villages. ^16This is the inheritance of the children of Zebulun according to their families, these cities with their villages.

^17And the fourth lot came out to Issachar, for the children of Issachar according to their families. ^18And their border was toward Jezreel, and Chesulloth, and Shunem, ^19and Haphraim, and Shihon, and Anaharath, ^20and Rabbith, and Kishion, and Abez, ^21and Remeth, and Engannim, and Enhaddah, and Bethpazzez; ^22and the coast reacheth to Tabor, and Shahazimah, and Bethshemesh; and the outgoings of their border were at Jordan: sixteen cities with their villages. ^23This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Issachar according to their families, the cities and their villages.

^24And the fifth lot came out for the tribe of the children of Asher according to their families. ^25And their border was Helkath, and Hali, and Beten, and Achshaph, ^26and Alammelech, and Amad, and Misheal; and reacheth to Carmel westward, and to Shihorlibnath; ^27and turneth toward the sunrising to Bethdagon, and reacheth to Zebulun, and to the valley of Jiphthahel toward the north side of Bethemek, and Neiel, and goeth out to Cabul on the left hand, ^28and Hebron, and Rehob, and Hammon, and Kanah, even unto great Zidon; ^29and then the coast turneth to Ramah, and to the strong city Tyre; and the coast turneth to Hosah; and the outgoings thereof are at the sea from the coast to Achzib: ^30Ummah also, and Aphek, and Rehob: twenty and two cities with their villages. ^31This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Asher according to their families, these cities with their villages.

^32The sixth lot came out to the children of Naphtali, even for the children of Naphtali according to their families. ^33And their coast was from Heleph, from Allon to Zaanannim, and Adami, Nekeb, and Jabneel, unto Lakum; and the outgoings thereof were at Jordan: ^34and then the coast turneth westward to Aznothtabor, and goeth out from thence to Hukkok, and reacheth to Zebulun on the south side, and reacheth to Asher on the west side, and to Judah upon Jordan toward the sunrising. ^35And the fenced cities are Ziddim, Zer, and Hammath, Rakkath, and Chinnereth, ^36and Adamah, and Ramah, and Hazor, ^37and Kedesh, and Edrei, and Enhazor, ^38and Iron, and Migdalel, Horem, and Bethanath, and Bethshemesh; nineteen cities with their villages. ^39This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Naphtali according to their families, the cities and their villages.

^40And the seventh lot came out for the tribe of the children of Dan according to their families. ^41And the coast of their inheritance was Zorah, and Eshtaol, and Irshemesh, ^42and Shaalabbin, and Ajalon, and Jethlah, ^43and Elon, and Thimnathah, and Ekron, ^44and Eltekeh, and Gibbethon, and Baalath, ^45and Jehud, and Beneberak, and Gathrimmon, ^46and Mejarkon, and Rakkon, with the border before Japho. ^47And the coast of the children of Dan went out too little for them: therefore the children of Dan went up to fight against Leshem, and took it, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and possessed it, and dwelt therein, and called Leshem, Dan, after the name of Dan their father. ^48This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Dan according to their families, these cities with their villages.

^49When they had made an end of dividing the land for inheritance by their coasts, the children of Israel gave an inheritance to Joshua the son of Nun among them: ^50according to the word of the Lord they gave him the city which he asked, even Timnathserah in mount Ephraim: and he built the city, and dwelt therein.

^51These are the inheritances, which Eleazar the priest, and Joshua the son of Nun, and the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the children of Israel, divided for an inheritance by lot in Shiloh before the Lord, at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. So they made an end of dividing the country.

XX

^1The Lord also spake unto Joshua, saying, ^2Speak to the children of Israel, saying, Appoint out for you cities of refuge, whereof I spake unto you by the hand of Moses: ^3that the slayer that killeth any person unawares and unwittingly may flee thither: and they shall be your refuge from the avenger of blood. ^4And when he that doth flee unto one of those cities shall stand at the entering of the gate of the city, and shall declare his cause in the ears of the elders of that city, they shall take him into the city unto them, and give him a place, that he may dwell among them. ^5And if the avenger of blood pursue after him, then they shall not deliver the slayer up into his hand; because he smote his neighbour unwittingly, and hated him not beforetime. ^6And he shall dwell in that city, until he stand before the congregation for judgment, and until the death of the high priest that shall be in those days: then shall the slayer return, and come unto his own city, and unto his own house, unto the city from whence he fled.

^7And they appointed Kedesh in Galilee in mount Naphtali, and Shechem in mount Ephraim, and Kirjatharba, which is Hebron, in the mountain of Judah. ^8And on the other side Jordan by Jericho eastward, they assigned Bezer in the wilderness upon the plain out of the tribe of Reuben, and Ramoth in Gilead out of the tribe of Gad, and Golan in Bashan out of the tribe of Manasseh. ^9These were the cities appointed for all the children of Israel, and for the stranger that sojourneth among them, that whosoever killeth any person at unawares might flee thither, and not die by the hand of the avenger of blood, until he stood before the congregation.

XXI

^1Then came near the heads of the fathers of the Levites unto Eleazar the priest, and unto Joshua the son of Nun, and unto the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the children of Israel; ^2and they spake unto them at Shiloh in the land of Canaan, saying, The Lord commanded by the hand of Moses to give us cities to dwell in, with the suburbs thereof for our cattle. ^3And the children of Israel gave unto the Levites out of their inheritance, at the commandment of the Lord, these cities and their suburbs.

^4And the lot came out for the families of the Kohathites: and the children of Aaron the priest, which were of the Levites, had by lot out of the tribe of Judah, and out of the tribe of Simeon, and out of the tribe of Benjamin, thirteen cities. ^5And the rest of the children of Kohath had by lot out of the families of the tribe of Ephraim, and out of the tribe of Dan, and out of the half tribe of Manasseh, ten cities. ^6And the children of Gershon had by lot out of the families of the tribe of Issachar, and out of the tribe of Asher, and out of the tribe of Naphtali, and out of the half tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteen cities. ^7The children of Merari by their families had out of the tribe of Reuben, and out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun, twelve cities.

^8And the children of Israel gave by lot unto the Levites these cities with their suburbs, as the Lord commanded by the hand of Moses. ^9And they gave out of the tribe of the children of Judah, and out of the tribe of the children of Simeon, these cities which are here mentioned by name. ^10Which the children of Aaron, being of the families of the Kohathites, who were of the children of Levi, had: for theirs was the first lot. ^11And they gave them the city of Arba the father of Anak, which city is Hebron, in the hill country of Judah, with the suburbs thereof round about it. ^12But the fields of the city, and the villages thereof, gave they to Caleb the son of Jephunneh for his possession.

^13Thus they gave to the children of Aaron the priest Hebron with her suburbs, to be a city of refuge for the slayer; and Libnah with her suburbs, ^14and Jattir with her suburbs, and Eshtemoa with her suburbs, ^15and Holon with her suburbs, and Debir with her suburbs, ^16and Ain with her suburbs, and Juttah with her suburbs, and Bethshemesh with her suburbs; nine cities out of those two tribes. ^17And out of the tribe of Benjamin, Gibeon with her suburbs, Geba with her suburbs, ^18Anathoth with her suburbs, and Almon with her suburbs; four cities. ^19All the cities of the children of Aaron, the priests, were thirteen cities with their suburbs.

^20And the families of the children of Kohath, the Levites which remained of the children of Kohath, even they had the cities of their lot out of the tribe of Ephraim. ^21For they gave them Shechem with her suburbs in mount Ephraim, to be a city of refuge for the slayer; and Gezer with her suburbs, ^22and Kibzaim with her suburbs, and Bethhoron with her suburbs; four cities. ^23And out of the tribe of Dan, Eltekeh with her suburbs, Gibbethon with her suburbs, ^24Aijalon with her suburbs, Gathrimmon with her suburbs; four cities. ^25And out of the half tribe of Manasseh, Tanach with her suburbs, and Gathrimmon with her suburbs; two cities. ^26All the cities were ten with their suburbs for the families of the children of Kohath that remained.

^27And unto the children of Gershon, of the families of the Levites, out of the other half tribe of Manasseh they gave Golan in Bashan with her suburbs, to be a city of refuge for the slayer; and Beeshterah with her suburbs; two cities. ^28And out of the tribe of Issachar, Kishon with her suburbs, Dabareh with her suburbs, ^29Jarmuth with her suburbs, Engannim with her suburbs; four cities. ^30And out of the tribe of Asher, Mishal with her suburbs, Abdon with her suburbs, ^31Helkath with her suburbs, and Rehob with her suburbs; four cities. ^32And out of the tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee with her suburbs, to be a city of refuge for the slayer; and Hammothdor with her suburbs, and Kartan with her suburbs; three cities. ^33All the cities of the Gershonites according to their families were thirteen cities with their suburbs.

^34And unto the families of the children of Merari, the rest of the Levites, out of the tribe of Zebulun, Jokneam with her suburbs, and Kartah with her suburbs, ^35Dimnah with her suburbs, Nahalal with her suburbs; four cities. ^36And out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer with her suburbs, and Jahazah with her suburbs, ^37Kedemoth with her suburbs, and Mephaath with her suburbs; four cities. ^38And out of the tribe of Gad, Ramoth in Gilead with her suburbs, to be a city of refuge for the slayer; and Mahanaim with her suburbs, ^39Heshbon with her suburbs, Jazer with her suburbs; four cities in all. ^40So all the cities for the children of Merari by their families, which were remaining of the families of the Levites, were by their lot twelve cities.

^41All the cities of the Levites within the possession of the children of Israel were forty and eight cities with their suburbs. ^42These cities were every one with their suburbs round about them: thus were all these cities.

^43And the Lord gave unto Israel all the land which he sware to give unto their fathers; and they possessed it, and dwelt therein. ^44And the Lord gave them rest round about, according to all that he sware unto their fathers: and there stood not a man of all their enemies before them; the Lord delivered all their enemies into their hand. ^45There failed not ought of any good thing which the Lord had spoken unto the house of Israel; all came to pass.

XXII

^1Then Joshua called the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half tribe of Manasseh, ^2and said unto them, Ye have kept all that Moses the servant of the Lord commanded you, and have obeyed my voice in all that I commanded you: ^3ye have not left your brethren these many days unto this day, but have kept the charge of the commandment of the Lord your God. ^4And now the Lord your God hath given rest unto your brethren, as he promised them: therefore now return ye, and get you unto your tents, and unto the land of your possession, which Moses the servant of the Lord gave you on the other side Jordan. ^5But take diligent heed to do the commandment and the law, which Moses the servant of the Lord charged you, to love the Lord your God, and to walk in all his ways, and to keep his commandments, and to cleave unto him, and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul. ^6So Joshua blessed them, and sent them away: and they went unto their tents.

^7Now to the one half of the tribe of Manasseh Moses had given possession in Bashan: but unto the other half thereof gave Joshua among their brethren on this side Jordan westward. And when Joshua sent them away also unto their tents, then he blessed them, ^8and he spake unto them, saying, Return with much riches unto your tents, and with very much cattle, with silver, and with gold, and with brass, and with iron, and with very much raiment: divide the spoil of your enemies with your brethren. ^9And the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the half tribe of Manasseh returned, and departed from the children of Israel out of Shiloh, which is in the land of Canaan, to go unto the country of Gilead, to the land of their possession, whereof they were possessed, according to the word of the Lord by the hand of Moses.

^10And when they came unto the borders of Jordan, that are in the land of Canaan, the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the half tribe of Manasseh built there an altar by Jordan, a great altar to see to. ^11And the children of Israel heard say, Behold, the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the half tribe of Manasseh have built an altar over against the land of Canaan, in the borders of Jordan, at the passage of the children of Israel. ^12And when the children of Israel heard of it, the whole congregation of the children of Israel gathered themselves together at Shiloh, to go up to war against them.

^13And the children of Israel sent unto the children of Reuben, and to the children of Gad, and to the half tribe of Manasseh, into the land of Gilead, Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest, ^14and with him ten princes, of each chief house a prince throughout all the tribes of Israel; and each one was an head of the house of their fathers among the thousands of Israel. ^15And they came unto the children of Reuben, and to the children of Gad, and to the half tribe of Manasseh, unto the land of Gilead, and they spake with them, saying, ^16Thus saith the whole congregation of the Lord, What trespass is this that ye have committed against the God of Israel, to turn away this day from following the Lord, in that ye have builded you an altar, that ye might rebel this day against the Lord? ^17Is the iniquity of Peor too little for us, from which we are not cleansed until this day, although there was a plague in the congregation of the Lord, ^18But that ye must turn away this day from following the Lord? and it will be, seeing ye rebel to day against the Lord, that to morrow he will be wroth with the whole congregation of Israel. ^19Notwithstanding, if the land of your possession be unclean, then pass ye over unto the land of the possession of the Lord, wherein the Lord’s tabernacle dwelleth, and take possession among us: but rebel not against the Lord, nor rebel against us, in building you an altar beside the altar of the Lord our God. ^20Did not Achan the son of Zerah commit a trespass in the accursed thing, and wrath fell on all the congregation of Israel? and that man perished not alone in his iniquity.

^21Then the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the half tribe of Manasseh answered, and said unto the heads of the thousands of Israel, ^22The Lord God of gods, the Lord God of gods, he knoweth, and Israel he shall know; if it be in rebellion, or if in transgression against the Lord, (save us not this day,) ^23that we have built us an altar to turn from following the Lord, or if to offer thereon burnt offering or meat offering, or if to offer peace offerings thereon, let the Lord himself require it; ^24and if we have not rather done it for fear of this thing, saying, In time to come your children might speak unto our children, saying, What have ye to do with the Lord God of Israel? ^25For the Lord hath made Jordan a border between us and you, ye children of Reuben and children of Gad; ye have no part in the Lord: so shall your children make our children cease from fearing the Lord. ^26Therefore we said, Let us now prepare to build us an altar, not for burnt offering, nor for sacrifice: ^27but that it may be a witness between us, and you, and our generations after us, that we might do the service of the Lord before him with our burnt offerings, and with our sacrifices, and with our peace offerings; that your children may not say to our children in time to come, Ye have no part in the Lord. ^28Therefore said we, that it shall be, when they should so say to us or to our generations in time to come, that we may say again, Behold the pattern of the altar of the Lord, which our fathers made, not for burnt offerings, nor for sacrifices; but it is a witness between us and you. ^29God forbid that we should rebel against the Lord, and turn this day from following the Lord, to build an altar for burnt offerings, for meat offerings, or for sacrifices, beside the altar of the Lord our God that is before his tabernacle.

^30And when Phinehas the priest, and the princes of the congregation and heads of the thousands of Israel which were with him, heard the words that the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the children of Manasseh spake, it pleased them. ^31And Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest said unto the children of Reuben, and to the children of Gad, and to the children of Manasseh, This day we perceive that the Lord is among us, because ye have not committed this trespass against the Lord: now ye have delivered the children of Israel out of the hand of the Lord. ^32And Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest, and the princes, returned from the children of Reuben, and from the children of Gad, out of the land of Gilead, unto the land of Canaan, to the children of Israel, and brought them word again. ^33And the thing pleased the children of Israel; and the children of Israel blessed God, and did not intend to go up against them in battle, to destroy the land wherein the children of Reuben and Gad dwelt. ^34And the children of Reuben and the children of Gad called the altar Ed: for it shall be a witness between us that the Lord is God.

XXIII

^1And it came to pass a long time after that the Lord had given rest unto Israel from all their enemies round about, that Joshua waxed old and stricken in age. ^2And Joshua called for all Israel, and for their elders, and for their heads, and for their judges, and for their officers, and said unto them, I am old and stricken in age: ^3and ye have seen all that the Lord your God hath done unto all these nations because of you; for the Lord your God is he that hath fought for you. ^4Behold, I have divided unto you by lot these nations that remain, to be an inheritance for your tribes, from Jordan, with all the nations that I have cut off, even unto the great sea westward. ^5And the Lord your God, he shall expel them from before you, and drive them from out of your sight; and ye shall possess their land, as the Lord your God hath promised unto you. ^6Be ye therefore very courageous to keep and to do all that is written in the book of the law of Moses, that ye turn not aside therefrom to the right hand or to the left; ^7that ye come not among these nations, these that remain among you; neither make mention of the name of their gods, nor cause to swear by them, neither serve them, nor bow yourselves unto them: ^8but cleave unto the Lord your God, as ye have done unto this day. ^9For the Lord hath driven out from before you great nations and strong: but as for you, no man hath been able to stand before you unto this day. ^10One man of you shall chase a thousand: for the Lord your God, he it is that fighteth for you, as he hath promised you. ^11Take good heed therefore unto yourselves, that ye love the Lord your God. ^12Else if ye do in any wise go back, and cleave unto the remnant of these nations, even these that remain among you, and shall make marriages with them, and go in unto them, and they to you: ^13know for a certainty that the Lord your God will no more drive out any of these nations from before you; but they shall be snares and traps unto you, and scourges in your sides, and thorns in your eyes, until ye perish from off this good land which the Lord your God hath given you.

^14And, behold, this day I am going the way of all the earth: and ye know in all your hearts and in all your souls, that not one thing hath failed of all the good things which the Lord your God spake concerning you; all are come to pass unto you, and not one thing hath failed thereof. ^15Therefore it shall come to pass, that as all good things are come upon you, which the Lord your God promised you; so shall the Lord bring upon you all evil things, until he have destroyed you from off this good land which the Lord your God hath given you. ^16When ye have transgressed the covenant of the Lord your God, which he commanded you, and have gone and served other gods, and bowed yourselves to them; then shall the anger of the Lord be kindled against you, and ye shall perish quickly from off the good land which he hath given unto you.

XXIV

^1And Joshua gathered all the tribes of Israel to Shechem, and called for the elders of Israel, and for their heads, and for their judges, and for their officers; and they presented themselves before God. ^2And Joshua said unto all the people, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, Your fathers dwelt on the other side of the flood in old time, even Terah, the father of Abraham, and the father of Nachor: and they served other gods. ^3And I took your father Abraham from the other side of the flood, and led him throughout all the land of Canaan, and multiplied his seed, and gave him Isaac. ^4And I gave unto Isaac Jacob and Esau: and I gave unto Esau mount Seir, to possess it; but Jacob and his children went down into Egypt. ^5I sent Moses also and Aaron, and I plagued Egypt, according to that which I did among them: and afterward I brought you out. ^6And I brought your fathers out of Egypt: and ye came unto the sea; and the Egyptians pursued after your fathers with chariots and horsemen unto the Red sea. ^7And when they cried unto the Lord, he put darkness between you and the Egyptians, and brought the sea upon them, and covered them; and your eyes have seen what I have done in Egypt: and ye dwelt in the wilderness a long season. ^8And I brought you into the land of the Amorites, which dwelt on the other side Jordan; and they fought with you: and I gave them into your hand, that ye might possess their land; and I destroyed them from before you. ^9Then Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab, arose and warred against Israel, and sent and called Balaam the son of Beor to curse you: ^10but I would not hearken unto Balaam; therefore he blessed you still: so I delivered you out of his hand. ^11And you went over Jordan, and came unto Jericho: and the men of Jericho fought against you, the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Canaanites, and the Hittites, and the Girgashites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites; and I delivered them into your hand. ^12And I sent the hornet before you, which drave them out from before you, even the two kings of the Amorites; but not with thy sword, nor with thy bow. ^13And I have given you a land for which ye did not labour, and cities which ye built not, and ye dwell in them; of the vineyards and oliveyards which ye planted not do ye eat.

^14Now therefore fear the Lord, and serve him in sincerity and in truth: and put away the gods which your fathers served on the other side of the flood, and in Egypt; and serve ye the Lord. ^15And if it seem evil unto you to serve the Lord, choose you this day whom ye will serve; whether the gods which your fathers served that were on the other side of the flood, or the gods of the Amorites, in whose land ye dwell: but as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord.

^16And the people answered and said, God forbid that we should forsake the Lord, to serve other gods; ^17for the Lord our God, he it is that brought us up and our fathers out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage, and which did those great signs in our sight, and preserved us in all the way wherein we went, and among all the people through whom we passed: ^18and the Lord drave out from before us all the people, even the Amorites which dwelt in the land: therefore will we also serve the Lord; for he is our God.

^19And Joshua said unto the people, Ye cannot serve the Lord: for he is an holy God; he is a jealous God; he will not forgive your transgressions nor your sins. ^20If ye forsake the Lord, and serve strange gods, then he will turn and do you hurt, and consume you, after that he hath done you good. ^21And the people said unto Joshua, Nay; but we will serve the Lord. ^22And Joshua said unto the people, Ye are witnesses against yourselves that ye have chosen you the Lord, to serve him. And they said, We are witnesses. ^23Now therefore put away, said he, the strange gods which are among you, and incline your heart unto the Lord God of Israel. ^24And the people said unto Joshua, The Lord our God will we serve, and his voice will we obey. ^25So Joshua made a covenant with the people that day, and set them a statute and an ordinance in Shechem. ^26And Joshua wrote these words in the book of the law of God, and took a great stone, and set it up there under an oak, that was by the sanctuary of the Lord. ^27And Joshua said unto all the people, Behold, this stone shall be a witness unto us; for it hath heard all the words of the Lord which he spake unto us: it shall be therefore a witness unto you, lest ye deny your God. ^28So Joshua let the people depart, every man unto his inheritance.

^29And it came to pass after these things, that Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of the Lord, died, being an hundred and ten years old. ^30And they buried him in the border of his inheritance in Timnathserah, which is in mount Ephraim, on the north side of the hill of Gaash. ^31And Israel served the Lord all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders that overlived Joshua, and which had known all the works of the Lord, that he had done for Israel.

^32And the bones of Joseph, which the children of Israel brought up out of Egypt, buried they in Shechem, in a parcel of ground which Jacob bought of the sons of Hamor the father of Shechem for an hundred pieces of silver: and it became the inheritance of the children of Joseph. ^33And Eleazar the son of Aaron died; and they buried him in a hill that pertained to Phinehas his son, which was given him in mount Ephraim.

Judges

The Book of

Judges

I

1^1Now after the death of Joshua it came to pass, that the children of Israel asked the Lord, saying, Who shall go up for us against the Canaanites first, to fight against them?

^2And the Lord said, Judah shall go up: behold, I have delivered the land into his hand.

^3And Judah said unto Simeon his brother, Come up with me into my lot, that we may fight against the Canaanites; and I likewise will go with thee into thy lot. So Simeon went with him.

^4And Judah went up; and the Lord delivered the Canaanites and the Perizzites into their hand: and they slew of them in Bezek ten thousand men.

^5And they found Adonibezek in Bezek: and they fought against him, and they slew the Canaanites and the Perizzites.

^6But Adonibezek fled; and they pursued after him, and caught him, and cut off his thumbs and his great toes.

^7And Adonibezek said, Threescore and ten kings, having their thumbs and their great toes cut off, gathered their meat under my table: as I have done, so God hath requited me. And they brought him to Jerusalem, and there he died.

^8Now the children of Judah had fought against Jerusalem, and had taken it, and smitten it with the edge of the sword, and set the city on fire.

^9And afterward the children of Judah went down to fight against the Canaanites, that dwelt in the mountain, and in the south, and in the valley.

^10And Judah went against the Canaanites that dwelt in Hebron: (now the name of Hebron before was Kirjatharba:) and they slew Sheshai, and Ahiman, and Talmai.

^11And from thence he went against the inhabitants of Debir: and the name of Debir before was Kirjathsepher:

^12And Caleb said, He that smiteth Kirjathsepher, and taketh it, to him will I give Achsah my daughter to wife.

^13And Othniel the son of Kenaz, Caleb’s younger brother, took it: and he gave him Achsah his daughter to wife.

^14And it came to pass, when she came to him, that she moved him to ask of her father a field: and she lighted from off her ass; and Caleb said unto her, What wilt thou?

^15And she said unto him, Give me a blessing: for thou hast given me a south land; give me also springs of water. And Caleb gave her the upper springs and the nether springs.

^16And the children of the Kenite, Moses’ father in law, went up out of the city of palm trees with the children of Judah into the wilderness of Judah, which lieth in the south of Arad; and they went and dwelt among the people.

^17And Judah went with Simeon his brother, and they slew the Canaanites that inhabited Zephath, and utterly destroyed it. And the name of the city was called Hormah.

^18Also Judah took Gaza with the coast thereof, and Askelon with the coast thereof, and Ekron with the coast thereof.

^19And the Lord was with Judah; and he drave out the inhabitants of the mountain; but could not drive out the inhabitants of the valley, because they had chariots of iron.

^20And they gave Hebron unto Caleb, as Moses said: and he expelled thence the three sons of Anak.

^21And the children of Benjamin did not drive out the Jebusites that inhabited Jerusalem; but the Jebusites dwell with the children of Benjamin in Jerusalem unto this day.

^22And the house of Joseph, they also went up against Bethel: and the Lord was with them.

^23And the house of Joseph sent to descry Bethel. (Now the name of the city before was Luz.)

^24And the spies saw a man come forth out of the city, and they said unto him, Shew us, we pray thee, the entrance into the city, and we will shew thee mercy.

^25And when he shewed them the entrance into the city, they smote the city with the edge of the sword; but they let go the man and all his family.

^26And the man went into the land of the Hittites, and built a city, and called the name thereof Luz: which is the name thereof unto this day.

^27Neither did Manasseh drive out the inhabitants of Bethshean and her towns, nor Taanach and her towns, nor the inhabitants of Dor and her towns, nor the inhabitants of Ibleam and her towns, nor the inhabitants of Megiddo and her towns: but the Canaanites would dwell in that land.

^28And it came to pass, when Israel was strong, that they put the Canaanites to tribute, and did not utterly drive them out.

^29Neither did Ephraim drive out the Canaanites that dwelt in Gezer; but the Canaanites dwelt in Gezer among them.

^30Neither did Zebulun drive out the inhabitants of Kitron, nor the inhabitants of Nahalol; but the Canaanites dwelt among them, and became tributaries.

^31Neither did Asher drive out the inhabitants of Accho, nor the inhabitants of Zidon, nor of Ahlab, nor of Achzib, nor of Helbah, nor of Aphik, nor of Rehob:

^32But the Asherites dwelt among the Canaanites, the inhabitants of the land: for they did not drive them out.

^33Neither did Naphtali drive out the inhabitants of Bethshemesh, nor the inhabitants of Bethanath; but he dwelt among the Canaanites, the inhabitants of the land: nevertheless the inhabitants of Bethshemesh and of Bethanath became tributaries unto them.

^34And the Amorites forced the children of Dan into the mountain: for they would not suffer them to come down to the valley:

^35But the Amorites would dwell in mount Heres in Aijalon, and in Shaalbim: yet the hand of the house of Joseph prevailed, so that they became tributaries.

^36And the coast of the Amorites was from the going up to Akrabbim, from the rock, and upward.

II

2^1And an angel of the Lord came up from Gilgal to Bochim, and said, I made you to go up out of Egypt, and have brought you unto the land which I sware unto your fathers; and I said, I will never break my covenant with you.

^2And ye shall make no league with the inhabitants of this land; ye shall throw down their altars: but ye have not obeyed my voice: why have ye done this?

^3Wherefore I also said, I will not drive them out from before you; but they shall be as thorns in your sides, and their gods shall be a snare unto you.

^4And it came to pass, when the angel of the Lord spake these words unto all the children of Israel, that the people lifted up their voice, and wept.

^5And they called the name of that place Bochim: and they sacrificed there unto the Lord.

^6And when Joshua had let the people go, the children of Israel went every man unto his inheritance to possess the land.

^7And the people served the Lord all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders that outlived Joshua, who had seen all the great works of the Lord, that he did for Israel.

^8And Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of the Lord, died, being an hundred and ten years old.

^9And they buried him in the border of his inheritance in Timnathheres, in the mount of Ephraim, on the north side of the hill Gaash.

^10And also all that generation were gathered unto their fathers: and there arose another generation after them, which knew not the Lord, nor yet the works which he had done for Israel.

^11And the children of Israel did evil in the sight of the Lord, and served Baalim:

^12And they forsook the Lord God of their fathers, which brought them out of the land of Egypt, and followed other gods, of the gods of the people that were round about them, and bowed themselves unto them, and provoked the Lord to anger.

^13And they forsook the Lord, and served Baal and Ashtaroth.

^14And the anger of the Lord was hot against Israel, and he delivered them into the hands of spoilers that spoiled them, and he sold them into the hands of their enemies round about, so that they could not any longer stand before their enemies.

^15Whithersoever they went out, the hand of the Lord was against them for evil, as the Lord had said, and as the Lord had sworn unto them: and they were greatly distressed.

^16Nevertheless the Lord raised up judges, which delivered them out of the hand of those that spoiled them.

^17And yet they would not hearken unto their judges, but they went a whoring after other gods, and bowed themselves unto them: they turned quickly out of the way which their fathers walked in, obeying the commandments of the Lord; but they did not so.

^18And when the Lord raised them up judges, then the Lord was with the judge, and delivered them out of the hand of their enemies all the days of the judge: for it repented the Lord because of their groanings by reason of them that oppressed them and vexed them.

^19And it came to pass, when the judge was dead, that they returned, and corrupted themselves more than their fathers, in following other gods to serve them, and to bow down unto them; they ceased not from their own doings, nor from their stubborn way.

^20And the anger of the Lord was hot against Israel; and he said, Because that this people hath transgressed my covenant which I commanded their fathers, and have not hearkened unto my voice;

^21I also will not henceforth drive out any from before them of the nations which Joshua left when he died:

^22That through them I may prove Israel, whether they will keep the way of the Lord to walk therein, as their fathers did keep it, or not.

^23Therefore the Lord left those nations, without driving them out hastily; neither delivered he them into the hand of Joshua.

III

3^1Now these are the nations which the Lord left, to prove Israel by them, even as many of Israel as had not known all the wars of Canaan;

^2Only that the generations of the children of Israel might know, to teach them war, at the least such as before knew nothing thereof;

^3Namely, five lords of the Philistines, and all the Canaanites, and the Sidonians, and the Hivites that dwelt in mount Lebanon, from mount Baalhermon unto the entering in of Hamath.

^4And they were to prove Israel by them, to know whether they would hearken unto the commandments of the Lord, which he commanded their fathers by the hand of Moses.

^5And the children of Israel dwelt among the Canaanites, Hittites, and Amorites, and Perizzites, and Hivites, and Jebusites:

^6And they took their daughters to be their wives, and gave their daughters to their sons, and served their gods.

^7And the children of Israel did evil in the sight of the Lord, and forgat the Lord their God, and served Baalim and the groves.

^8Therefore the anger of the Lord was hot against Israel, and he sold them into the hand of Chushanrishathaim king of Mesopotamia: and the children of Israel served Chushanrishathaim eight years.

^9And when the children of Israel cried unto the Lord, the Lord raised up a deliverer to the children of Israel, who delivered them, even Othniel the son of Kenaz, Caleb’s younger brother.

^10And the Spirit of the Lord came upon him, and he judged Israel, and went out to war: and the Lord delivered Chushanrishathaim king of Mesopotamia into his hand; and his hand prevailed against Chushanrishathaim.

^11And the land had rest forty years. And Othniel the son of Kenaz died.

^12And the children of Israel did evil again in the sight of the Lord: and the Lord strengthened Eglon the king of Moab against Israel, because they had done evil in the sight of the Lord.

^13And he gathered unto him the children of Ammon and Amalek, and went and smote Israel, and possessed the city of palm trees.

^14So the children of Israel served Eglon the king of Moab eighteen years.

^15But when the children of Israel cried unto the Lord, the Lord raised them up a deliverer, Ehud the son of Gera, a Benjamite, a man lefthanded: and by him the children of Israel sent a present unto Eglon the king of Moab.

^16But Ehud made him a dagger which had two edges, of a cubit length; and he did gird it under his raiment upon his right thigh.

^17And he brought the present unto Eglon king of Moab: and Eglon was a very fat man.

^18And when he had made an end to offer the present, he sent away the people that bare the present.

^19But he himself turned again from the quarries that were by Gilgal, and said, I have a secret errand unto thee, O king: who said, Keep silence. And all that stood by him went out from him.

^20And Ehud came unto him; and he was sitting in a summer parlour, which he had for himself alone. And Ehud said, I have a message from God unto thee. And he arose out of his seat.

^21And Ehud put forth his left hand, and took the dagger from his right thigh, and thrust it into his belly:

^22And the haft also went in after the blade; and the fat closed upon the blade, so that he could not draw the dagger out of his belly; and the dirt came out.

^23Then Ehud went forth through the porch, and shut the doors of the parlour upon him, and locked them.

^24When he was gone out, his servants came; and when they saw that, behold, the doors of the parlour were locked, they said, Surely he covereth his feet in his summer chamber.

^25And they tarried till they were ashamed: and, behold, he opened not the doors of the parlour; therefore they took a key, and opened them: and, behold, their lord was fallen down dead on the earth.

^26And Ehud escaped while they tarried, and passed beyond the quarries, and escaped unto Seirath.

^27And it came to pass, when he was come, that he blew a trumpet in the mountain of Ephraim, and the children of Israel went down with him from the mount, and he before them.

^28And he said unto them, Follow after me: for the Lord hath delivered your enemies the Moabites into your hand. And they went down after him, and took the fords of Jordan toward Moab, and suffered not a man to pass over.

^29And they slew of Moab at that time about ten thousand men, all lusty, and all men of valour; and there escaped not a man.

^30So Moab was subdued that day under the hand of Israel. And the land had rest fourscore years.

^31And after him was Shamgar the son of Anath, which slew of the Philistines six hundred men with an ox goad: and he also delivered Israel.

IV

4^1And the children of Israel again did evil in the sight of the Lord, when Ehud was dead.

^2And the Lord sold them into the hand of Jabin king of Canaan, that reigned in Hazor; the captain of whose host was Sisera, which dwelt in Harosheth of the Gentiles.

^3And the children of Israel cried unto the Lord: for he had nine hundred chariots of iron; and twenty years he mightily oppressed the children of Israel.

^4And Deborah, a prophetess, the wife of Lapidoth, she judged Israel at that time.

^5And she dwelt under the palm tree of Deborah between Ramah and Bethel in mount Ephraim: and the children of Israel came up to her for judgment.

^6And she sent and called Barak the son of Abinoam out of Kedeshnaphtali, and said unto him, Hath not the Lord God of Israel commanded, saying, Go and draw toward mount Tabor, and take with thee ten thousand men of the children of Naphtali and of the children of Zebulun?

^7And I will draw unto thee to the river Kishon Sisera, the captain of Jabin’s army, with his chariots and his multitude; and I will deliver him into thine hand.

^8And Barak said unto her, If thou wilt go with me, then I will go: but if thou wilt not go with me, then I will not go.

^9And she said, I will surely go with thee: notwithstanding the journey that thou takest shall not be for thine honour; for the Lord shall sell Sisera into the hand of a woman. And Deborah arose, and went with Barak to Kedesh.

^10And Barak called Zebulun and Naphtali to Kedesh; and he went up with ten thousand men at his feet: and Deborah went up with him.

^11Now Heber the Kenite, which was of the children of Hobab the father in law of Moses, had severed himself from the Kenites, and pitched his tent unto the plain of Zaanaim, which is by Kedesh.

^12And they shewed Sisera that Barak the son of Abinoam was gone up to mount Tabor.

^13And Sisera gathered together all his chariots, even nine hundred chariots of iron, and all the people that were with him, from Harosheth of the Gentiles unto the river of Kishon.

^14And Deborah said unto Barak, Up; for this is the day in which the Lord hath delivered Sisera into thine hand: is not the Lord gone out before thee? So Barak went down from mount Tabor, and ten thousand men after him.

^15And the Lord discomfited Sisera, and all his chariots, and all his host, with the edge of the sword before Barak; so that Sisera lighted down off his chariot, and fled away on his feet.

^16But Barak pursued after the chariots, and after the host, unto Harosheth of the Gentiles: and all the host of Sisera fell upon the edge of the sword; and there was not a man left.

^17Howbeit Sisera fled away on his feet to the tent of Jael the wife of Heber the Kenite: for there was peace between Jabin the king of Hazor and the house of Heber the Kenite.

^18And Jael went out to meet Sisera, and said unto him, Turn in, my lord, turn in to me; fear not. And when he had turned in unto her into the tent, she covered him with a mantle.

^19And he said unto her, Give me, I pray thee, a little water to drink; for I am thirsty. And she opened a bottle of milk, and gave him drink, and covered him.

^20Again he said unto her, Stand in the door of the tent, and it shall be, when any man doth come and enquire of thee, and say, Is there any man here? that thou shalt say, No.

^21Then Jael Heber’s wife took a nail of the tent, and took an hammer in her hand, and went softly unto him, and smote the nail into his temples, and fastened it into the ground: for he was fast asleep and weary. So he died.

^22And, behold, as Barak pursued Sisera, Jael came out to meet him, and said unto him, Come, and I will shew thee the man whom thou seekest. And when he came into her tent, behold, Sisera lay dead, and the nail was in his temples.

^23So God subdued on that day Jabin the king of Canaan before the children of Israel.

^24And the hand of the children of Israel prospered, and prevailed against Jabin the king of Canaan, until they had destroyed Jabin king of Canaan.

V

5^1Then sang Deborah and Barak the son of Abinoam on that day, saying,

^2Praise ye the Lord for the avenging of Israel, when the people willingly offered themselves.

^3Hear, O ye kings; give ear, O ye princes; I, even I, will sing unto the Lord; I will sing praise to the Lord God of Israel.

^4Lord, when thou wentest out of Seir, when thou marchedst out of the field of Edom, the earth trembled, and the heavens dropped, the clouds also dropped water.

^5The mountains melted from before the Lord, even that Sinai from before the Lord God of Israel.

^6In the days of Shamgar the son of Anath, in the days of Jael, the highways were unoccupied, and the travellers walked through byways.

^7The inhabitants of the villages ceased, they ceased in Israel, until that I Deborah arose, that I arose a mother in Israel.

^8They chose new gods; then was war in the gates: was there a shield or spear seen among forty thousand in Israel?

^9My heart is toward the governors of Israel, that offered themselves willingly among the people. Bless ye the Lord.

^10Speak, ye that ride on white asses, ye that sit in judgment, and walk by the way.

^11They that are delivered from the noise of archers in the places of drawing water, there shall they rehearse the righteous acts of the Lord, even the righteous acts toward the inhabitants of his villages in Israel: then shall the people of the Lord go down to the gates.

^12Awake, awake, Deborah: awake, awake, utter a song: arise, Barak, and lead thy captivity captive, thou son of Abinoam.

^13Then he made him that remaineth have dominion over the nobles among the people: the Lord made me have dominion over the mighty.

^14Out of Ephraim was there a root of them against Amalek; after thee, Benjamin, among thy people; out of Machir came down governors, and out of Zebulun they that handle the pen of the writer.

^15And the princes of Issachar were with Deborah; even Issachar, and also Barak: he was sent on foot into the valley. For the divisions of Reuben there were great thoughts of heart.

^16Why abodest thou among the sheepfolds, to hear the bleatings of the flocks? For the divisions of Reuben there were great searchings of heart.

^17Gilead abode beyond Jordan: and why did Dan remain in ships? Asher continued on the sea shore, and abode in his breaches.

^18Zebulun and Naphtali were a people that jeoparded their lives unto the death in the high places of the field.

^19The kings came and fought, then fought the kings of Canaan in Taanach by the waters of Megiddo; they took no gain of money.

^20They fought from heaven; the stars in their courses fought against Sisera.

^21The river of Kishon swept them away, that ancient river, the river Kishon. O my soul, thou hast trodden down strength.

^22Then were the horsehoofs broken by the means of the pransings, the pransings of their mighty ones.

^23Curse ye Meroz, said the angel of the Lord, curse ye bitterly the inhabitants thereof; because they came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord against the mighty.

^24Blessed above women shall Jael the wife of Heber the Kenite be, blessed shall she be above women in the tent.

^25He asked water, and she gave him milk; she brought forth butter in a lordly dish.

^26She put her hand to the nail, and her right hand to the workmen’s hammer; and with the hammer she smote Sisera, she smote off his head, when she had pierced and stricken through his temples.

^27At her feet he bowed, he fell, he lay down: at her feet he bowed, he fell: where he bowed, there he fell down dead.

^28The mother of Sisera looked out at a window, and cried through the lattice, Why is his chariot so long in coming? why tarry the wheels of his chariots?

^29Her wise ladies answered her, yea, she returned answer to herself,

^30Have they not sped? have they not divided the prey; to every man a damsel or two; to Sisera a prey of divers colours, a prey of divers colours of needlework, of divers colours of needlework on both sides, meet for the necks of them that take the spoil?

^31So let all thine enemies perish, O Lord: but let them that love him be as the sun when he goeth forth in his might. And the land had rest forty years.

VI

6^1And the children of Israel did evil in the sight of the Lord: and the Lord delivered them into the hand of Midian seven years.

^2And the hand of Midian prevailed against Israel: and because of the Midianites the children of Israel made them the dens which are in the mountains, and caves, and strong holds.

^3And so it was, when Israel had sown, that the Midianites came up, and the Amalekites, and the children of the east, even they came up against them;

^4And they encamped against them, and destroyed the increase of the earth, till thou come unto Gaza, and left no sustenance for Israel, neither sheep, nor ox, nor ass.

^5For they came up with their cattle and their tents, and they came as grasshoppers for multitude; for both they and their camels were without number: and they entered into the land to destroy it.

^6And Israel was greatly impoverished because of the Midianites; and the children of Israel cried unto the Lord.

^7And it came to pass, when the children of Israel cried unto the Lord because of the Midianites,

^8That the Lord sent a prophet unto the children of Israel, which said unto them, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, I brought you up from Egypt, and brought you forth out of the house of bondage;

^9And I delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of all that oppressed you, and drave them out from before you, and gave you their land;

^10And I said unto you, I am the Lord your God; fear not the gods of the Amorites, in whose land ye dwell: but ye have not obeyed my voice.

^11And there came an angel of the Lord, and sat under an oak which was in Ophrah, that pertained unto Joash the Abiezrite: and his son Gideon threshed wheat by the winepress, to hide it from the Midianites.

^12And the angel of the Lord appeared unto him, and said unto him, The Lord is with thee, thou mighty man of valour.

^13And Gideon said unto him, Oh my Lord, if the Lord be with us, why then is all this befallen us? and where be all his miracles which our fathers told us of, saying, Did not the Lord bring us up from Egypt? but now the Lord hath forsaken us, and delivered us into the hands of the Midianites.

^14And the Lord looked upon him, and said, Go in this thy might, and thou shalt save Israel from the hand of the Midianites: have not I sent thee?

^15And he said unto him, Oh my Lord, wherewith shall I save Israel? behold, my family is poor in Manasseh, and I am the least in my father’s house.

^16And the Lord said unto him, Surely I will be with thee, and thou shalt smite the Midianites as one man.

^17And he said unto him, If now I have found grace in thy sight, then shew me a sign that thou talkest with me.

^18Depart not hence, I pray thee, until I come unto thee, and bring forth my present, and set it before thee. And he said, I will tarry until thou come again.

^19And Gideon went in, and made ready a kid, and unleavened cakes of an ephah of flour: the flesh he put in a basket, and he put the broth in a pot, and brought it out unto him under the oak, and presented it.

^20And the angel of God said unto him, Take the flesh and the unleavened cakes, and lay them upon this rock, and pour out the broth. And he did so.

^21Then the angel of the Lord put forth the end of the staff that was in his hand, and touched the flesh and the unleavened cakes; and there rose up fire out of the rock, and consumed the flesh and the unleavened cakes. Then the angel of the Lord departed out of his sight.

^22And when Gideon perceived that he was an angel of the Lord, Gideon said, Alas, O Lord God! for because I have seen an angel of the Lord face to face.

^23And the Lord said unto him, Peace be unto thee; fear not: thou shalt not die.

^24Then Gideon built an altar there unto the Lord, and called it Jehovahshalom: unto this day it is yet in Ophrah of the Abiezrites.

^25And it came to pass the same night, that the Lord said unto him, Take thy father’s young bullock, even the second bullock of seven years old, and throw down the altar of Baal that thy father hath, and cut down the grove that is by it:

^26And build an altar unto the Lord thy God upon the top of this rock, in the ordered place, and take the second bullock, and offer a burnt sacrifice with the wood of the grove which thou shalt cut down.

^27Then Gideon took ten men of his servants, and did as the Lord had said unto him: and so it was, because he feared his father’s household, and the men of the city, that he could not do it by day, that he did it by night.

^28And when the men of the city arose early in the morning, behold, the altar of Baal was cast down, and the grove was cut down that was by it, and the second bullock was offered upon the altar that was built.

^29And they said one to another, Who hath done this thing? And when they enquired and asked, they said, Gideon the son of Joash hath done this thing.

^30Then the men of the city said unto Joash, Bring out thy son, that he may die: because he hath cast down the altar of Baal, and because he hath cut down the grove that was by it.

^31And Joash said unto all that stood against him, Will ye plead for Baal? will ye save him? he that will plead for him, let him be put to death whilst it is yet morning: if he be a god, let him plead for himself, because one hath cast down his altar.

^32Therefore on that day he called him Jerubbaal, saying, Let Baal plead against him, because he hath thrown down his altar.

^33Then all the Midianites and the Amalekites and the children of the east were gathered together, and went over, and pitched in the valley of Jezreel.

^34But the Spirit of the Lord came upon Gideon, and he blew a trumpet; and Abiezer was gathered after him.

^35And he sent messengers throughout all Manasseh; who also was gathered after him: and he sent messengers unto Asher, and unto Zebulun, and unto Naphtali; and they came up to meet them.

^36And Gideon said unto God, If thou wilt save Israel by mine hand, as thou hast said,

^37Behold, I will put a fleece of wool in the floor; and if the dew be on the fleece only, and it be dry upon all the earth beside, then shall I know that thou wilt save Israel by mine hand, as thou hast said.

^38And it was so: for he rose up early on the morrow, and thrust the fleece together, and wringed the dew out of the fleece, a bowl full of water.

^39And Gideon said unto God, Let not thine anger be hot against me, and I will speak but this once: let me prove, I pray thee, but this once with the fleece; let it now be dry only upon the fleece, and upon all the ground let there be dew.

^40And God did so that night: for it was dry upon the fleece only, and there was dew on all the ground.

VII

7^1Then Jerubbaal, who is Gideon, and all the people that were with him, rose up early, and pitched beside the well of Harod: so that the host of the Midianites were on the north side of them, by the hill of Moreh, in the valley.

^2And the Lord said unto Gideon, The people that are with thee are too many for me to give the Midianites into their hands, lest Israel vaunt themselves against me, saying, Mine own hand hath saved me.

^3Now therefore go to, proclaim in the ears of the people, saying, Whosoever is fearful and afraid, let him return and depart early from mount Gilead. And there returned of the people twenty and two thousand; and there remained ten thousand.

^4And the Lord said unto Gideon, The people are yet too many; bring them down unto the water, and I will try them for thee there: and it shall be, that of whom I say unto thee, This shall go with thee, the same shall go with thee; and of whomsoever I say unto thee, This shall not go with thee, the same shall not go.

^5So he brought down the people unto the water: and the Lord said unto Gideon, Every one that lappeth of the water with his tongue, as a dog lappeth, him shalt thou set by himself; likewise every one that boweth down upon his knees to drink.

^6And the number of them that lapped, putting their hand to their mouth, were three hundred men: but all the rest of the people bowed down upon their knees to drink water.

^7And the Lord said unto Gideon, By the three hundred men that lapped will I save you, and deliver the Midianites into thine hand: and let all the other people go every man unto his place.

^8So the people took victuals in their hand, and their trumpets: and he sent all the rest of Israel every man unto his tent, and retained those three hundred men: and the host of Midian was beneath him in the valley.

^9And it came to pass the same night, that the Lord said unto him, Arise, get thee down unto the host; for I have delivered it into thine hand.

^10But if thou fear to go down, go thou with Phurah thy servant down to the host:

^11And thou shalt hear what they say; and afterward shall thine hands be strengthened to go down unto the host. Then went he down with Phurah his servant unto the outside of the armed men that were in the host.

^12And the Midianites and the Amalekites and all the children of the east lay along in the valley like grasshoppers for multitude; and their camels were without number, as the sand by the sea side for multitude.

^13And when Gideon was come, behold, there was a man that told a dream unto his fellow, and said, Behold, I dreamed a dream, and, lo, a cake of barley bread tumbled into the host of Midian, and came unto a tent, and smote it that it fell, and overturned it, that the tent lay along.

^14And his fellow answered and said, This is nothing else save the sword of Gideon the son of Joash, a man of Israel: for into his hand hath God delivered Midian, and all the host.

^15And it was so, when Gideon heard the telling of the dream, and the interpretation thereof, that he worshipped, and returned into the host of Israel, and said, Arise; for the Lord hath delivered into your hand the host of Midian.

^16And he divided the three hundred men into three companies, and he put a trumpet in every man’s hand, with empty pitchers, and lamps within the pitchers.

^17And he said unto them, Look on me, and do likewise: and, behold, when I come to the outside of the camp, it shall be that, as I do, so shall ye do.

^18When I blow with a trumpet, I and all that are with me, then blow ye the trumpets also on every side of all the camp, and say, The sword of the Lord, and of Gideon.

^19So Gideon, and the hundred men that were with him, came unto the outside of the camp in the beginning of the middle watch; and they had but newly set the watch: and they blew the trumpets, and brake the pitchers that were in their hands.

^20And the three companies blew the trumpets, and brake the pitchers, and held the lamps in their left hands, and the trumpets in their right hands to blow withal: and they cried, The sword of the Lord, and of Gideon.

^21And they stood every man in his place round about the camp; and all the host ran, and cried, and fled.

^22And the three hundred blew the trumpets, and the Lord set every man’s sword against his fellow, even throughout all the host: and the host fled to Bethshittah in Zererath, and to the border of Abelmeholah, unto Tabbath.

^23And the men of Israel gathered themselves together out of Naphtali, and out of Asher, and out of all Manasseh, and pursued after the Midianites.

^24And Gideon sent messengers throughout all mount Ephraim, saying, come down against the Midianites, and take before them the waters unto Bethbarah and Jordan. Then all the men of Ephraim gathered themselves together, and took the waters unto Bethbarah and Jordan.

^25And they took two princes of the Midianites, Oreb and Zeeb; and they slew Oreb upon the rock Oreb, and Zeeb they slew at the winepress of Zeeb, and pursued Midian, and brought the heads of Oreb and Zeeb to Gideon on the other side Jordan.

VIII

8^1And the men of Ephraim said unto him, Why hast thou served us thus, that thou calledst us not, when thou wentest to fight with the Midianites? And they did chide with him sharply.

^2And he said unto them, What have I done now in comparison of you? Is not the gleaning of the grapes of Ephraim better than the vintage of Abiezer?

^3God hath delivered into your hands the princes of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb: and what was I able to do in comparison of you? Then their anger was abated toward him, when he had said that.

^4And Gideon came to Jordan, and passed over, he, and the three hundred men that were with him, faint, yet pursuing them.

^5And he said unto the men of Succoth, Give, I pray you, loaves of bread unto the people that follow me; for they be faint, and I am pursuing after Zebah and Zalmunna, kings of Midian.

^6And the princes of Succoth said, Are the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna now in thine hand, that we should give bread unto thine army?

^7And Gideon said, Therefore when the Lord hath delivered Zebah and Zalmunna into mine hand, then I will tear your flesh with the thorns of the wilderness and with briers.

^8And he went up thence to Penuel, and spake unto them likewise: and the men of Penuel answered him as the men of Succoth had answered him.

^9And he spake also unto the men of Penuel, saying, When I come again in peace, I will break down this tower.

^10Now Zebah and Zalmunna were in Karkor, and their hosts with them, about fifteen thousand men, all that were left of all the hosts of the children of the east: for there fell an hundred and twenty thousand men that drew sword.

^11And Gideon went up by the way of them that dwelt in tents on the east of Nobah and Jogbehah, and smote the host; for the host was secure.

^12And when Zebah and Zalmunna fled, he pursued after them, and took the two kings of Midian, Zebah and Zalmunna, and discomfited all the host.

^13And Gideon the son of Joash returned from battle before the sun was up,

^14And caught a young man of the men of Succoth, and enquired of him: and he described unto him the princes of Succoth, and the elders thereof, even threescore and seventeen men.

^15And he came unto the men of Succoth, and said, Behold Zebah and Zalmunna, with whom ye did upbraid me, saying, Are the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna now in thine hand, that we should give bread unto thy men that are weary?

^16And he took the elders of the city, and thorns of the wilderness and briers, and with them he taught the men of Succoth.

^17And he beat down the tower of Penuel, and slew the men of the city.

^18Then said he unto Zebah and Zalmunna, What manner of men were they whom ye slew at Tabor? And they answered, As thou art, so were they; each one resembled the children of a king.

^19And he said, They were my brethren, even the sons of my mother: as the Lord liveth, if ye had saved them alive, I would not slay you.

^20And he said unto Jether his firstborn, Up, and slay them. But the youth drew not his sword: for he feared, because he was yet a youth.

^21Then Zebah and Zalmunna said, Rise thou, and fall upon us: for as the man is, so is his strength. And Gideon arose, and slew Zebah and Zalmunna, and took away the ornaments that were on their camels’ necks.

^22Then the men of Israel said unto Gideon, Rule thou over us, both thou, and thy son, and thy son’s son also: for thou hast delivered us from the hand of Midian.

^23And Gideon said unto them, I will not rule over you, neither shall my son rule over you: the Lord shall rule over you.

^24And Gideon said unto them, I would desire a request of you, that ye would give me every man the earrings of his prey. (For they had golden earrings, because they were Ishmaelites.)

^25And they answered, We will willingly give them. And they spread a garment, and did cast therein every man the earrings of his prey.

^26And the weight of the golden earrings that he requested was a thousand and seven hundred shekels of gold; beside ornaments, and collars, and purple raiment that was on the kings of Midian, and beside the chains that were about their camels’ necks.

^27And Gideon made an ephod thereof, and put it in his city, even in Ophrah: and all Israel went thither a whoring after it: which thing became a snare unto Gideon, and to his house.

^28Thus was Midian subdued before the children of Israel, so that they lifted up their heads no more. And the country was in quietness forty years in the days of Gideon.

^29And Jerubbaal the son of Joash went and dwelt in his own house.

^30And Gideon had threescore and ten sons of his body begotten: for he had many wives.

^31And his concubine that was in Shechem, she also bare him a son, whose name he called Abimelech.

^32And Gideon the son of Joash died in a good old age, and was buried in the sepulchre of Joash his father, in Ophrah of the Abiezrites.

^33And it came to pass, as soon as Gideon was dead, that the children of Israel turned again, and went a whoring after Baalim, and made Baalberith their god.

^34And the children of Israel remembered not the Lord their God, who had delivered them out of the hands of all their enemies on every side:

^35Neither shewed they kindness to the house of Jerubbaal, namely, Gideon, according to all the goodness which he had shewed unto Israel.

IX

9^1And Abimelech the son of Jerubbaal went to Shechem unto his mother’s brethren, and communed with them, and with all the family of the house of his mother’s father, saying,

^2Speak, I pray you, in the ears of all the men of Shechem, Whether is better for you, either that all the sons of Jerubbaal, which are threescore and ten persons, reign over you, or that one reign over you? remember also that I am your bone and your flesh.

^3And his mother’s brethren spake of him in the ears of all the men of Shechem all these words: and their hearts inclined to follow Abimelech; for they said, He is our brother.

^4And they gave him threescore and ten pieces of silver out of the house of Baalberith, wherewith Abimelech hired vain and light persons, which followed him.

^5And he went unto his father’s house at Ophrah, and slew his brethren the sons of Jerubbaal, being threescore and ten persons, upon one stone: notwithstanding yet Jotham the youngest son of Jerubbaal was left; for he hid himself.

^6And all the men of Shechem gathered together, and all the house of Millo, and went, and made Abimelech king, by the plain of the pillar that was in Shechem.

^7And when they told it to Jotham, he went and stood in the top of mount Gerizim, and lifted up his voice, and cried, and said unto them, Hearken unto me, ye men of Shechem, that God may hearken unto you.

^8The trees went forth on a time to anoint a king over them; and they said unto the olive tree, Reign thou over us.

^9But the olive tree said unto them, Should I leave my fatness, wherewith by me they honour God and man, and go to be promoted over the trees?

^10And the trees said to the fig tree, Come thou, and reign over us.

^11But the fig tree said unto them, Should I forsake my sweetness, and my good fruit, and go to be promoted over the trees?

^12Then said the trees unto the vine, Come thou, and reign over us.

^13And the vine said unto them, Should I leave my wine, which cheereth God and man, and go to be promoted over the trees?

^14Then said all the trees unto the bramble, Come thou, and reign over us.

^15And the bramble said unto the trees, If in truth ye anoint me king over you, then come and put your trust in my shadow: and if not, let fire come out of the bramble, and devour the cedars of Lebanon.

^16Now therefore, if ye have done truly and sincerely, in that ye have made Abimelech king, and if ye have dealt well with Jerubbaal and his house, and have done unto him according to the deserving of his hands;

^17(For my father fought for you, and adventured his life far, and delivered you out of the hand of Midian:

^18And ye are risen up against my father’s house this day, and have slain his sons, threescore and ten persons, upon one stone, and have made Abimelech, the son of his maidservant, king over the men of Shechem, because he is your brother;)

^19If ye then have dealt truly and sincerely with Jerubbaal and with his house this day, then rejoice ye in Abimelech, and let him also rejoice in you:

^20But if not, let fire come out from Abimelech, and devour the men of Shechem, and the house of Millo; and let fire come out from the men of Shechem, and from the house of Millo, and devour Abimelech.

^21And Jotham ran away, and fled, and went to Beer, and dwelt there, for fear of Abimelech his brother.

^22When Abimelech had reigned three years over Israel,

^23Then God sent an evil spirit between Abimelech and the men of Shechem; and the men of Shechem dealt treacherously with Abimelech:

^24That the cruelty done to the threescore and ten sons of Jerubbaal might come, and their blood be laid upon Abimelech their brother, which slew them; and upon the men of Shechem, which aided him in the killing of his brethren.

^25And the men of Shechem set liers in wait for him in the top of the mountains, and they robbed all that came along that way by them: and it was told Abimelech.

^26And Gaal the son of Ebed came with his brethren, and went over to Shechem: and the men of Shechem put their confidence in him.

^27And they went out into the fields, and gathered their vineyards, and trode the grapes, and made merry, and went into the house of their god, and did eat and drink, and cursed Abimelech.

^28And Gaal the son of Ebed said, Who is Abimelech, and who is Shechem, that we should serve him? is not he the son of Jerubbaal? and Zebul his officer? serve the men of Hamor the father of Shechem: for why should we serve him?

^29And would to God this people were under my hand! then would I remove Abimelech. And he said to Abimelech, Increase thine army, and come out.

^30And when Zebul the ruler of the city heard the words of Gaal the son of Ebed, his anger was kindled.

^31And he sent messengers unto Abimelech privily, saying, Behold, Gaal the son of Ebed and his brethren be come to Shechem; and, behold, they fortify the city against thee.

^32Now therefore up by night, thou and the people that is with thee, and lie in wait in the field:

^33And it shall be, that in the morning, as soon as the sun is up, thou shalt rise early, and set upon the city: and, behold, when he and the people that is with him come out against thee, then mayest thou do to them as thou shalt find occasion.

^34And Abimelech rose up, and all the people that were with him, by night, and they laid wait against Shechem in four companies.

^35And Gaal the son of Ebed went out, and stood in the entering of the gate of the city: and Abimelech rose up, and the people that were with him, from lying in wait.

^36And when Gaal saw the people, he said to Zebul, Behold, there come people down from the top of the mountains. And Zebul said unto him, Thou seest the shadow of the mountains as if they were men.

^37And Gaal spake again, and said, See there come people down by the middle of the land, and another company come along by the plain of Meonenim.

^38Then said Zebul unto him, Where is now thy mouth, wherewith thou saidst, Who is Abimelech, that we should serve him? is not this the people that thou hast despised? go out, I pray now, and fight with them.

^39And Gaal went out before the men of Shechem, and fought with Abimelech.

^40And Abimelech chased him, and he fled before him, and many were overthrown and wounded, even unto the entering of the gate.

^41And Abimelech dwelt at Arumah: and Zebul thrust out Gaal and his brethren, that they should not dwell in Shechem.

^42And it came to pass on the morrow, that the people went out into the field; and they told Abimelech.

^43And he took the people, and divided them into three companies, and laid wait in the field, and looked, and, behold, the people were come forth out of the city; and he rose up against them, and smote them.

^44And Abimelech, and the company that was with him, rushed forward, and stood in the entering of the gate of the city: and the two other companies ran upon all the people that were in the fields, and slew them.

^45And Abimelech fought against the city all that day; and he took the city, and slew the people that was therein, and beat down the city, and sowed it with salt.

^46And when all the men of the tower of Shechem heard that, they entered into an hold of the house of the god Berith.

^47And it was told Abimelech, that all the men of the tower of Shechem were gathered together.

^48And Abimelech gat him up to mount Zalmon, he and all the people that were with him; and Abimelech took an axe in his hand, and cut down a bough from the trees, and took it, and laid it on his shoulder, and said unto the people that were with him, What ye have seen me do, make haste, and do as I have done.

^49And all the people likewise cut down every man his bough, and followed Abimelech, and put them to the hold, and set the hold on fire upon them; so that all the men of the tower of Shechem died also, about a thousand men and women.

^50Then went Abimelech to Thebez, and encamped against Thebez, and took it.

^51But there was a strong tower within the city, and thither fled all the men and women, and all they of the city, and shut it to them, and gat them up to the top of the tower.

^52And Abimelech came unto the tower, and fought against it, and went hard unto the door of the tower to burn it with fire.

^53And a certain woman cast a piece of a millstone upon Abimelech’s head, and all to brake his skull.

^54Then he called hastily unto the young man his armourbearer, and said unto him, Draw thy sword, and slay me, that men say not of me, A women slew him. And his young man thrust him through, and he died.

^55And when the men of Israel saw that Abimelech was dead, they departed every man unto his place.

^56Thus God rendered the wickedness of Abimelech, which he did unto his father, in slaying his seventy brethren:

^57And all the evil of the men of Shechem did God render upon their heads: and upon them came the curse of Jotham the son of Jerubbaal.

X

10^1And after Abimelech there arose to defend Israel Tola the son of Puah, the son of Dodo, a man of Issachar; and he dwelt in Shamir in mount Ephraim.

^2And he judged Israel twenty and three years, and died, and was buried in Shamir.

^3And after him arose Jair, a Gileadite, and judged Israel twenty and two years.

^4And he had thirty sons that rode on thirty ass colts, and they had thirty cities, which are called Havothjair unto this day, which are in the land of Gilead.

^5And Jair died, and was buried in Camon.

^6And the children of Israel did evil again in the sight of the Lord, and served Baalim, and Ashtaroth, and the gods of Syria, and the gods of Zidon, and the gods of Moab, and the gods of the children of Ammon, and the gods of the Philistines, and forsook the Lord, and served not him.

^7And the anger of the Lord was hot against Israel, and he sold them into the hands of the Philistines, and into the hands of the children of Ammon.

^8And that year they vexed and oppressed the children of Israel: eighteen years, all the children of Israel that were on the other side Jordan in the land of the Amorites, which is in Gilead.

^9Moreover the children of Ammon passed over Jordan to fight also against Judah, and against Benjamin, and against the house of Ephraim; so that Israel was sore distressed.

^10And the children of Israel cried unto the Lord, saying, We have sinned against thee, both because we have forsaken our God, and also served Baalim.

^11And the Lord said unto the children of Israel, Did not I deliver you from the Egyptians, and from the Amorites, from the children of Ammon, and from the Philistines?

^12The Zidonians also, and the Amalekites, and the Maonites, did oppress you; and ye cried to me, and I delivered you out of their hand.

^13Yet ye have forsaken me, and served other gods: wherefore I will deliver you no more.

^14Go and cry unto the gods which ye have chosen; let them deliver you in the time of your tribulation.

^15And the children of Israel said unto the Lord, We have sinned: do thou unto us whatsoever seemeth good unto thee; deliver us only, we pray thee, this day.

^16And they put away the strange gods from among them, and served the Lord: and his soul was grieved for the misery of Israel.

^17Then the children of Ammon were gathered together, and encamped in Gilead. And the children of Israel assembled themselves together, and encamped in Mizpeh.

^18And the people and princes of Gilead said one to another, What man is he that will begin to fight against the children of Ammon? he shall be head over all the inhabitants of Gilead.

XI

11^1Now Jephthah the Gileadite was a mighty man of valour, and he was the son of an harlot: and Gilead begat Jephthah.

^2And Gilead’s wife bare him sons; and his wife’s sons grew up, and they thrust out Jephthah, and said unto him, Thou shalt not inherit in our father’s house; for thou art the son of a strange woman.

^3Then Jephthah fled from his brethren, and dwelt in the land of Tob: and there were gathered vain men to Jephthah, and went out with him.

^4And it came to pass in process of time, that the children of Ammon made war against Israel.

^5And it was so, that when the children of Ammon made war against Israel, the elders of Gilead went to fetch Jephthah out of the land of Tob:

^6And they said unto Jephthah, Come, and be our captain, that we may fight with the children of Ammon.

^7And Jephthah said unto the elders of Gilead, Did not ye hate me, and expel me out of my father’s house? and why are ye come unto me now when ye are in distress?

^8And the elders of Gilead said unto Jephthah, Therefore we turn again to thee now, that thou mayest go with us, and fight against the children of Ammon, and be our head over all the inhabitants of Gilead.

^9And Jephthah said unto the elders of Gilead, If ye bring me home again to fight against the children of Ammon, and the Lord deliver them before me, shall I be your head?

^10And the elders of Gilead said unto Jephthah, The Lord be witness between us, if we do not so according to thy words.

^11Then Jephthah went with the elders of Gilead, and the people made him head and captain over them: and Jephthah uttered all his words before the Lord in Mizpeh.

^12And Jephthah sent messengers unto the king of the children of Ammon, saying, What hast thou to do with me, that thou art come against me to fight in my land?

^13And the king of the children of Ammon answered unto the messengers of Jephthah, Because Israel took away my land, when they came up out of Egypt, from Arnon even unto Jabbok, and unto Jordan: now therefore restore those lands again peaceably.

^14And Jephthah sent messengers again unto the king of the children of Ammon:

^15And said unto him, Thus saith Jephthah, Israel took not away the land of Moab, nor the land of the children of Ammon:

^16But when Israel came up from Egypt, and walked through the wilderness unto the Red sea, and came to Kadesh;

^17Then Israel sent messengers unto the king of Edom, saying, Let me, I pray thee, pass through thy land: but the king of Edom would not hearken thereto. And in like manner they sent unto the king of Moab: but he would not consent: and Israel abode in Kadesh.

^18Then they went along through the wilderness, and compassed the land of Edom, and the land of Moab, and came by the east side of the land of Moab, and pitched on the other side of Arnon, but came not within the border of Moab: for Arnon was the border of Moab.

^19And Israel sent messengers unto Sihon king of the Amorites, the king of Heshbon; and Israel said unto him, Let us pass, we pray thee, through thy land into my place.

^20But Sihon trusted not Israel to pass through his coast: but Sihon gathered all his people together, and pitched in Jahaz, and fought against Israel.

^21And the Lord God of Israel delivered Sihon and all his people into the hand of Israel, and they smote them: so Israel possessed all the land of the Amorites, the inhabitants of that country.

^22And they possessed all the coasts of the Amorites, from Arnon even unto Jabbok, and from the wilderness even unto Jordan.

^23So now the Lord God of Israel hath dispossessed the Amorites from before his people Israel, and shouldest thou possess it?

^24Wilt not thou possess that which Chemosh thy god giveth thee to possess? So whomsoever the Lord our God shall drive out from before us, them will we possess.

^25And now art thou any thing better than Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab? did he ever strive against Israel, or did he ever fight against them,

^26While Israel dwelt in Heshbon and her towns, and in Aroer and her towns, and in all the cities that be along by the coasts of Arnon, three hundred years? why therefore did ye not recover them within that time?

^27Wherefore I have not sinned against thee, but thou doest me wrong to war against me: the Lord the Judge be judge this day between the children of Israel and the children of Ammon.

^28Howbeit the king of the children of Ammon hearkened not unto the words of Jephthah which he sent him.

^29Then the Spirit of the Lord came upon Jephthah, and he passed over Gilead, and Manasseh, and passed over Mizpeh of Gilead, and from Mizpeh of Gilead he passed over unto the children of Ammon.

^30And Jephthah vowed a vow unto the Lord, and said, If thou shalt without fail deliver the children of Ammon into mine hands,

^31Then it shall be, that whatsoever cometh forth of the doors of my house to meet me, when I return in peace from the children of Ammon, shall surely be the Lord’s, and I will offer it up for a burnt offering.

^32So Jephthah passed over unto the children of Ammon to fight against them; and the Lord delivered them into his hands.

^33And he smote them from Aroer, even till thou come to Minnith, even twenty cities, and unto the plain of the vineyards, with a very great slaughter. Thus the children of Ammon were subdued before the children of Israel.

^34And Jephthah came to Mizpeh unto his house, and, behold, his daughter came out to meet him with timbrels and with dances: and she was his only child; beside her he had neither son nor daughter.

^35And it came to pass, when he saw her, that he rent his clothes, and said, Alas, my daughter! thou hast brought me very low, and thou art one of them that trouble me: for I have opened my mouth unto the Lord, and I cannot go back.

^36And she said unto him, My father, if thou hast opened thy mouth unto the Lord, do to me according to that which hath proceeded out of thy mouth; forasmuch as the Lord hath taken vengeance for thee of thine enemies, even of the children of Ammon.

^37And she said unto her father, Let this thing be done for me: let me alone two months, that I may go up and down upon the mountains, and bewail my virginity, I and my fellows.

^38And he said, Go. And he sent her away for two months: and she went with her companions, and bewailed her virginity upon the mountains.

^39And it came to pass at the end of two months, that she returned unto her father, who did with her according to his vow which he had vowed: and she knew no man. And it was a custom in Israel,

^40That the daughters of Israel went yearly to lament the daughter of Jephthah the Gileadite four days in a year.

XII

12^1And the men of Ephraim gathered themselves together, and went northward, and said unto Jephthah, Wherefore passedst thou over to fight against the children of Ammon, and didst not call us to go with thee? we will burn thine house upon thee with fire.

^2And Jephthah said unto them, I and my people were at great strife with the children of Ammon; and when I called you, ye delivered me not out of their hands.

^3And when I saw that ye delivered me not, I put my life in my hands, and passed over against the children of Ammon, and the Lord delivered them into my hand: wherefore then are ye come up unto me this day, to fight against me?

^4Then Jephthah gathered together all the men of Gilead, and fought with Ephraim: and the men of Gilead smote Ephraim, because they said, Ye Gileadites are fugitives of Ephraim among the Ephraimites, and among the Manassites.

^5And the Gileadites took the passages of Jordan before the Ephraimites: and it was so, that when those Ephraimites which were escaped said, Let me go over; that the men of Gilead said unto him, Art thou an Ephraimite? If he said, Nay;

^6Then said they unto him, Say now Shibboleth: and he said Sibboleth: for he could not frame to pronounce it right. Then they took him, and slew him at the passages of Jordan: and there fell at that time of the Ephraimites forty and two thousand.

^7And Jephthah judged Israel six years. Then died Jephthah the Gileadite, and was buried in one of the cities of Gilead.

^8And after him Ibzan of Bethlehem judged Israel.

^9And he had thirty sons, and thirty daughters, whom he sent abroad, and took in thirty daughters from abroad for his sons. And he judged Israel seven years.

^10Then died Ibzan, and was buried at Bethlehem.

^11And after him Elon, a Zebulonite, judged Israel; and he judged Israel ten years.

^12And Elon the Zebulonite died, and was buried in Aijalon in the country of Zebulun.

^13And after him Abdon the son of Hillel, a Pirathonite, judged Israel.

^14And he had forty sons and thirty nephews, that rode on threescore and ten ass colts: and he judged Israel eight years.

^15And Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite died, and was buried in Pirathon in the land of Ephraim, in the mount of the Amalekites.

XIII

13^1And the children of Israel did evil again in the sight of the Lord; and the Lord delivered them into the hand of the Philistines forty years.

^2And there was a certain man of Zorah, of the family of the Danites, whose name was Manoah; and his wife was barren, and bare not.

^3And the angel of the Lord appeared unto the woman, and said unto her, Behold now, thou art barren, and bearest not: but thou shalt conceive, and bear a son.

^4Now therefore beware, I pray thee, and drink not wine nor strong drink, and eat not any unclean thing:

^5For, lo, thou shalt conceive, and bear a son; and no razor shall come on his head: for the child shall be a Nazarite unto God from the womb: and he shall begin to deliver Israel out of the hand of the Philistines.

^6Then the woman came and told her husband, saying, A man of God came unto me, and his countenance was like the countenance of an angel of God, very terrible: but I asked him not whence he was, neither told he me his name:

^7But he said unto me, Behold, thou shalt conceive, and bear a son; and now drink no wine nor strong drink, neither eat any unclean thing: for the child shall be a Nazarite to God from the womb to the day of his death.

^8Then Manoah intreated the Lord, and said, O my Lord, let the man of God which thou didst send come again unto us, and teach us what we shall do unto the child that shall be born.

^9And God hearkened to the voice of Manoah; and the angel of God came again unto the woman as she sat in the field: but Manoah her husband was not with her.

^10And the woman made haste, and ran, and shewed her husband, and said unto him, Behold, the man hath appeared unto me, that came unto me the other day.

^11And Manoah arose, and went after his wife, and came to the man, and said unto him, Art thou the man that spakest unto the woman? And he said, I am.

^12And Manoah said, Now let thy words come to pass. How shall we order the child, and how shall we do unto him?

^13And the angel of the Lord said unto Manoah, Of all that I said unto the woman let her beware.

^14She may not eat of any thing that cometh of the vine, neither let her drink wine or strong drink, nor eat any unclean thing: all that I commanded her let her observe.

^15And Manoah said unto the angel of the Lord, I pray thee, let us detain thee, until we shall have made ready a kid for thee.

^16And the angel of the Lord said unto Manoah, Though thou detain me, I will not eat of thy bread: and if thou wilt offer a burnt offering, thou must offer it unto the Lord. For Manoah knew not that he was an angel of the Lord.

^17And Manoah said unto the angel of the Lord, What is thy name, that when thy sayings come to pass we may do thee honour?

^18And the angel of the Lord said unto him, Why askest thou thus after my name, seeing it is secret?

^19So Manoah took a kid with a meat offering, and offered it upon a rock unto the Lord: and the angel did wonderously; and Manoah and his wife looked on.

^20For it came to pass, when the flame went up toward heaven from off the altar, that the angel of the Lord ascended in the flame of the altar. And Manoah and his wife looked on it, and fell on their faces to the ground.

^21But the angel of the Lord did no more appear to Manoah and to his wife. Then Manoah knew that he was an angel of the Lord.

^22And Manoah said unto his wife, We shall surely die, because we have seen God.

^23But his wife said unto him, If the Lord were pleased to kill us, he would not have received a burnt offering and a meat offering at our hands, neither would he have shewed us all these things, nor would as at this time have told us such things as these.

^24And the woman bare a son, and called his name Samson: and the child grew, and the Lord blessed him.

^25And the Spirit of the Lord began to move him at times in the camp of Dan between Zorah and Eshtaol.

XIV

14^1And Samson went down to Timnath, and saw a woman in Timnath of the daughters of the Philistines.

^2And he came up, and told his father and his mother, and said, I have seen a woman in Timnath of the daughters of the Philistines: now therefore get her for me to wife.

^3Then his father and his mother said unto him, Is there never a woman among the daughters of thy brethren, or among all my people, that thou goest to take a wife of the uncircumcised Philistines? And Samson said unto his father, Get her for me; for she pleaseth me well.

^4But his father and his mother knew not that it was of the Lord, that he sought an occasion against the Philistines: for at that time the Philistines had dominion over Israel.

^5Then went Samson down, and his father and his mother, to Timnath, and came to the vineyards of Timnath: and, behold, a young lion roared against him.

^6And the Spirit of the Lord came mightily upon him, and he rent him as he would have rent a kid, and he had nothing in his hand: but he told not his father or his mother what he had done.

^7And he went down, and talked with the woman; and she pleased Samson well.

^8And after a time he returned to take her, and he turned aside to see the carcase of the lion: and, behold, there was a swarm of bees and honey in the carcase of the lion.

^9And he took thereof in his hands, and went on eating, and came to his father and mother, and he gave them, and they did eat: but he told not them that he had taken the honey out of the carcase of the lion.

^10So his father went down unto the woman: and Samson made there a feast; for so used the young men to do.

^11And it came to pass, when they saw him, that they brought thirty companions to be with him.

^12And Samson said unto them, I will now put forth a riddle unto you: if ye can certainly declare it me within the seven days of the feast, and find it out, then I will give you thirty sheets and thirty change of garments:

^13But if ye cannot declare it me, then shall ye give me thirty sheets and thirty change of garments. And they said unto him, Put forth thy riddle, that we may hear it.

^14And he said unto them, Out of the eater came forth meat, and out of the strong came forth sweetness. And they could not in three days expound the riddle.

^15And it came to pass on the seventh day, that they said unto Samson’s wife, Entice thy husband, that he may declare unto us the riddle, lest we burn thee and thy father’s house with fire: have ye called us to take that we have? is it not so?

^16And Samson’s wife wept before him, and said, Thou dost but hate me, and lovest me not: thou hast put forth a riddle unto the children of my people, and hast not told it me. And he said unto her, Behold, I have not told it my father nor my mother, and shall I tell it thee?

^17And she wept before him the seven days, while their feast lasted: and it came to pass on the seventh day, that he told her, because she lay sore upon him: and she told the riddle to the children of her people.

^18And the men of the city said unto him on the seventh day before the sun went down, What is sweeter than honey? And what is stronger than a lion? and he said unto them, If ye had not plowed with my heifer, ye had not found out my riddle.

^19And the Spirit of the Lord came upon him, and he went down to Ashkelon, and slew thirty men of them, and took their spoil, and gave change of garments unto them which expounded the riddle. And his anger was kindled, and he went up to his father’s house.

^20But Samson’s wife was given to his companion, whom he had used as his friend.

XV

15^1But it came to pass within a while after, in the time of wheat harvest, that Samson visited his wife with a kid; and he said, I will go in to my wife into the chamber. But her father would not suffer him to go in.

^2And her father said, I verily thought that thou hadst utterly hated her; therefore I gave her to thy companion: is not her younger sister fairer than she? take her, I pray thee, instead of her.

^3And Samson said concerning them, Now shall I be more blameless than the Philistines, though I do them a displeasure.

^4And Samson went and caught three hundred foxes, and took firebrands, and turned tail to tail, and put a firebrand in the midst between two tails.

^5And when he had set the brands on fire, he let them go into the standing corn of the Philistines, and burnt up both the shocks, and also the standing corn, with the vineyards and olives.

^6Then the Philistines said, Who hath done this? And they answered, Samson, the son in law of the Timnite, because he had taken his wife, and given her to his companion. And the Philistines came up, and burnt her and her father with fire.

^7And Samson said unto them, Though ye have done this, yet will I be avenged of you, and after that I will cease.

^8And he smote them hip and thigh with a great slaughter: and he went down and dwelt in the top of the rock Etam.

^9Then the Philistines went up, and pitched in Judah, and spread themselves in Lehi.

^10And the men of Judah said, Why are ye come up against us? And they answered, To bind Samson are we come up, to do to him as he hath done to us.

^11Then three thousand men of Judah went to the top of the rock Etam, and said to Samson, Knowest thou not that the Philistines are rulers over us? what is this that thou hast done unto us? And he said unto them, As they did unto me, so have I done unto them.

^12And they said unto him, We are come down to bind thee, that we may deliver thee into the hand of the Philistines. And Samson said unto them, Swear unto me, that ye will not fall upon me yourselves.

^13And they spake unto him, saying, No; but we will bind thee fast, and deliver thee into their hand: but surely we will not kill thee. And they bound him with two new cords, and brought him up from the rock.

^14And when he came unto Lehi, the Philistines shouted against him: and the Spirit of the Lord came mightily upon him, and the cords that were upon his arms became as flax that was burnt with fire, and his bands loosed from off his hands.

^15And he found a new jawbone of an ass, and put forth his hand, and took it, and slew a thousand men therewith.

^16And Samson said, With the jawbone of an ass, heaps upon heaps, with the jaw of an ass have I slain a thousand men.

^17And it came to pass, when he had made an end of speaking, that he cast away the jawbone out of his hand, and called that place Ramathlehi.

^18And he was sore athirst, and called on the Lord, and said, Thou hast given this great deliverance into the hand of thy servant: and now shall I die for thirst, and fall into the hand of the uncircumcised?

^19But God clave an hollow place that was in the jaw, and there came water thereout; and when he had drunk, his spirit came again, and he revived: wherefore he called the name thereof Enhakkore, which is in Lehi unto this day.

^20And he judged Israel in the days of the Philistines twenty years.

XVI

16^1Then went Samson to Gaza, and saw there an harlot, and went in unto her.

^2And it was told the Gazites, saying, Samson is come hither. And they compassed him in, and laid wait for him all night in the gate of the city, and were quiet all the night, saying, In the morning, when it is day, we shall kill him.

^3And Samson lay till midnight, and arose at midnight, and took the doors of the gate of the city, and the two posts, and went away with them, bar and all, and put them upon his shoulders, and carried them up to the top of an hill that is before Hebron.

^4And it came to pass afterward, that he loved a woman in the valley of Sorek, whose name was Delilah.

^5And the lords of the Philistines came up unto her, and said unto her, Entice him, and see wherein his great strength lieth, and by what means we may prevail against him, that we may bind him to afflict him; and we will give thee every one of us eleven hundred pieces of silver.

^6And Delilah said to Samson, Tell me, I pray thee, wherein thy great strength lieth, and wherewith thou mightest be bound to afflict thee.

^7And Samson said unto her, If they bind me with seven green withs that were never dried, then shall I be weak, and be as another man.

^8Then the lords of the Philistines brought up to her seven green withs which had not been dried, and she bound him with them.

^9Now there were men lying in wait, abiding with her in the chamber. And she said unto him, The Philistines be upon thee, Samson. And he brake the withs, as a thread of tow is broken when it toucheth the fire. So his strength was not known.

^10And Delilah said unto Samson, Behold, thou hast mocked me, and told me lies: now tell me, I pray thee, wherewith thou mightest be bound.

^11And he said unto her, If they bind me fast with new ropes that never were occupied, then shall I be weak, and be as another man.

^12Delilah therefore took new ropes, and bound him therewith, and said unto him, The Philistines be upon thee, Samson. And there were liers in wait abiding in the chamber. And he brake them from off his arms like a thread.

^13And Delilah said unto Samson, Hitherto thou hast mocked me, and told me lies: tell me wherewith thou mightest be bound. And he said unto her, If thou weavest the seven locks of my head with the web.

^14And she fastened it with the pin, and said unto him, The Philistines be upon thee, Samson. And he awaked out of his sleep, and went away with the pin of the beam, and with the web.

^15And she said unto him, How canst thou say, I love thee, when thine heart is not with me? thou hast mocked me these three times, and hast not told me wherein thy great strength lieth.

^16And it came to pass, when she pressed him daily with her words, and urged him, so that his soul was vexed unto death;

^17That he told her all his heart, and said unto her, There hath not come a razor upon mine head; for I have been a Nazarite unto God from my mother’s womb: if I be shaven, then my strength will go from me, and I shall become weak, and be like any other man.

^18And when Delilah saw that he had told her all his heart, she sent and called for the lords of the Philistines, saying, Come up this once, for he hath shewed me all his heart. Then the lords of the Philistines came up unto her, and brought money in their hand.

^19And she made him sleep upon her knees; and she called for a man, and she caused him to shave off the seven locks of his head; and she began to afflict him, and his strength went from him.

^20And she said, The Philistines be upon thee, Samson. And he awoke out of his sleep, and said, I will go out as at other times before, and shake myself. And he wist not that the Lord was departed from him.

^21But the Philistines took him, and put out his eyes, and brought him down to Gaza, and bound him with fetters of brass; and he did grind in the prison house.

^22Howbeit the hair of his head began to grow again after he was shaven.

^23Then the lords of the Philistines gathered them together for to offer a great sacrifice unto Dagon their god, and to rejoice: for they said, Our god hath delivered Samson our enemy into our hand.

^24And when the people saw him, they praised their god: for they said, Our god hath delivered into our hands our enemy, and the destroyer of our country, which slew many of us.

^25And it came to pass, when their hearts were merry, that they said, Call for Samson, that he may make us sport. And they called for Samson out of the prison house; and he made them sport: and they set him between the pillars.

^26And Samson said unto the lad that held him by the hand, Suffer me that I may feel the pillars whereupon the house standeth, that I may lean upon them.

^27Now the house was full of men and women; and all the lords of the Philistines were there; and there were upon the roof about three thousand men and women, that beheld while Samson made sport.

^28And Samson called unto the Lord, and said, O Lord God, remember me, I pray thee, and strengthen me, I pray thee, only this once, O God, that I may be at once avenged of the Philistines for my two eyes.

^29And Samson took hold of the two middle pillars upon which the house stood, and on which it was borne up, of the one with his right hand, and of the other with his left.

^30And Samson said, Let me die with the Philistines. And he bowed himself with all his might; and the house fell upon the lords, and upon all the people that were therein. So the dead which he slew at his death were more than they which he slew in his life.

^31Then his brethren and all the house of his father came down, and took him, and brought him up, and buried him between Zorah and Eshtaol in the buryingplace of Manoah his father. And he judged Israel twenty years.

XVII

17^1And there was a man of mount Ephraim, whose name was Micah.

^2And he said unto his mother, The eleven hundred shekels of silver that were taken from thee, about which thou cursedst, and spakest of also in mine ears, behold, the silver is with me; I took it. And his mother said, Blessed be thou of the Lord, my son.

^3And when he had restored the eleven hundred shekels of silver to his mother, his mother said, I had wholly dedicated the silver unto the Lord from my hand for my son, to make a graven image and a molten image: now therefore I will restore it unto thee.

^4Yet he restored the money unto his mother; and his mother took two hundred shekels of silver, and gave them to the founder, who made thereof a graven image and a molten image: and they were in the house of Micah.

^5And the man Micah had an house of gods, and made an ephod, and teraphim, and consecrated one of his sons, who became his priest.

^6In those days there was no king in Israel, but every man did that which was right in his own eyes.

^7And there was a young man out of Bethlehemjudah of the family of Judah, who was a Levite, and he sojourned there.

^8And the man departed out of the city from Bethlehemjudah to sojourn where he could find a place: and he came to mount Ephraim to the house of Micah, as he journeyed.

^9And Micah said unto him, Whence comest thou? And he said unto him, I am a Levite of Bethlehemjudah, and I go to sojourn where I may find a place.

^10And Micah said unto him, Dwell with me, and be unto me a father and a priest, and I will give thee ten shekels of silver by the year, and a suit of apparel, and thy victuals. So the Levite went in.

^11And the Levite was content to dwell with the man; and the young man was unto him as one of his sons.

^12And Micah consecrated the Levite; and the young man became his priest, and was in the house of Micah.

^13Then said Micah, Now know I that the Lord will do me good, seeing I have a Levite to my priest.

XVIII

18^1In those days there was no king in Israel: and in those days the tribe of the Danites sought them an inheritance to dwell in; for unto that day all their inheritance had not fallen unto them among the tribes of Israel.

^2And the children of Dan sent of their family five men from their coasts, men of valour, from Zorah, and from Eshtaol, to spy out the land, and to search it; and they said unto them, Go, search the land: who when they came to mount Ephraim, to the house of Micah, they lodged there.

^3When they were by the house of Micah, they knew the voice of the young man the Levite: and they turned in thither, and said unto him, Who brought thee hither? and what makest thou in this place? and what hast thou here?

^4And he said unto them, Thus and thus dealeth Micah with me, and hath hired me, and I am his priest.

^5And they said unto him, Ask counsel, we pray thee, of God, that we may know whether our way which we go shall be prosperous.

^6And the priest said unto them, Go in peace: before the Lord is your way wherein ye go.

^7Then the five men departed, and came to Laish, and saw the people that were therein, how they dwelt careless, after the manner of the Zidonians, quiet and secure; and there was no magistrate in the land, that might put them to shame in any thing; and they were far from the Zidonians, and had no business with any man.

^8And they came unto their brethren to Zorah and Eshtaol: and their brethren said unto them, What say ye?

^9And they said, Arise, that we may go up against them: for we have seen the land, and, behold, it is very good: and are ye still? be not slothful to go, and to enter to possess the land.

^10When ye go, ye shall come unto a people secure, and to a large land: for God hath given it into your hands; a place where there is no want of any thing that is in the earth.

^11And there went from thence of the family of the Danites, out of Zorah and out of Eshtaol, six hundred men appointed with weapons of war.

^12And they went up, and pitched in Kirjathjearim, in Judah: wherefore they called that place Mahanehdan unto this day: behold, it is behind Kirjathjearim.

^13And they passed thence unto mount Ephraim, and came unto the house of Micah.

^14Then answered the five men that went to spy out the country of Laish, and said unto their brethren, Do ye know that there is in these houses an ephod, and teraphim, and a graven image, and a molten image? now therefore consider what ye have to do.

^15And they turned thitherward, and came to the house of the young man the Levite, even unto the house of Micah, and saluted him.

^16And the six hundred men appointed with their weapons of war, which were of the children of Dan, stood by the entering of the gate.

^17And the five men that went to spy out the land went up, and came in thither, and took the graven image, and the ephod, and the teraphim, and the molten image: and the priest stood in the entering of the gate with the six hundred men that were appointed with weapons of war.

^18And these went into Micah’s house, and fetched the carved image, the ephod, and the teraphim, and the molten image. Then said the priest unto them, What do ye?

^19And they said unto him, Hold thy peace, lay thine hand upon thy mouth, and go with us, and be to us a father and a priest: is it better for thee to be a priest unto the house of one man, or that thou be a priest unto a tribe and a family in Israel?

^20And the priest’s heart was glad, and he took the ephod, and the teraphim, and the graven image, and went in the midst of the people.

^21So they turned and departed, and put the little ones and the cattle and the carriage before them.

^22And when they were a good way from the house of Micah, the men that were in the houses near to Micah’s house were gathered together, and overtook the children of Dan.

^23And they cried unto the children of Dan. And they turned their faces, and said unto Micah, What aileth thee, that thou comest with such a company?

^24And he said, Ye have taken away my gods which I made, and the priest, and ye are gone away: and what have I more? and what is this that ye say unto me, What aileth thee?

^25And the children of Dan said unto him, Let not thy voice be heard among us, lest angry fellows run upon thee, and thou lose thy life, with the lives of thy household.

^26And the children of Dan went their way: and when Micah saw that they were too strong for him, he turned and went back unto his house.

^27And they took the things which Micah had made, and the priest which he had, and came unto Laish, unto a people that were at quiet and secure: and they smote them with the edge of the sword, and burnt the city with fire.

^28And there was no deliverer, because it was far from Zidon, and they had no business with any man; and it was in the valley that lieth by Bethrehob. And they built a city, and dwelt therein.

^29And they called the name of the city Dan, after the name of Dan their father, who was born unto Israel: howbeit the name of the city was Laish at the first.

^30And the children of Dan set up the graven image: and Jonathan, the son of Gershom, the son of Manasseh, he and his sons were priests to the tribe of Dan until the day of the captivity of the land.

^31And they set them up Micah’s graven image, which he made, all the time that the house of God was in Shiloh.

XIX

19^1And it came to pass in those days, when there was no king in Israel, that there was a certain Levite sojourning on the side of mount Ephraim, who took to him a concubine out of Bethlehemjudah.

^2And his concubine played the whore against him, and went away from him unto her father’s house to Bethlehemjudah, and was there four whole months.

^3And her husband arose, and went after her, to speak friendly unto her, and to bring her again, having his servant with him, and a couple of asses: and she brought him into her father’s house: and when the father of the damsel saw him, he rejoiced to meet him.

^4And his father in law, the damsel’s father, retained him; and he abode with him three days: so they did eat and drink, and lodged there.

^5And it came to pass on the fourth day, when they arose early in the morning, that he rose up to depart: and the damsel’s father said unto his son in law, Comfort thine heart with a morsel of bread, and afterward go your way.

^6And they sat down, and did eat and drink both of them together: for the damsel’s father had said unto the man, Be content, I pray thee, and tarry all night, and let thine heart be merry.

^7And when the man rose up to depart, his father in law urged him: therefore he lodged there again.

^8And he arose early in the morning on the fifth day to depart; and the damsel’s father said, Comfort thine heart, I pray thee. And they tarried until afternoon, and they did eat both of them.

^9And when the man rose up to depart, he, and his concubine, and his servant, his father in law, the damsel’s father, said unto him, Behold, now the day draweth toward evening, I pray you tarry all night: behold, the day groweth to an end, lodge here, that thine heart may be merry; and to morrow get you early on your way, that thou mayest go home.

^10But the man would not tarry that night, but he rose up and departed, and came over against Jebus, which is Jerusalem; and there were with him two asses saddled, his concubine also was with him.

^11And when they were by Jebus, the day was far spent; and the servant said unto his master, Come, I pray thee, and let us turn in into this city of the Jebusites, and lodge in it.

^12And his master said unto him, We will not turn aside hither into the city of a stranger, that is not of the children of Israel; we will pass over to Gibeah.

^13And he said unto his servant, Come, and let us draw near to one of these places to lodge all night, in Gibeah, or in Ramah.

^14And they passed on and went their way; and the sun went down upon them when they were by Gibeah, which belongeth to Benjamin.

^15And they turned aside thither, to go in and to lodge in Gibeah: and when he went in, he sat him down in a street of the city: for there was no man that took them into his house to lodging.

^16And, behold, there came an old man from his work out of the field at even, which was also of mount Ephraim; and he sojourned in Gibeah: but the men of the place were Benjamites.

^17And when he had lifted up his eyes, he saw a wayfaring man in the street of the city: and the old man said, Whither goest thou? and whence comest thou?

^18And he said unto him, We are passing from Bethlehemjudah toward the side of mount Ephraim; from thence am I: and I went to Bethlehemjudah, but I am now going to the house of the Lord; and there is no man that receiveth me to house.

^19Yet there is both straw and provender for our asses; and there is bread and wine also for me, and for thy handmaid, and for the young man which is with thy servants: there is no want of any thing.

^20And the old man said, Peace be with thee; howsoever let all thy wants lie upon me; only lodge not in the street.

^21So he brought him into his house, and gave provender unto the asses: and they washed their feet, and did eat and drink.

^22Now as they were making their hearts merry, behold, the men of the city, certain sons of Belial, beset the house round about, and beat at the door, and spake to the master of the house, the old man, saying, Bring forth the man that came into thine house, that we may know him.

^23And the man, the master of the house, went out unto them, and said unto them, Nay, my brethren, nay, I pray you, do not so wickedly; seeing that this man is come into mine house, do not this folly.

^24Behold, here is my daughter a maiden, and his concubine; them I will bring out now, and humble ye them, and do with them what seemeth good unto you: but unto this man do not so vile a thing.

^25But the men would not hearken to him: so the man took his concubine, and brought her forth unto them; and they knew her, and abused her all the night until the morning: and when the day began to spring, they let her go.

^26Then came the woman in the dawning of the day, and fell down at the door of the man’s house where her lord was, till it was light.

^27And her lord rose up in the morning, and opened the doors of the house, and went out to go his way: and, behold, the woman his concubine was fallen down at the door of the house, and her hands were upon the threshold.

^28And he said unto her, Up, and let us be going. But none answered. Then the man took her up upon an ass, and the man rose up, and gat him unto his place.

^29And when he was come into his house, he took a knife, and laid hold on his concubine, and divided her, together with her bones, into twelve pieces, and sent her into all the coasts of Israel.

^30And it was so, that all that saw it said, There was no such deed done nor seen from the day that the children of Israel came up out of the land of Egypt unto this day: consider of it, take advice, and speak your minds.

XX

20^1Then all the children of Israel went out, and the congregation was gathered together as one man, from Dan even to Beersheba, with the land of Gilead, unto the Lord in Mizpeh.

^2And the chief of all the people, even of all the tribes of Israel, presented themselves in the assembly of the people of God, four hundred thousand footmen that drew sword.

^3(Now the children of Benjamin heard that the children of Israel were gone up to Mizpeh.) Then said the children of Israel, Tell us, how was this wickedness?

^4And the Levite, the husband of the woman that was slain, answered and said, I came into Gibeah that belongeth to Benjamin, I and my concubine, to lodge.

^5And the men of Gibeah rose against me, and beset the house round about upon me by night, and thought to have slain me: and my concubine have they forced, that she is dead.

^6And I took my concubine, and cut her in pieces, and sent her throughout all the country of the inheritance of Israel: for they have committed lewdness and folly in Israel.

^7Behold, ye are all children of Israel; give here your advice and counsel.

^8And all the people arose as one man, saying, We will not any of us go to his tent, neither will we any of us turn into his house.

^9But now this shall be the thing which we will do to Gibeah; we will go up by lot against it;

^10And we will take ten men of an hundred throughout all the tribes of Israel, and an hundred of a thousand, and a thousand out of ten thousand, to fetch victual for the people, that they may do, when they come to Gibeah of Benjamin, according to all the folly that they have wrought in Israel.

^11So all the men of Israel were gathered against the city, knit together as one man.

^12And the tribes of Israel sent men through all the tribe of Benjamin, saying, What wickedness is this that is done among you?

^13Now therefore deliver us the men, the children of Belial, which are in Gibeah, that we may put them to death, and put away evil from Israel. But the children of Benjamin would not hearken to the voice of their brethren the children of Israel.

^14But the children of Benjamin gathered themselves together out of the cities unto Gibeah, to go out to battle against the children of Israel.

^15And the children of Benjamin were numbered at that time out of the cities twenty and six thousand men that drew sword, beside the inhabitants of Gibeah, which were numbered seven hundred chosen men.

^16Among all this people there were seven hundred chosen men lefthanded; every one could sling stones at an hair breadth, and not miss.

^17And the men of Israel, beside Benjamin, were numbered four hundred thousand men that drew sword: all these were men of war.

^18And the children of Israel arose, and went up to the house of God, and asked counsel of God, and said, Which of us shall go up first to the battle against the children of Benjamin? And the Lord said, Judah shall go up first.

^19And the children of Israel rose up in the morning, and encamped against Gibeah.

^20And the men of Israel went out to battle against Benjamin; and the men of Israel put themselves in array to fight against them at Gibeah.

^21And the children of Benjamin came forth out of Gibeah, and destroyed down to the ground of the Israelites that day twenty and two thousand men.

^22And the people the men of Israel encouraged themselves, and set their battle again in array in the place where they put themselves in array the first day.

^23(And the children of Israel went up and wept before the Lord until even, and asked counsel of the Lord, saying, Shall I go up again to battle against the children of Benjamin my brother? And the Lord said, Go up against him.)

^24And the children of Israel came near against the children of Benjamin the second day.

^25And Benjamin went forth against them out of Gibeah the second day, and destroyed down to the ground of the children of Israel again eighteen thousand men; all these drew the sword.

^26Then all the children of Israel, and all the people, went up, and came unto the house of God, and wept, and sat there before the Lord, and fasted that day until even, and offered burnt offerings and peace offerings before the Lord.

^27And the children of Israel enquired of the Lord, (for the ark of the covenant of God was there in those days,

^28And Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron, stood before it in those days,) saying, Shall I yet again go out to battle against the children of Benjamin my brother, or shall I cease? And the Lord said, Go up; for to morrow I will deliver them into thine hand.

^29And Israel set liers in wait round about Gibeah.

^30And the children of Israel went up against the children of Benjamin on the third day, and put themselves in array against Gibeah, as at other times.

^31And the children of Benjamin went out against the people, and were drawn away from the city; and they began to smite of the people, and kill, as at other times, in the highways, of which one goeth up to the house of God, and the other to Gibeah in the field, about thirty men of Israel.

^32And the children of Benjamin said, They are smitten down before us, as at the first. But the children of Israel said, Let us flee, and draw them from the city unto the highways.

^33And all the men of Israel rose up out of their place, and put themselves in array at Baaltamar: and the liers in wait of Israel came forth out of their places, even out of the meadows of Gibeah.

^34And there came against Gibeah ten thousand chosen men out of all Israel, and the battle was sore: but they knew not that evil was near them.

^35And the Lord smote Benjamin before Israel: and the children of Israel destroyed of the Benjamites that day twenty and five thousand and an hundred men: all these drew the sword.

^36So the children of Benjamin saw that they were smitten: for the men of Israel gave place to the Benjamites, because they trusted unto the liers in wait which they had set beside Gibeah.

^37And the liers in wait hasted, and rushed upon Gibeah; and the liers in wait drew themselves along, and smote all the city with the edge of the sword.

^38Now there was an appointed sign between the men of Israel and the liers in wait, that they should make a great flame with smoke rise up out of the city.

^39And when the men of Israel retired in the battle, Benjamin began to smite and kill of the men of Israel about thirty persons: for they said, Surely they are smitten down before us, as in the first battle.

^40But when the flame began to arise up out of the city with a pillar of smoke, the Benjamites looked behind them, and, behold, the flame of the city ascended up to heaven.

^41And when the men of Israel turned again, the men of Benjamin were amazed: for they saw that evil was come upon them.

^42Therefore they turned their backs before the men of Israel unto the way of the wilderness; but the battle overtook them; and them which came out of the cities they destroyed in the midst of them.

^43Thus they inclosed the Benjamites round about, and chased them, and trode them down with ease over against Gibeah toward the sunrising.

^44And there fell of Benjamin eighteen thousand men; all these were men of valour.

^45And they turned and fled toward the wilderness unto the rock of Rimmon: and they gleaned of them in the highways five thousand men; and pursued hard after them unto Gidom, and slew two thousand men of them.

^46So that all which fell that day of Benjamin were twenty and five thousand men that drew the sword; all these were men of valour.

^47But six hundred men turned and fled to the wilderness unto the rock Rimmon, and abode in the rock Rimmon four months.

^48And the men of Israel turned again upon the children of Benjamin, and smote them with the edge of the sword, as well the men of every city, as the beast, and all that came to hand: also they set on fire all the cities that they came to.

XXI

21^1Now the men of Israel had sworn in Mizpeh, saying, There shall not any of us give his daughter unto Benjamin to wife.

^2And the people came to the house of God, and abode there till even before God, and lifted up their voices, and wept sore;

^3And said, O Lord God of Israel, why is this come to pass in Israel, that there should be to day one tribe lacking in Israel?

^4And it came to pass on the morrow, that the people rose early, and built there an altar, and offered burnt offerings and peace offerings.

^5And the children of Israel said, Who is there among all the tribes of Israel that came not up with the congregation unto the Lord? For they had made a great oath concerning him that came not up to the Lord to Mizpeh, saying, He shall surely be put to death.

^6And the children of Israel repented them for Benjamin their brother, and said, There is one tribe cut off from Israel this day.

^7How shall we do for wives for them that remain, seeing we have sworn by the Lord that we will not give them of our daughters to wives?

^8And they said, What one is there of the tribes of Israel that came not up to Mizpeh to the Lord? And, behold, there came none to the camp from Jabeshgilead to the assembly.

^9For the people were numbered, and, behold, there were none of the inhabitants of Jabeshgilead there.

^10And the congregation sent thither twelve thousand men of the valiantest, and commanded them, saying, Go and smite the inhabitants of Jabeshgilead with the edge of the sword, with the women and the children.

^11And this is the thing that ye shall do, Ye shall utterly destroy every male, and every woman that hath lain by man.

^12And they found among the inhabitants of Jabeshgilead four hundred young virgins, that had known no man by lying with any male: and they brought them unto the camp to Shiloh, which is in the land of Canaan.

^13And the whole congregation sent some to speak to the children of Benjamin that were in the rock Rimmon, and to call peaceably unto them.

^14And Benjamin came again at that time; and they gave them wives which they had saved alive of the women of Jabeshgilead: and yet so they sufficed them not.

^15And the people repented them for Benjamin, because that the Lord had made a breach in the tribes of Israel.

^16Then the elders of the congregation said, How shall we do for wives for them that remain, seeing the women are destroyed out of Benjamin?

^17And they said, There must be an inheritance for them that be escaped of Benjamin, that a tribe be not destroyed out of Israel.

^18Howbeit we may not give them wives of our daughters: for the children of Israel have sworn, saying, Cursed be he that giveth a wife to Benjamin.

^19Then they said, Behold, there is a feast of the Lord in Shiloh yearly in a place which is on the north side of Bethel, on the east side of the highway that goeth up from Bethel to Shechem, and on the south of Lebonah.

^20Therefore they commanded the children of Benjamin, saying, Go and lie in wait in the vineyards;

^21And see, and, behold, if the daughters of Shiloh come out to dance in dances, then come ye out of the vineyards, and catch you every man his wife of the daughters of Shiloh, and go to the land of Benjamin.

^22And it shall be, when their fathers or their brethren come unto us to complain, that we will say unto them, Be favourable unto them for our sakes: because we reserved not to each man his wife in the war: for ye did not give unto them at this time, that ye should be guilty.

^23And the children of Benjamin did so, and took them wives, according to their number, of them that danced, whom they caught: and they went and returned unto their inheritance, and repaired the cities, and dwelt in them.

^24And the children of Israel departed thence at that time, every man to his tribe and to his family, and they went out from thence every man to his inheritance.

^25In those days there was no king in Israel: every man did that which was right in his own eyes.

Ruth 1

1^1Now it came to pass in the days when the judges ruled, that there was a famine in the land. And a certain man of Bethlehemjudah went to sojourn in the country of Moab, he, and his wife, and his two sons.

^2And the name of the man was Elimelech, and the name of his wife Naomi, and the name of his two sons Mahlon and Chilion, Ephrathites of Bethlehemjudah. And they came into the country of Moab, and continued there.

^3And Elimelech Naomi’s husband died; and she was left, and her two sons.

^4And they took them wives of the women of Moab; the name of the one was Orpah, and the name of the other Ruth: and they dwelled there about ten years.

^5And Mahlon and Chilion died also both of them; and the woman was left of her two sons and her husband.

^6Then she arose with her daughters in law, that she might return from the country of Moab: for she had heard in the country of Moab how that the Lord had visited his people in giving them bread.

^7Wherefore she went forth out of the place where she was, and her two daughters in law with her; and they went on the way to return unto the land of Judah.

^8And Naomi said unto her two daughters in law, Go, return each to her mother’s house: the Lord deal kindly with you, as ye have dealt with the dead, and with me.

^9The Lord grant you that ye may find rest, each of you in the house of her husband. Then she kissed them; and they lifted up their voice, and wept.

^10And they said unto her, Surely we will return with thee unto thy people.

^11And Naomi said, Turn again, my daughters: why will ye go with me? are there yet any more sons in my womb, that they may be your husbands?

^12Turn again, my daughters, go your way; for I am too old to have an husband. If I should say, I have hope, if I should have an husband also to night, and should also bear sons;

^13Would ye tarry for them till they were grown? would ye stay for them from having husbands? nay, my daughters; for it grieveth me much for your sakes that the hand of the Lord is gone out against me.

^14And they lifted up their voice, and wept again: and Orpah kissed her mother in law; but Ruth clave unto her.

^15And she said, Behold, thy sister in law is gone back unto her people, and unto her gods: return thou after thy sister in law.

^16And Ruth said, Intreat me not to leave thee, or to return from following after thee: for whither thou goest, I will go; and where thou lodgest, I will lodge: thy people shall be my people, and thy God my God:

^17Where thou diest, will I die, and there will I be buried: the Lord do so to me, and more also, if ought but death part thee and me.

^18When she saw that she was stedfastly minded to go with her, then she left speaking unto her.

^19So they two went until they came to Bethlehem. And it came to pass, when they were come to Bethlehem, that all the city was moved about them, and they said, Is this Naomi?

^20And she said unto them, Call me not Naomi, call me Mara: for the Almighty hath dealt very bitterly with me.

^21I went out full and the Lord hath brought me home again empty: why then call ye me Naomi, seeing the Lord hath testified against me, and the Almighty hath afflicted me?

^22So Naomi returned, and Ruth the Moabitess, her daughter in law, with her, which returned out of the country of Moab: and they came to Bethlehem in the beginning of barley harvest.

Ruth 2

2^1And Naomi had a kinsman of her husband’s, a mighty man of wealth, of the family of Elimelech; and his name was Boaz.

^2And Ruth the Moabitess said unto Naomi, Let me now go to the field, and glean ears of corn after him in whose sight I shall find grace. And she said unto her, Go, my daughter.

^3And she went, and came, and gleaned in the field after the reapers: and her hap was to light on a part of the field belonging unto Boaz, who was of the kindred of Elimelech.

^4And, behold, Boaz came from Bethlehem, and said unto the reapers, The Lord be with you. And they answered him, The Lord bless thee.

^5Then said Boaz unto his servant that was set over the reapers, Whose damsel is this?

^6And the servant that was set over the reapers answered and said, It is the Moabitish damsel that came back with Naomi out of the country of Moab:

^7And she said, I pray you, let me glean and gather after the reapers among the sheaves: so she came, and hath continued even from the morning until now, that she tarried a little in the house.

^8Then said Boaz unto Ruth, Hearest thou not, my daughter? Go not to glean in another field, neither go from hence, but abide here fast by my maidens:

^9Let thine eyes be on the field that they do reap, and go thou after them: have I not charged the young men that they shall not touch thee? and when thou art athirst, go unto the vessels, and drink of that which the young men have drawn.

^10Then she fell on her face, and bowed herself to the ground, and said unto him, Why have I found grace in thine eyes, that thou shouldest take knowledge of me, seeing I am a stranger?

^11And Boaz answered and said unto her, It hath fully been shewed me, all that thou hast done unto thy mother in law since the death of thine husband: and how thou hast left thy father and thy mother, and the land of thy nativity, and art come unto a people which thou knewest not heretofore.

^12The Lord recompense thy work, and a full reward be given thee of the Lord God of Israel, under whose wings thou art come to trust.

^13Then she said, Let me find favour in thy sight, my lord; for that thou hast comforted me, and for that thou hast spoken friendly unto thine handmaid, though I be not like unto one of thine handmaidens.

^14And Boaz said unto her, At mealtime come thou hither, and eat of the bread, and dip thy morsel in the vinegar. And she sat beside the reapers: and he reached her parched corn, and she did eat, and was sufficed, and left.

^15And when she was risen up to glean, Boaz commanded his young men, saying, Let her glean even among the sheaves, and reproach her not:

^16And let fall also some of the handfuls of purpose for her, and leave them, that she may glean them, and rebuke her not.

^17So she gleaned in the field until even, and beat out that she had gleaned: and it was about an ephah of barley.

^18And she took it up, and went into the city: and her mother in law saw what she had gleaned: and she brought forth, and gave to her that she had reserved after she was sufficed.

^19And her mother in law said unto her, Where hast thou gleaned to day? and where wroughtest thou? blessed be he that did take knowledge of thee. And she shewed her mother in law with whom she had wrought, and said, The man’s name with whom I wrought to day is Boaz.

^20And Naomi said unto her daughter in law, Blessed be he of the Lord, who hath not left off his kindness to the living and to the dead. And Naomi said unto her, The man is near of kin unto us, one of our next kinsmen.

^21And Ruth the Moabitess said, He said unto me also, Thou shalt keep fast by my young men, until they have ended all my harvest.

^22And Naomi said unto Ruth her daughter in law, It is good, my daughter, that thou go out with his maidens, that they meet thee not in any other field.

^23So she kept fast by the maidens of Boaz to glean unto the end of barley harvest and of wheat harvest; and dwelt with her mother in law.

Ruth 3

3^1Then Naomi her mother in law said unto her, My daughter, shall I not seek rest for thee, that it may be well with thee?

^2And now is not Boaz of our kindred, with whose maidens thou wast? Behold, he winnoweth barley to night in the threshingfloor.

^3Wash thyself therefore, and anoint thee, and put thy raiment upon thee, and get thee down to the floor: but make not thyself known unto the man, until he shall have done eating and drinking.

^4And it shall be, when he lieth down, that thou shalt mark the place where he shall lie, and thou shalt go in, and uncover his feet, and lay thee down; and he will tell thee what thou shalt do.

^5And she said unto her, All that thou sayest unto me I will do.

^6And she went down unto the floor, and did according to all that her mother in law bade her.

^7And when Boaz had eaten and drunk, and his heart was merry, he went to lie down at the end of the heap of corn: and she came softly, and uncovered his feet, and laid her down.

^8And it came to pass at midnight, that the man was afraid, and turned himself: and, behold, a woman lay at his feet.

^9And he said, Who art thou? And she answered, I am Ruth thine handmaid: spread therefore thy skirt over thine handmaid; for thou art a near kinsman.

^10And he said, Blessed be thou of the Lord, my daughter: for thou hast shewed more kindness in the latter end than at the beginning, inasmuch as thou followedst not young men, whether poor or rich.

^11And now, my daughter, fear not; I will do to thee all that thou requirest: for all the city of my people doth know that thou art a virtuous woman.

^12And now it is true that I am thy near kinsman: howbeit there is a kinsman nearer than I.

^13Tarry this night, and it shall be in the morning, that if he will perform unto thee the part of a kinsman, well; let him do the kinsman’s part: but if he will not do the part of a kinsman to thee, then will I do the part of a kinsman to thee, as the Lord liveth: lie down until the morning.

^14And she lay at his feet until the morning: and she rose up before one could know another. And he said, Let it not be known that a woman came into the floor.

^15Also he said, Bring the vail that thou hast upon thee, and hold it. And when she held it, he measured six measures of barley, and laid it on her: and she went into the city.

^16And when she came to her mother in law, she said, Who art thou, my daughter? And she told her all that the man had done to her.

^17And she said, These six measures of barley gave he me; for he said to me, Go not empty unto thy mother in law.

^18Then said she, Sit still, my daughter, until thou know how the matter will fall: for the man will not be in rest, until he have finished the thing this day.

Ruth 4

4^1Then went Boaz up to the gate, and sat him down there: and, behold, the kinsman of whom Boaz spake came by; unto whom he said, Ho, such a one! turn aside, sit down here. And he turned aside, and sat down.

^2And he took ten men of the elders of the city, and said, Sit ye down here. And they sat down.

^3And he said unto the kinsman, Naomi, that is come again out of the country of Moab, selleth a parcel of land, which was our brother Elimelech’s:

^4And I thought to advertise thee, saying, Buy it before the inhabitants, and before the elders of my people. If thou wilt redeem it, redeem it: but if thou wilt not redeem it, then tell me, that I may know: for there is none to redeem it beside thee; and I am after thee. And he said, I will redeem it.

^5Then said Boaz, What day thou buyest the field of the hand of Naomi, thou must buy it also of Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of the dead, to raise up the name of the dead upon his inheritance.

^6And the kinsman said, I cannot redeem it for myself, lest I mar mine own inheritance: redeem thou my right to thyself; for I cannot redeem it.

^7Now this was the manner in former time in Israel concerning redeeming and concerning changing, for to confirm all things; a man plucked off his shoe, and gave it to his neighbour: and this was a testimony in Israel.

^8Therefore the kinsman said unto Boaz, Buy it for thee. So he drew off his shoe.

^9And Boaz said unto the elders, and unto all the people, Ye are witnesses this day, that I have bought all that was Elimelech’s, and all that was Chilion’s and Mahlon’s, of the hand of Naomi.

^10Moreover Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of Mahlon, have I purchased to be my wife, to raise up the name of the dead upon his inheritance, that the name of the dead be not cut off from among his brethren, and from the gate of his place: ye are witnesses this day.

^11And all the people that were in the gate, and the elders, said, We are witnesses. The Lord make the woman that is come into thine house like Rachel and like Leah, which two did build the house of Israel: and do thou worthily in Ephratah, and be famous in Bethlehem:

^12And let thy house be like the house of Pharez, whom Tamar bare unto Judah, of the seed which the Lord shall give thee of this young woman.

^13So Boaz took Ruth, and she was his wife: and when he went in unto her, the Lord gave her conception, and she bare a son.

^14And the women said unto Naomi, Blessed be the Lord, which hath not left thee this day without a kinsman, that his name may be famous in Israel.

^15And he shall be unto thee a restorer of thy life, and a nourisher of thine old age: for thy daughter in law, which loveth thee, which is better to thee than seven sons, hath born him.

^16And Naomi took the child, and laid it in her bosom, and became nurse unto it.

^17And the women her neighbours gave it a name, saying, There is a son born to Naomi; and they called his name Obed: he is the father of Jesse, the father of David.

^18Now these are the generations of Pharez: Pharez begat Hezron,

^19And Hezron begat Ram, and Ram begat Amminadab,

^20And Amminadab begat Nahshon, and Nahshon begat Salmon,

^21And Salmon begat Boaz, and Boaz begat Obed,

^22And Obed begat Jesse, and Jesse begat David.

I Chronicles

The First Book of

Chronicles

I

1^1Adam, Sheth, Enosh,

^2Kenan, Mahalaleel, Jered,

^3Henoch, Methuselah, Lamech,

^4Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.

^5The sons of Japheth; Gomer, and Magog, and Madai, and Javan, and Tubal, and Meshech, and Tiras.

^6And the sons of Gomer; Ashchenaz, and Riphath, and Togarmah.

^7And the sons of Javan; Elishah, and Tarshish, Kittim, and Dodanim.

^8The sons of Ham; Cush, and Mizraim, Put, and Canaan.

^9And the sons of Cush; Seba, and Havilah, and Sabta, and Raamah, and Sabtecha. And the sons of Raamah; Sheba, and Dedan.

^10And Cush begat Nimrod: he began to be mighty upon the earth.

^11And Mizraim begat Ludim, and Anamim, and Lehabim, and Naphtuhim,

^12And Pathrusim, and Casluhim, (of whom came the Philistines,) and Caphthorim.

^13And Canaan begat Zidon his firstborn, and Heth,

^14The Jebusite also, and the Amorite, and the Girgashite,

^15And the Hivite, and the Arkite, and the Sinite,

^16And the Arvadite, and the Zemarite, and the Hamathite.

^17The sons of Shem; Elam, and Asshur, and Arphaxad, and Lud, and Aram, and Uz, and Hul, and Gether, and Meshech.

^18And Arphaxad begat Shelah, and Shelah begat Eber.

^19And unto Eber were born two sons: the name of the one was Peleg; because in his days the earth was divided: and his brother’s name was Joktan.

^20And Joktan begat Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazarmaveth, and Jerah,

^21Hadoram also, and Uzal, and Diklah,

^22And Ebal, and Abimael, and Sheba,

^23And Ophir, and Havilah, and Jobab. All these were the sons of Joktan.

^24Shem, Arphaxad, Shelah,

^25Eber, Peleg, Reu,

^26Serug, Nahor, Terah,

^27Abram; the same is Abraham.

^28The sons of Abraham; Isaac, and Ishmael.

^29These are their generations: The firstborn of Ishmael, Nebaioth; then Kedar, and Adbeel, and Mibsam,

^30Mishma, and Dumah, Massa, Hadad, and Tema,

^31Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah. These are the sons of Ishmael.

^32Now the sons of Keturah, Abraham’s concubine: she bare Zimran, and Jokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah. And the sons of Jokshan; Sheba, and Dedan.

^33And the sons of Midian; Ephah, and Epher, and Henoch, and Abida, and Eldaah. All these are the sons of Keturah.

^34And Abraham begat Isaac. The sons of Isaac; Esau and Israel.

^35The sons of Esau; Eliphaz, Reuel, and Jeush, and Jaalam, and Korah.

^36The sons of Eliphaz; Teman, and Omar, Zephi, and Gatam, Kenaz, and Timna, and Amalek.

^37The sons of Reuel; Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah.

^38And the sons of Seir; Lotan, and Shobal, and Zibeon, and Anah, and Dishon, and Ezar, and Dishan.

^39And the sons of Lotan; Hori, and Homam: and Timna was Lotan’s sister.

^40The sons of Shobal; Alian, and Manahath, and Ebal, Shephi, and Onam. and the sons of Zibeon; Aiah, and Anah.

^41The sons of Anah; Dishon. And the sons of Dishon; Amram, and Eshban, and Ithran, and Cheran.

^42The sons of Ezer; Bilhan, and Zavan, and Jakan. The sons of Dishan; Uz, and Aran.

^43Now these are the kings that reigned in the land of Edom before any king reigned over the children of Israel; Bela the son of Beor: and the name of his city was Dinhabah.

^44And when Bela was dead, Jobab the son of Zerah of Bozrah reigned in his stead.

^45And when Jobab was dead, Husham of the land of the Temanites reigned in his stead.

^46And when Husham was dead, Hadad the son of Bedad, which smote Midian in the field of Moab, reigned in his stead: and the name of his city was Avith.

^47And when Hadad was dead, Samlah of Masrekah reigned in his stead.

^48And when Samlah was dead, Shaul of Rehoboth by the river reigned in his stead.

^49And when Shaul was dead, Baalhanan the son of Achbor reigned in his stead.

^50And when Baalhanan was dead, Hadad reigned in his stead: and the name of his city was Pai; and his wife’s name was Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, the daughter of Mezahab.

^51Hadad died also. And the dukes of Edom were; duke Timnah, duke Aliah, duke Jetheth,

^52Duke Aholibamah, duke Elah, duke Pinon,

^53Duke Kenaz, duke Teman, duke Mibzar,

^54Duke Magdiel, duke Iram. These are the dukes of Edom.

II

2^1These are the sons of Israel; Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah, Issachar, and Zebulun,

^2Dan, Joseph, and Benjamin, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher.

^3The sons of Judah; Er, and Onan, and Shelah: which three were born unto him of the daughter of Shua the Canaanitess. And Er, the firstborn of Judah, was evil in the sight of the Lord; and he slew him.

^4And Tamar his daughter in law bore him Pharez and Zerah. All the sons of Judah were five.

^5The sons of Pharez; Hezron, and Hamul.

^6And the sons of Zerah; Zimri, and Ethan, and Heman, and Calcol, and Dara: five of them in all.

^7And the sons of Carmi; Achar, the troubler of Israel, who transgressed in the thing accursed.

^8And the sons of Ethan; Azariah.

^9The sons also of Hezron, that were born unto him; Jerahmeel, and Ram, and Chelubai.

^10And Ram begat Amminadab; and Amminadab begat Nahshon, prince of the children of Judah;

^11And Nahshon begat Salma, and Salma begat Boaz,

^12And Boaz begat Obed, and Obed begat Jesse,

^13And Jesse begat his firstborn Eliab, and Abinadab the second, and Shimma the third,

^14Nethaneel the fourth, Raddai the fifth,

^15Ozem the sixth, David the seventh:

^16Whose sisters were Zeruiah, and Abigail. And the sons of Zeruiah; Abishai, and Joab, and Asahel, three.

^17And Abigail bare Amasa: and the father of Amasa was Jether the Ishmeelite.

^18And Caleb the son of Hezron begat children of Azubah his wife, and of Jerioth: her sons are these; Jesher, and Shobab, and Ardon.

^19And when Azubah was dead, Caleb took unto him Ephrath, which bare him Hur.

^20And Hur begat Uri, and Uri begat Bezaleel.

^21And afterward Hezron went in to the daughter of Machir the father of Gilead, whom he married when he was threescore years old; and she bare him Segub.

^22And Segub begat Jair, who had three and twenty cities in the land of Gilead.

^23And he took Geshur, and Aram, with the towns of Jair, from them, with Kenath, and the towns thereof, even threescore cities. All these belonged to the sons of Machir the father of Gilead.

^24And after that Hezron was dead in Calebephratah, then Abiah Hezron’s wife bare him Ashur the father of Tekoa.

^25And the sons of Jerahmeel the firstborn of Hezron were, Ram the firstborn, and Bunah, and Oren, and Ozem, and Ahijah.

^26Jerahmeel had also another wife, whose name was Atarah; she was the mother of Onam.

^27And the sons of Ram the firstborn of Jerahmeel were, Maaz, and Jamin, and Eker.

^28And the sons of Onam were, Shammai, and Jada. And the sons of Shammai; Nadab and Abishur.

^29And the name of the wife of Abishur was Abihail, and she bare him Ahban, and Molid.

^30And the sons of Nadab; Seled, and Appaim: but Seled died without children.

^31And the sons of Appaim; Ishi. And the sons of Ishi; Sheshan. And the children of Sheshan; Ahlai.

^32And the sons of Jada the brother of Shammai; Jether, and Jonathan: and Jether died without children.

^33And the sons of Jonathan; Peleth, and Zaza. These were the sons of Jerahmeel.

^34Now Sheshan had no sons, but daughters. And Sheshan had a servant, an Egyptian, whose name was Jarha.

^35And Sheshan gave his daughter to Jarha his servant to wife; and she bare him Attai.

^36And Attai begat Nathan, and Nathan begat Zabad,

^37And Zabad begat Ephlal, and Ephlal begat Obed,

^38And Obed begat Jehu, and Jehu begat Azariah,

^39And Azariah begat Helez, and Helez begat Eleasah,

^40And Eleasah begat Sisamai, and Sisamai begat Shallum,

^41And Shallum begat Jekamiah, and Jekamiah begat Elishama.

^42Now the sons of Caleb the brother of Jerahmeel were, Mesha his firstborn, which was the father of Ziph; and the sons of Mareshah the father of Hebron.

^43And the sons of Hebron; Korah, and Tappuah, and Rekem, and Shema.

^44And Shema begat Raham, the father of Jorkoam: and Rekem begat Shammai.

^45And the son of Shammai was Maon: and Maon was the father of Bethzur.

^46And Ephah, Caleb’s concubine, bare Haran, and Moza, and Gazez: and Haran begat Gazez.

^47And the sons of Jahdai; Regem, and Jotham, and Gesham, and Pelet, and Ephah, and Shaaph.

^48Maachah, Caleb’s concubine, bare Sheber, and Tirhanah.

^49She bare also Shaaph the father of Madmannah, Sheva the father of Machbenah, and the father of Gibea: and the daughter of Caleb was Achsa.

^50These were the sons of Caleb the son of Hur, the firstborn of Ephratah; Shobal the father of Kirjathjearim.

^51Salma the father of Bethlehem, Hareph the father of Bethgader.

^52And Shobal the father of Kirjathjearim had sons; Haroeh, and half of the Manahethites.

^53And the families of Kirjathjearim; the Ithrites, and the Puhites, and the Shumathites, and the Mishraites; of them came the Zareathites, and the Eshtaulites,

^54The sons of Salma; Bethlehem, and the Netophathites, Ataroth, the house of Joab, and half of the Manahethites, the Zorites.

^55And the families of the scribes which dwelt at Jabez; the Tirathites, the Shimeathites, and Suchathites. These are the Kenites that came of Hemath, the father of the house of Rechab.

III

3^1Now these were the sons of David, which were born unto him in Hebron; the firstborn Amnon, of Ahinoam the Jezreelitess; the second Daniel, of Abigail the Carmelitess:

^2The third, Absalom the son of Maachah the daughter of Talmai king of Geshur: the fourth, Adonijah the son of Haggith:

^3The fifth, Shephatiah of Abital: the sixth, Ithream by Eglah his wife.

^4These six were born unto him in Hebron; and there he reigned seven years and six months: and in Jerusalem he reigned thirty and three years.

^5And these were born unto him in Jerusalem; Shimea, and Shobab, and Nathan, and Solomon, four, of Bathshua the daughter of Ammiel:

^6Ibhar also, and Elishama, and Eliphelet,

^7And Nogah, and Nepheg, and Japhia,

^8And Elishama, and Eliada, and Eliphelet, nine.

^9These were all the sons of David, beside the sons of the concubines, and Tamar their sister.

^10And Solomon’s son was Rehoboam, Abia his son, Asa his son, Jehoshaphat his son,

^11Joram his son, Ahaziah his son, Joash his son,

^12Amaziah his son, Azariah his son, Jotham his son,

^13Ahaz his son, Hezekiah his son, Manasseh his son,

^14Amon his son, Josiah his son.

^15And the sons of Josiah were, the firstborn Johanan, the second Jehoiakim, the third Zedekiah, the fourth Shallum.

^16And the sons of Jehoiakim: Jeconiah his son, Zedekiah his son.

^17And the sons of Jeconiah; Assir, Salathiel his son,

^18Malchiram also, and Pedaiah, and Shenazar, Jecamiah, Hoshama, and Nedabiah.

^19And the sons of Pedaiah were, Zerubbabel, and Shimei: and the sons of Zerubbabel; Meshullam, and Hananiah, and Shelomith their sister:

^20And Hashubah, and Ohel, and Berechiah, and Hasadiah, Jushabhesed, five.

^21And the sons of Hananiah; Pelatiah, and Jesaiah: the sons of Rephaiah, the sons of Arnan, the sons of Obadiah, the sons of Shechaniah.

^22And the sons of Shechaniah; Shemaiah: and the sons of Shemaiah; Hattush, and Igeal, and Bariah, and Neariah, and Shaphat, six.

^23And the sons of Neariah; Elioenai, and Hezekiah, and Azrikam, three.

^24And the sons of Elioenai were, Hodaiah, and Eliashib, and Pelaiah, and Akkub, and Johanan, and Dalaiah, and Anani, seven.

IV

4^1The sons of Judah; Pharez, Hezron, and Carmi, and Hur, and Shobal.

^2And Reaiah the son of Shobal begat Jahath; and Jahath begat Ahumai, and Lahad. These are the families of the Zorathites.

^3And these were of the father of Etam; Jezreel, and Ishma, and Idbash: and the name of their sister was Hazelelponi:

^4And Penuel the father of Gedor, and Ezer the father of Hushah. These are the sons of Hur, the firstborn of Ephratah, the father of Bethlehem.

^5And Ashur the father of Tekoa had two wives, Helah and Naarah.

^6And Naarah bare him Ahuzam, and Hepher, and Temeni, and Haahashtari. These were the sons of Naarah.

^7And the sons of Helah were, Zereth, and Jezoar, and Ethnan.

^8And Coz begat Anub, and Zobebah, and the families of Aharhel the son of Harum.

^9And Jabez was more honourable than his brethren: and his mother called his name Jabez, saying, Because I bare him with sorrow.

^10And Jabez called on the God of Israel, saying, Oh that thou wouldest bless me indeed, and enlarge my coast, and that thine hand might be with me, and that thou wouldest keep me from evil, that it may not grieve me! And God granted him that which he requested.

^11And Chelub the brother of Shuah begat Mehir, which was the father of Eshton.

^12And Eshton begat Bethrapha, and Paseah, and Tehinnah the father of Irnahash. These are the men of Rechah.

^13And the sons of Kenaz; Othniel, and Seraiah: and the sons of Othniel; Hathath.

^14And Meonothai begat Ophrah: and Seraiah begat Joab, the father of the valley of Charashim; for they were craftsmen.

^15And the sons of Caleb the son of Jephunneh; Iru, Elah, and Naam: and the sons of Elah, even Kenaz.

^16And the sons of Jehaleleel; Ziph, and Ziphah, Tiria, and Asareel.

^17And the sons of Ezra were, Jether, and Mered, and Epher, and Jalon: and she bare Miriam, and Shammai, and Ishbah the father of Eshtemoa.

^18And his wife Jehudijah bare Jered the father of Gedor, and Heber the father of Socho, and Jekuthiel the father of Zanoah. And these are the sons of Bithiah the daughter of Pharaoh, which Mered took.

^19And the sons of his wife Hodiah the sister of Naham, the father of Keilah the Garmite, and Eshtemoa the Maachathite.

^20And the sons of Shimon were, Amnon, and Rinnah, Benhanan, and Tilon. And the sons of Ishi were, Zoheth, and Benzoheth.

^21The sons of Shelah the son of Judah were, Er the father of Lecah, and Laadah the father of Mareshah, and the families of the house of them that wrought fine linen, of the house of Ashbea,

^22And Jokim, and the men of Chozeba, and Joash, and Saraph, who had the dominion in Moab, and Jashubilehem. And these are ancient things.

^23These were the potters, and those that dwelt among plants and hedges: there they dwelt with the king for his work.

^24The sons of Simeon were, Nemuel, and Jamin, Jarib, Zerah, and Shaul:

^25Shallum his son, Mibsam his son, Mishma his son.

^26And the sons of Mishma; Hamuel his son, Zacchur his son, Shimei his son.

^27And Shimei had sixteen sons and six daughters: but his brethren had not many children, neither did all their family multiply, like to the children of Judah.

^28And they dwelt at Beersheba, and Moladah, and Hazarshual,

^29And at Bilhah, and at Ezem, and at Tolad,

^30And at Bethuel, and at Hormah, and at Ziklag,

^31And at Bethmarcaboth, and Hazarsusim, and at Bethbirei, and at Shaaraim. These were their cities unto the reign of David.

^32And their villages were, Etam, and Ain, Rimmon, and Tochen, and Ashan, five cities:

^33And all their villages that were round about the same cities, unto Baal. These were their habitations, and their genealogy.

^34And Meshobab, and Jamlech, and Joshah, the son of Amaziah,

^35And Joel, and Jehu the son of Josibiah, the son of Seraiah, the son of Asiel,

^36And Elioenai, and Jaakobah, and Jeshohaiah, and Asaiah, and Adiel, and Jesimiel, and Benaiah,

^37And Ziza the son of Shiphi, the son of Allon, the son of Jedaiah, the son of Shimri, the son of Shemaiah;

^38These mentioned by their names were princes in their families: and the house of their fathers increased greatly.

^39And they went to the entrance of Gedor, even unto the east side of the valley, to seek pasture for their flocks.

^40And they found fat pasture and good, and the land was wide, and quiet, and peaceable; for they of Ham had dwelt there of old.

^41And these written by name came in the days of Hezekiah king of Judah, and smote their tents, and the habitations that were found there, and destroyed them utterly unto this day, and dwelt in their rooms: because there was pasture there for their flocks.

^42And some of them, even of the sons of Simeon, five hundred men, went to mount Seir, having for their captains Pelatiah, and Neariah, and Rephaiah, and Uzziel, the sons of Ishi.

^43And they smote the rest of the Amalekites that were escaped, and dwelt there unto this day.

V

5^1Now the sons of Reuben the firstborn of Israel, (for he was the firstborn; but forasmuch as he defiled his father’s bed, his birthright was given unto the sons of Joseph the son of Israel: and the genealogy is not to be reckoned after the birthright.

^2For Judah prevailed above his brethren, and of him came the chief ruler; but the birthright was Joseph’s:)

^3The sons, I say, of Reuben the firstborn of Israel were, Hanoch, and Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi.

^4The sons of Joel; Shemaiah his son, Gog his son, Shimei his son,

^5Micah his son, Reaia his son, Baal his son,

^6Beerah his son, whom Tilgathpilneser king of Assyria carried away captive: he was prince of the Reubenites.

^7And his brethren by their families, when the genealogy of their generations was reckoned, were the chief, Jeiel, and Zechariah,

^8And Bela the son of Azaz, the son of Shema, the son of Joel, who dwelt in Aroer, even unto Nebo and Baalmeon:

^9And eastward he inhabited unto the entering in of the wilderness from the river Euphrates: because their cattle were multiplied in the land of Gilead.

^10And in the days of Saul they made war with the Hagarites, who fell by their hand: and they dwelt in their tents throughout all the east land of Gilead.

^11And the children of Gad dwelt over against them, in the land of Bashan unto Salcah:

^12Joel the chief, and Shapham the next, and Jaanai, and Shaphat in Bashan.

^13And their brethren of the house of their fathers were, Michael, and Meshullam, and Sheba, and Jorai, and Jachan, and Zia, and Heber, seven.

^14These are the children of Abihail the son of Huri, the son of Jaroah, the son of Gilead, the son of Michael, the son of Jeshishai, the son of Jahdo, the son of Buz;

^15Ahi the son of Abdiel, the son of Guni, chief of the house of their fathers.

^16And they dwelt in Gilead in Bashan, and in her towns, and in all the suburbs of Sharon, upon their borders.

^17All these were reckoned by genealogies in the days of Jotham king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam king of Israel.

^18The sons of Reuben, and the Gadites, and half the tribe of Manasseh, of valiant men, men able to bear buckler and sword, and to shoot with bow, and skilful in war, were four and forty thousand seven hundred and threescore, that went out to the war.

^19And they made war with the Hagarites, with Jetur, and Nephish, and Nodab.

^20And they were helped against them, and the Hagarites were delivered into their hand, and all that were with them: for they cried to God in the battle, and he was intreated of them; because they put their trust in him.

^21And they took away their cattle; of their camels fifty thousand, and of sheep two hundred and fifty thousand, and of asses two thousand, and of men an hundred thousand.

^22For there fell down many slain, because the war was of God. And they dwelt in their steads until the captivity.

^23And the children of the half tribe of Manasseh dwelt in the land: they increased from Bashan unto Baalhermon and Senir, and unto mount Hermon.

^24And these were the heads of the house of their fathers, even Epher, and Ishi, and Eliel, and Azriel, and Jeremiah, and Hodaviah, and Jahdiel, mighty men of valour, famous men, and heads of the house of their fathers.

^25And they transgressed against the God of their fathers, and went a whoring after the gods of the people of the land, whom God destroyed before them.

^26And the God of Israel stirred up the spirit of Pul king of Assyria, and the spirit of Tilgathpilneser king of Assyria, and he carried them away, even the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half tribe of Manasseh, and brought them unto Halah, and Habor, and Hara, and to the river Gozan, unto this day.

VI

6^1The sons of Levi; Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.

^2And the sons of Kohath; Amram, Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel.

^3And the children of Amram; Aaron, and Moses, and Miriam. The sons also of Aaron; Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.

^4Eleazar begat Phinehas, Phinehas begat Abishua,

^5And Abishua begat Bukki, and Bukki begat Uzzi,

^6And Uzzi begat Zerahiah, and Zerahiah begat Meraioth,

^7Meraioth begat Amariah, and Amariah begat Ahitub,

^8And Ahitub begat Zadok, and Zadok begat Ahimaaz,

^9And Ahimaaz begat Azariah, and Azariah begat Johanan,

^10And Johanan begat Azariah, (he it is that executed the priest’s office in the temple that Solomon built in Jerusalem:)

^11And Azariah begat Amariah, and Amariah begat Ahitub,

^12And Ahitub begat Zadok, and Zadok begat Shallum,

^13And Shallum begat Hilkiah, and Hilkiah begat Azariah,

^14And Azariah begat Seraiah, and Seraiah begat Jehozadak,

^15And Jehozadak went into captivity, when the Lord carried away Judah and Jerusalem by the hand of Nebuchadnezzar.

^16The sons of Levi; Gershom, Kohath, and Merari.

^17And these be the names of the sons of Gershom; Libni, and Shimei.

^18And the sons of Kohath were, Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel.

^19The sons of Merari; Mahli, and Mushi. And these are the families of the Levites according to their fathers.

^20Of Gershom; Libni his son, Jahath his son, Zimmah his son,

^21Joah his son, Iddo his son, Zerah his son, Jeaterai his son.

^22The sons of Kohath; Amminadab his son, Korah his son, Assir his son,

^23Elkanah his son, and Ebiasaph his son, and Assir his son,

^24Tahath his son, Uriel his son, Uzziah his son, and Shaul his son.

^25And the sons of Elkanah; Amasai, and Ahimoth.

^26As for Elkanah: the sons of Elkanah; Zophai his son, and Nahath his son,

^27Eliab his son, Jeroham his son, Elkanah his son.

^28And the sons of Samuel; the firstborn Vashni, and Abiah.

^29The sons of Merari; Mahli, Libni his son, Shimei his son, Uzza his son,

^30Shimea his son, Haggiah his son, Asaiah his son.

^31And these are they whom David set over the service of song in the house of the Lord, after that the ark had rest.

^32And they ministered before the dwelling place of the tabernacle of the congregation with singing, until Solomon had built the house of the Lord in Jerusalem: and then they waited on their office according to their order.

^33And these are they that waited with their children. Of the sons of the Kohathites: Heman a singer, the son of Joel, the son of Shemuel,

^34The son of Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Eliel, the son of Toah,

^35The son of Zuph, the son of Elkanah, the son of Mahath, the son of Amasai,

^36The son of Elkanah, the son of Joel, the son of Azariah, the son of Zephaniah,

^37The son of Tahath, the son of Assir, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah,

^38The son of Izhar, the son of Kohath, the son of Levi, the son of Israel.

^39And his brother Asaph, who stood on his right hand, even Asaph the son of Berachiah, the son of Shimea,

^40The son of Michael, the son of Baaseiah, the son of Malchiah,

^41The son of Ethni, the son of Zerah, the son of Adaiah,

^42The son of Ethan, the son of Zimmah, the son of Shimei,

^43The son of Jahath, the son of Gershom, the son of Levi.

^44And their brethren the sons of Merari stood on the left hand: Ethan the son of Kishi, the son of Abdi, the son of Malluch,

^45The son of Hashabiah, the son of Amaziah, the son of Hilkiah,

^46The son of Amzi, the son of Bani, the son of Shamer,

^47The son of Mahli, the son of Mushi, the son of Merari, the son of Levi.

^48Their brethren also the Levites were appointed unto all manner of service of the tabernacle of the house of God.

^49But Aaron and his sons offered upon the altar of the burnt offering, and on the altar of incense, and were appointed for all the work of the place most holy, and to make an atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses the servant of God had commanded.

^50And these are the sons of Aaron; Eleazar his son, Phinehas his son, Abishua his son,

^51Bukki his son, Uzzi his son, Zerahiah his son,

^52Meraioth his son, Amariah his son, Ahitub his son,

^53Zadok his son, Ahimaaz his son.

^54Now these are their dwelling places throughout their castles in their coasts, of the sons of Aaron, of the families of the Kohathites: for theirs was the lot.

^55And they gave them Hebron in the land of Judah, and the suburbs thereof round about it.

^56But the fields of the city, and the villages thereof, they gave to Caleb the son of Jephunneh.

^57And to the sons of Aaron they gave the cities of Judah, namely, Hebron, the city of refuge, and Libnah with her suburbs, and Jattir, and Eshtemoa, with their suburbs,

^58And Hilen with her suburbs, Debir with her suburbs,

^59And Ashan with her suburbs, and Bethshemesh with her suburbs:

^60And out of the tribe of Benjamin; Geba with her suburbs, and Alemeth with her suburbs, and Anathoth with her suburbs. All their cities throughout their families were thirteen cities.

^61And unto the sons of Kohath, which were left of the family of that tribe, were cities given out of the half tribe, namely, out of the half tribe of Manasseh, by lot, ten cities.

^62And to the sons of Gershom throughout their families out of the tribe of Issachar, and out of the tribe of Asher, and out of the tribe of Naphtali, and out of the tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteen cities.

^63Unto the sons of Merari were given by lot, throughout their families, out of the tribe of Reuben, and out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun, twelve cities.

^64And the children of Israel gave to the Levites these cities with their suburbs.

^65And they gave by lot out of the tribe of the children of Judah, and out of the tribe of the children of Simeon, and out of the tribe of the children of Benjamin, these cities, which are called by their names.

^66And the residue of the families of the sons of Kohath had cities of their coasts out of the tribe of Ephraim.

^67And they gave unto them, of the cities of refuge, Shechem in mount Ephraim with her suburbs; they gave also Gezer with her suburbs,

^68And Jokmeam with her suburbs, and Bethhoron with her suburbs,

^69And Aijalon with her suburbs, and Gathrimmon with her suburbs:

^70And out of the half tribe of Manasseh; Aner with her suburbs, and Bileam with her suburbs, for the family of the remnant of the sons of Kohath.

^71Unto the sons of Gershom were given out of the family of the half tribe of Manasseh, Golan in Bashan with her suburbs, and Ashtaroth with her suburbs:

^72And out of the tribe of Issachar; Kedesh with her suburbs, Daberath with her suburbs,

^73And Ramoth with her suburbs, and Anem with her suburbs:

^74And out of the tribe of Asher; Mashal with her suburbs, and Abdon with her suburbs,

^75And Hukok with her suburbs, and Rehob with her suburbs:

^76And out of the tribe of Naphtali; Kedesh in Galilee with her suburbs, and Hammon with her suburbs, and Kirjathaim with her suburbs.

^77Unto the rest of the children of Merari were given out of the tribe of Zebulun, Rimmon with her suburbs, Tabor with her suburbs:

^78And on the other side Jordan by Jericho, on the east side of Jordan, were given them out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer in the wilderness with her suburbs, and Jahzah with her suburbs,

^79Kedemoth also with her suburbs, and Mephaath with her suburbs:

^80And out of the tribe of Gad; Ramoth in Gilead with her suburbs, and Mahanaim with her suburbs,

^81And Heshbon with her suburbs, and Jazer with her suburbs.

VII

7^1Now the sons of Issachar were, Tola, and Puah, Jashub, and Shimrom, four.

^2And the sons of Tola; Uzzi, and Rephaiah, and Jeriel, and Jahmai, and Jibsam, and Shemuel, heads of their father’s house, to wit, of Tola: they were valiant men of might in their generations; whose number was in the days of David two and twenty thousand and six hundred.

^3And the sons of Uzzi; Izrahiah: and the sons of Izrahiah; Michael, and Obadiah, and Joel, Ishiah, five: all of them chief men.

^4And with them, by their generations, after the house of their fathers, were bands of soldiers for war, six and thirty thousand men: for they had many wives and sons.

^5And their brethren among all the families of Issachar were valiant men of might, reckoned in all by their genealogies fourscore and seven thousand.

^6The sons of Benjamin; Bela, and Becher, and Jediael, three.

^7And the sons of Bela; Ezbon, and Uzzi, and Uzziel, and Jerimoth, and Iri, five; heads of the house of their fathers, mighty men of valour; and were reckoned by their genealogies twenty and two thousand and thirty and four.

^8And the sons of Becher; Zemira, and Joash, and Eliezer, and Elioenai, and Omri, and Jerimoth, and Abiah, and Anathoth, and Alameth. All these are the sons of Becher.

^9And the number of them, after their genealogy by their generations, heads of the house of their fathers, mighty men of valour, was twenty thousand and two hundred.

^10The sons also of Jediael; Bilhan: and the sons of Bilhan; Jeush, and Benjamin, and Ehud, and Chenaanah, and Zethan, and Tharshish, and Ahishahar.

^11All these the sons of Jediael, by the heads of their fathers, mighty men of valour, were seventeen thousand and two hundred soldiers, fit to go out for war and battle.

^12Shuppim also, and Huppim, the children of Ir, and Hushim, the sons of Aher.

^13The sons of Naphtali; Jahziel, and Guni, and Jezer, and Shallum, the sons of Bilhah.

^14The sons of Manasseh; Ashriel, whom she bare: (but his concubine the Aramitess bare Machir the father of Gilead:

^15And Machir took to wife the sister of Huppim and Shuppim, whose sister’s name was Maachah;) and the name of the second was Zelophehad: and Zelophehad had daughters.

^16And Maachah the wife of Machir bare a son, and she called his name Peresh; and the name of his brother was Sheresh; and his sons were Ulam and Rakem.

^17And the sons of Ulam; Bedan. These were the sons of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh.

^18And his sister Hammoleketh bare Ishod, and Abiezer, and Mahalah.

^19And the sons of Shemidah were, Ahian, and Shechem, and Likhi, and Aniam.

^20And the sons of Ephraim; Shuthelah, and Bered his son, and Tahath his son, and Eladah his son, and Tahath his son,

^21And Zabad his son, and Shuthelah his son, and Ezer, and Elead, whom the men of Gath that were born in that land slew, because they came down to take away their cattle.

^22And Ephraim their father mourned many days, and his brethren came to comfort him.

^23And when he went in to his wife, she conceived, and bare a son, and he called his name Beriah, because it went evil with his house.

^24(And his daughter was Sherah, who built Bethhoron the nether, and the upper, and Uzzensherah.)

^25And Rephah was his son, also Resheph, and Telah his son, and Tahan his son.

^26Laadan his son, Ammihud his son, Elishama his son.

^27Non his son, Jehoshuah his son.

^28And their possessions and habitations were, Bethel and the towns thereof, and eastward Naaran, and westward Gezer, with the towns thereof; Shechem also and the towns thereof, unto Gaza and the towns thereof:

^29And by the borders of the children of Manasseh, Bethshean and her towns, Taanach and her towns, Megiddo and her towns, Dor and her towns. In these dwelt the children of Joseph the son of Israel.

^30The sons of Asher; Imnah, and Isuah, and Ishuai, and Beriah, and Serah their sister.

^31And the sons of Beriah; Heber, and Malchiel, who is the father of Birzavith.

^32And Heber begat Japhlet, and Shomer, and Hotham, and Shua their sister.

^33And the sons of Japhlet; Pasach, and Bimhal, and Ashvath. These are the children of Japhlet.

^34And the sons of Shamer; Ahi, and Rohgah, Jehubbah, and Aram.

^35And the sons of his brother Helem; Zophah, and Imna, and Shelesh, and Amal.

^36The sons of Zophah; Suah, and Harnepher, and Shual, and Beri, and Imrah,

^37Bezer, and Hod, and Shamma, and Shilshah, and Ithran, and Beera.

^38And the sons of Jether; Jephunneh, and Pispah, and Ara.

^39And the sons of Ulla; Arah, and Haniel, and Rezia.

^40All these were the children of Asher, heads of their father’s house, choice and mighty men of valour, chief of the princes. And the number throughout the genealogy of them that were apt to the war and to battle was twenty and six thousand men.

VIII

8^1Now Benjamin begat Bela his firstborn, Ashbel the second, and Aharah the third,

^2Nohah the fourth, and Rapha the fifth.

^3And the sons of Bela were, Addar, and Gera, and Abihud,

^4And Abishua, and Naaman, and Ahoah,

^5And Gera, and Shephuphan, and Huram.

^6And these are the sons of Ehud: these are the heads of the fathers of the inhabitants of Geba, and they removed them to Manahath:

^7And Naaman, and Ahiah, and Gera, he removed them, and begat Uzza, and Ahihud.

^8And Shaharaim begat children in the country of Moab, after he had sent them away; Hushim and Baara were his wives.

^9And he begat of Hodesh his wife, Jobab, and Zibia, and Mesha, and Malcham,

^10And Jeuz, and Shachia, and Mirma. These were his sons, heads of the fathers.

^11And of Hushim he begat Abitub, and Elpaal.

^12The sons of Elpaal; Eber, and Misham, and Shamed, who built Ono, and Lod, with the towns thereof:

^13Beriah also, and Shema, who were heads of the fathers of the inhabitants of Aijalon, who drove away the inhabitants of Gath:

^14And Ahio, Shashak, and Jeremoth,

^15And Zebadiah, and Arad, and Ader,

^16And Michael, and Ispah, and Joha, the sons of Beriah;

^17And Zebadiah, and Meshullam, and Hezeki, and Heber,

^18Ishmerai also, and Jezliah, and Jobab, the sons of Elpaal;

^19And Jakim, and Zichri, and Zabdi,

^20And Elienai, and Zilthai, and Eliel,

^21And Adaiah, and Beraiah, and Shimrath, the sons of Shimhi;

^22And Ishpan, and Heber, and Eliel,

^23And Abdon, and Zichri, and Hanan,

^24And Hananiah, and Elam, and Antothijah,

^25And Iphedeiah, and Penuel, the sons of Shashak;

^26And Shamsherai, and Shehariah, and Athaliah,

^27And Jaresiah, and Eliah, and Zichri, the sons of Jeroham.

^28These were heads of the fathers, by their generations, chief men. These dwelt in Jerusalem.

^29And at Gibeon dwelt the father of Gibeon; whose wife’s name was Maachah:

^30And his firstborn son Abdon, and Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Nadab,

^31And Gedor, and Ahio, and Zacher.

^32And Mikloth begat Shimeah. And these also dwelt with their brethren in Jerusalem, over against them.

^33And Ner begat Kish, and Kish begat Saul, and Saul begat Jonathan, and Malchishua, and Abinadab, and Eshbaal.

^34And the son of Jonathan was Meribbaal; and Meribbaal begat Micah.

^35And the sons of Micah were, Pithon, and Melech, and Tarea, and Ahaz.

^36And Ahaz begat Jehoadah; and Jehoadah begat Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri; and Zimri begat Moza,

^37And Moza begat Binea: Rapha was his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son:

^38And Azel had six sons, whose names are these, Azrikam, Bocheru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan. All these were the sons of Azel.

^39And the sons of Eshek his brother were, Ulam his firstborn, Jehush the second, and Eliphelet the third.

^40And the sons of Ulam were mighty men of valour, archers, and had many sons, and sons’ sons, an hundred and fifty. All these are of the sons of Benjamin.

IX

9^1So all Israel were reckoned by genealogies; and, behold, they were written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah, who were carried away to Babylon for their transgression.

^2Now the first inhabitants that dwelt in their possessions in their cities were, the Israelites, the priests, Levites, and the Nethinims.

^3And in Jerusalem dwelt of the children of Judah, and of the children of Benjamin, and of the children of Ephraim, and Manasseh;

^4Uthai the son of Ammihud, the son of Omri, the son of Imri, the son of Bani, of the children of Pharez the son of Judah.

^5And of the Shilonites; Asaiah the firstborn, and his sons.

^6And of the sons of Zerah; Jeuel, and their brethren, six hundred and ninety.

^7And of the sons of Benjamin; Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Hodaviah, the son of Hasenuah,

^8And Ibneiah the son of Jeroham, and Elah the son of Uzzi, the son of Michri, and Meshullam the son of Shephathiah, the son of Reuel, the son of Ibnijah;

^9And their brethren, according to their generations, nine hundred and fifty and six. All these men were chief of the fathers in the house of their fathers.

^10And of the priests; Jedaiah, and Jehoiarib, and Jachin,

^11And Azariah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the ruler of the house of God;

^12And Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pashur, the son of Malchijah, and Maasiai the son of Adiel, the son of Jahzerah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Meshillemith, the son of Immer;

^13And their brethren, heads of the house of their fathers, a thousand and seven hundred and threescore; very able men for the work of the service of the house of God.

^14And of the Levites; Shemaiah the son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, of the sons of Merari;

^15And Bakbakkar, Heresh, and Galal, and Mattaniah the son of Micah, the son of Zichri, the son of Asaph;

^16And Obadiah the son of Shemaiah, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun, and Berechiah the son of Asa, the son of Elkanah, that dwelt in the villages of the Netophathites.

^17And the porters were, Shallum, and Akkub, and Talmon, and Ahiman, and their brethren: Shallum was the chief;

^18Who hitherto waited in the king’s gate eastward: they were porters in the companies of the children of Levi.

^19And Shallum the son of Kore, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah, and his brethren, of the house of his father, the Korahites, were over the work of the service, keepers of the gates of the tabernacle: and their fathers, being over the host of the Lord, were keepers of the entry.

^20And Phinehas the son of Eleazar was the ruler over them in time past, and the Lord was with him.

^21And Zechariah the son of Meshelemiah was porter of the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.

^22All these which were chosen to be porters in the gates were two hundred and twelve. These were reckoned by their genealogy in their villages, whom David and Samuel the seer did ordain in their set office.

^23So they and their children had the oversight of the gates of the house of the Lord, namely, the house of the tabernacle, by wards.

^24In four quarters were the porters, toward the east, west, north, and south.

^25And their brethren, which were in their villages, were to come after seven days from time to time with them.

^26For these Levites, the four chief porters, were in their set office, and were over the chambers and treasuries of the house of God.

^27And they lodged round about the house of God, because the charge was upon them, and the opening thereof every morning pertained to them.

^28And certain of them had the charge of the ministering vessels, that they should bring them in and out by tale.

^29Some of them also were appointed to oversee the vessels, and all the instruments of the sanctuary, and the fine flour, and the wine, and the oil, and the frankincense, and the spices.

^30And some of the sons of the priests made the ointment of the spices.

^31And Mattithiah, one of the Levites, who was the firstborn of Shallum the Korahite, had the set office over the things that were made in the pans.

^32And other of their brethren, of the sons of the Kohathites, were over the shewbread, to prepare it every sabbath.

^33And these are the singers, chief of the fathers of the Levites, who remaining in the chambers were free: for they were employed in that work day and night.

^34These chief fathers of the Levites were chief throughout their generations; these dwelt at Jerusalem.

^35And in Gibeon dwelt the father of Gibeon, Jehiel, whose wife’s name was Maachah:

^36And his firstborn son Abdon, then Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Ner, and Nadab.

^37And Gedor, and Ahio, and Zechariah, and Mikloth.

^38And Mikloth begat Shimeam. And they also dwelt with their brethren at Jerusalem, over against their brethren.

^39And Ner begat Kish; and Kish begat Saul; and Saul begat Jonathan, and Malchishua, and Abinadab, and Eshbaal.

^40And the son of Jonathan was Meribbaal: and Meribbaal begat Micah.

^41And the sons of Micah were, Pithon, and Melech, and Tahrea, and Ahaz.

^42And Ahaz begat Jarah; and Jarah begat Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri; and Zimri begat Moza;

^43And Moza begat Binea; and Rephaiah his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son.

^44And Azel had six sons, whose names are these, Azrikam, Bocheru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan: these were the sons of Azel.

X

10^1Now the Philistines fought against Israel; and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines, and fell down slain in mount Gilboa.

^2And the Philistines followed hard after Saul, and after his sons; and the Philistines slew Jonathan, and Abinadab, and Malchishua, the sons of Saul.

^3And the battle went sore against Saul, and the archers hit him, and he was wounded of the archers.

^4Then said Saul to his armourbearer, Draw thy sword, and thrust me through therewith; lest these uncircumcised come and abuse me. But his armourbearer would not; for he was sore afraid. So Saul took a sword, and fell upon it.

^5And when his armourbearer saw that Saul was dead, he fell likewise on the sword, and died.

^6So Saul died, and his three sons, and all his house died together.

^7And when all the men of Israel that were in the valley saw that they fled, and that Saul and his sons were dead, then they forsook their cities, and fled: and the Philistines came and dwelt in them.

^8And it came to pass on the morrow, when the Philistines came to strip the slain, that they found Saul and his sons fallen in mount Gilboa.

^9And when they had stripped him, they took his head, and his armour, and sent into the land of the Philistines round about, to carry tidings unto their idols, and to the people.

^10And they put his armour in the house of their gods, and fastened his head in the temple of Dagon.

^11And when all Jabeshgilead heard all that the Philistines had done to Saul,

^12They arose, all the valiant men, and took away the body of Saul, and the bodies of his sons, and brought them to Jabesh, and buried their bones under the oak in Jabesh, and fasted seven days.

^13So Saul died for his transgression which he committed against the Lord, even against the word of the Lord, which he kept not, and also for asking counsel of one that had a familiar spirit, to enquire of it;

^14And enquired not of the Lord: therefore he slew him, and turned the kingdom unto David the son of Jesse.

XI

11^1Then all Israel gathered themselves to David unto Hebron, saying, Behold, we are thy bone and thy flesh.

^2And moreover in time past, even when Saul was king, thou wast he that leddest out and broughtest in Israel: and the Lord thy God said unto thee, Thou shalt feed my people Israel, and thou shalt be ruler over my people Israel.

^3Therefore came all the elders of Israel to the king to Hebron; and David made a covenant with them in Hebron before the Lord; and they anointed David king over Israel, according to the word of the Lord by Samuel.

^4And David and all Israel went to Jerusalem, which is Jebus; where the Jebusites were, the inhabitants of the land.

^5And the inhabitants of Jebus said to David, Thou shalt not come hither. Nevertheless David took the castle of Zion, which is the city of David.

^6And David said, Whosoever smiteth the Jebusites first shall be chief and captain. So Joab the son of Zeruiah went first up, and was chief.

^7And David dwelt in the castle; therefore they called it the city of David.

^8And he built the city round about, even from Millo round about: and Joab repaired the rest of the city.

^9So David waxed greater and greater: for the Lord of hosts was with him.

^10These also are the chief of the mighty men whom David had, who strengthened themselves with him in his kingdom, and with all Israel, to make him king, according to the word of the Lord concerning Israel.

^11And this is the number of the mighty men whom David had; Jashobeam, an Hachmonite, the chief of the captains: he lifted up his spear against three hundred slain by him at one time.

^12And after him was Eleazar the son of Dodo, the Ahohite, who was one of the three mighties.

^13He was with David at Pasdammim, and there the Philistines were gathered together to battle, where was a parcel of ground full of barley; and the people fled from before the Philistines.

^14And they set themselves in the midst of that parcel, and delivered it, and slew the Philistines; and the Lord saved them by a great deliverance.

^15Now three of the thirty captains went down to the rock to David, into the cave of Adullam; and the host of the Philistines encamped in the valley of Rephaim.

^16And David was then in the hold, and the Philistines’ garrison was then at Bethlehem.

^17And David longed, and said, Oh that one would give me drink of the water of the well of Bethlehem, that is at the gate!

^18And the three brake through the host of the Philistines, and drew water out of the well of Bethlehem, that was by the gate, and took it, and brought it to David: but David would not drink of it, but poured it out to the Lord.

^19And said, My God forbid it me, that I should do this thing: shall I drink the blood of these men that have put their lives in jeopardy? for with the jeopardy of their lives they brought it. Therefore he would not drink it. These things did these three mightiest.

^20And Abishai the brother of Joab, he was chief of the three: for lifting up his spear against three hundred, he slew them, and had a name among the three.

^21Of the three, he was more honourable than the two; for he was their captain: howbeit he attained not to the first three.

^22Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the son of a valiant man of Kabzeel, who had done many acts; he slew two lionlike men of Moab: also he went down and slew a lion in a pit in a snowy day.

^23And he slew an Egyptian, a man of great stature, five cubits high; and in the Egyptian’s hand was a spear like a weaver’s beam; and he went down to him with a staff, and plucked the spear out of the Egyptian’s hand, and slew him with his own spear.

^24These things did Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and had the name among the three mighties.

^25Behold, he was honourable among the thirty, but attained not to the first three: and David set him over his guard.

^26Also the valiant men of the armies were, Asahel the brother of Joab, Elhanan the son of Dodo of Bethlehem,

^27Shammoth the Harorite, Helez the Pelonite,

^28Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, Abiezer the Antothite,

^29Sibbecai the Hushathite, Ilai the Ahohite,

^30Maharai the Netophathite, Heled the son of Baanah the Netophathite,

^31Ithai the son of Ribai of Gibeah, that pertained to the children of Benjamin, Benaiah the Pirathonite,

^32Hurai of the brooks of Gaash, Abiel the Arbathite,

^33Azmaveth the Baharumite, Eliahba the Shaalbonite,

^34The sons of Hashem the Gizonite, Jonathan the son of Shage the Hararite,

^35Ahiam the son of Sacar the Hararite, Eliphal the son of Ur,

^36Hepher the Mecherathite, Ahijah the Pelonite,

^37Hezro the Carmelite, Naarai the son of Ezbai,

^38Joel the brother of Nathan, Mibhar the son of Haggeri,

^39Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Berothite, the armourbearer of Joab the son of Zeruiah,

^40Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite,

^41Uriah the Hittite, Zabad the son of Ahlai,

^42Adina the son of Shiza the Reubenite, a captain of the Reubenites, and thirty with him,

^43Hanan the son of Maachah, and Joshaphat the Mithnite,

^44Uzzia the Ashterathite, Shama and Jehiel the sons of Hothan the Aroerite,

^45Jediael the son of Shimri, and Joha his brother, the Tizite,

^46Eliel the Mahavite, and Jeribai, and Joshaviah, the sons of Elnaam, and Ithmah the Moabite,

^47Eliel, and Obed, and Jasiel the Mesobaite.

XII

12^1Now these are they that came to David to Ziklag, while he yet kept himself close because of Saul the son of Kish: and they were among the mighty men, helpers of the war.

^2They were armed with bows, and could use both the right hand and the left in hurling stones and shooting arrows out of a bow, even of Saul’s brethren of Benjamin.

^3The chief was Ahiezer, then Joash, the sons of Shemaah the Gibeathite; and Jeziel, and Pelet, the sons of Azmaveth; and Berachah, and Jehu the Antothite.

^4And Ismaiah the Gibeonite, a mighty man among the thirty, and over the thirty; and Jeremiah, and Jahaziel, and Johanan, and Josabad the Gederathite,

^5Eluzai, and Jerimoth, and Bealiah, and Shemariah, and Shephatiah the Haruphite,

^6Elkanah, and Jesiah, and Azareel, and Joezer, and Jashobeam, the Korhites,

^7And Joelah, and Zebadiah, the sons of Jeroham of Gedor.

^8And of the Gadites there separated themselves unto David into the hold to the wilderness men of might, and men of war fit for the battle, that could handle shield and buckler, whose faces were like the faces of lions, and were as swift as the roes upon the mountains;

^9Ezer the first, Obadiah the second, Eliab the third,

^10Mishmannah the fourth, Jeremiah the fifth,

^11Attai the sixth, Eliel the seventh,

^12Johanan the eighth, Elzabad the ninth,

^13Jeremiah the tenth, Machbanai the eleventh.

^14These were of the sons of Gad, captains of the host: one of the least was over an hundred, and the greatest over a thousand.

^15These are they that went over Jordan in the first month, when it had overflown all his banks; and they put to flight all them of the valleys, both toward the east, and toward the west.

^16And there came of the children of Benjamin and Judah to the hold unto David.

^17And David went out to meet them, and answered and said unto them, If ye be come peaceably unto me to help me, mine heart shall be knit unto you: but if ye be come to betray me to mine enemies, seeing there is no wrong in mine hands, the God of our fathers look thereon, and rebuke it.

^18Then the spirit came upon Amasai, who was chief of the captains, and he said, Thine are we, David, and on thy side, thou son of Jesse: peace, peace be unto thee, and peace be to thine helpers; for thy God helpeth thee. Then David received them, and made them captains of the band.

^19And there fell some of Manasseh to David, when he came with the Philistines against Saul to battle: but they helped them not: for the lords of the Philistines upon advisement sent him away, saying, He will fall to his master Saul to the jeopardy of our heads.

^20As he went to Ziklag, there fell to him of Manasseh, Adnah, and Jozabad, and Jediael, and Michael, and Jozabad, and Elihu, and Zilthai, captains of the thousands that were of Manasseh.

^21And they helped David against the band of the rovers: for they were all mighty men of valour, and were captains in the host.

^22For at that time day by day there came to David to help him, until it was a great host, like the host of God.

^23And these are the numbers of the bands that were ready armed to the war, and came to David to Hebron, to turn the kingdom of Saul to him, according to the word of the Lord.

^24The children of Judah that bare shield and spear were six thousand and eight hundred, ready armed to the war.

^25Of the children of Simeon, mighty men of valour for the war, seven thousand and one hundred.

^26Of the children of Levi four thousand and six hundred.

^27And Jehoiada was the leader of the Aaronites, and with him were three thousand and seven hundred;

^28And Zadok, a young man mighty of valour, and of his father’s house twenty and two captains.

^29And of the children of Benjamin, the kindred of Saul, three thousand: for hitherto the greatest part of them had kept the ward of the house of Saul.

^30And of the children of Ephraim twenty thousand and eight hundred, mighty men of valour, famous throughout the house of their fathers.

^31And of the half tribe of Manasseh eighteen thousand, which were expressed by name, to come and make David king.

^32And of the children of Issachar, which were men that had understanding of the times, to know what Israel ought to do; the heads of them were two hundred; and all their brethren were at their commandment.

^33Of Zebulun, such as went forth to battle, expert in war, with all instruments of war, fifty thousand, which could keep rank: they were not of double heart.

^34And of Naphtali a thousand captains, and with them with shield and spear thirty and seven thousand.

^35And of the Danites expert in war twenty and eight thousand and six hundred.

^36And of Asher, such as went forth to battle, expert in war, forty thousand.

^37And on the other side of Jordan, of the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and of the half tribe of Manasseh, with all manner of instruments of war for the battle, an hundred and twenty thousand.

^38All these men of war, that could keep rank, came with a perfect heart to Hebron, to make David king over all Israel: and all the rest also of Israel were of one heart to make David king.

^39And there they were with David three days, eating and drinking: for their brethren had prepared for them.

^40Moreover they that were nigh them, even unto Issachar and Zebulun and Naphtali, brought bread on asses, and on camels, and on mules, and on oxen, and meat, meal, cakes of figs, and bunches of raisins, and wine, and oil, and oxen, and sheep abundantly: for there was joy in Israel.

XIII

13^1And David consulted with the captains of thousands and hundreds, and with every leader.

^2And David said unto all the congregation of Israel, If it seem good unto you, and that it be of the Lord our God, let us send abroad unto our brethren every where, that are left in all the land of Israel, and with them also to the priests and Levites which are in their cities and suburbs, that they may gather themselves unto us:

^3And let us bring again the ark of our God to us: for we enquired not at it in the days of Saul.

^4And all the congregation said that they would do so: for the thing was right in the eyes of all the people.

^5So David gathered all Israel together, from Shihor of Egypt even unto the entering of Hemath, to bring the ark of God from Kirjathjearim.

^6And David went up, and all Israel, to Baalah, that is, to Kirjathjearim, which belonged to Judah, to bring up thence the ark of God the Lord, that dwelleth between the cherubims, whose name is called on it.

^7And they carried the ark of God in a new cart out of the house of Abinadab: and Uzza and Ahio drave the cart.

^8And David and all Israel played before God with all their might, and with singing, and with harps, and with psalteries, and with timbrels, and with cymbals, and with trumpets.

^9And when they came unto the threshingfloor of Chidon, Uzza put forth his hand to hold the ark; for the oxen stumbled.

^10And the anger of the Lord was kindled against Uzza, and he smote him, because he put his hand to the ark: and there he died before God.

^11And David was displeased, because the Lord had made a breach upon Uzza: wherefore that place is called Perezuzza to this day.

^12And David was afraid of God that day, saying, How shall I bring the ark of God home to me?

^13So David brought not the ark home to himself to the city of David, but carried it aside into the house of Obededom the Gittite.

^14And the ark of God remained with the family of Obededom in his house three months. And the Lord blessed the house of Obededom, and all that he had.

XIV

14^1Now Hiram king of Tyre sent messengers to David, and timber of cedars, with masons and carpenters, to build him an house.

^2And David perceived that the Lord had confirmed him king over Israel, for his kingdom was lifted up on high, because of his people Israel.

^3And David took more wives at Jerusalem: and David begat more sons and daughters.

^4Now these are the names of his children which he had in Jerusalem; Shammua, and Shobab, Nathan, and Solomon,

^5And Ibhar, and Elishua, and Elpalet,

^6And Nogah, and Nepheg, and Japhia,

^7And Elishama, and Beeliada, and Eliphalet.

^8And when the Philistines heard that David was anointed king over all Israel, all the Philistines went up to seek David. And David heard of it, and went out against them.

^9And the Philistines came and spread themselves in the valley of Rephaim.

^10And David enquired of God, saying, Shall I go up against the Philistines? And wilt thou deliver them into mine hand? And the Lord said unto him, Go up; for I will deliver them into thine hand.

^11So they came up to Baalperazim; and David smote them there. Then David said, God hath broken in upon mine enemies by mine hand like the breaking forth of waters: therefore they called the name of that place Baalperazim.

^12And when they had left their gods there, David gave a commandment, and they were burned with fire.

^13And the Philistines yet again spread themselves abroad in the valley.

^14Therefore David enquired again of God; and God said unto him, Go not up after them; turn away from them, and come upon them over against the mulberry trees.

^15And it shall be, when thou shalt hear a sound of going in the tops of the mulberry trees, that then thou shalt go out to battle: for God is gone forth before thee to smite the host of the Philistines.

^16David therefore did as God commanded him: and they smote the host of the Philistines from Gibeon even to Gazer.

^17And the fame of David went out into all lands; and the Lord brought the fear of him upon all nations.

XV

15^1And David made him houses in the city of David, and prepared a place for the ark of God, and pitched for it a tent.

^2Then David said, None ought to carry the ark of God but the Levites: for them hath the Lord chosen to carry the ark of God, and to minister unto him for ever.

^3And David gathered all Israel together to Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of the Lord unto his place, which he had prepared for it.

^4And David assembled the children of Aaron, and the Levites:

^5Of the sons of Kohath; Uriel the chief, and his brethren an hundred and twenty:

^6Of the sons of Merari; Asaiah the chief, and his brethren two hundred and twenty:

^7Of the sons of Gershom; Joel the chief and his brethren an hundred and thirty:

^8Of the sons of Elizaphan; Shemaiah the chief, and his brethren two hundred:

^9Of the sons of Hebron; Eliel the chief, and his brethren fourscore:

^10Of the sons of Uzziel; Amminadab the chief, and his brethren an hundred and twelve.

^11And David called for Zadok and Abiathar the priests, and for the Levites, for Uriel, Asaiah, and Joel, Shemaiah, and Eliel, and Amminadab,

^12And said unto them, Ye are the chief of the fathers of the Levites: sanctify yourselves, both ye and your brethren, that ye may bring up the ark of the Lord God of Israel unto the place that I have prepared for it.

^13For because ye did it not at the first, the Lord our God made a breach upon us, for that we sought him not after the due order.

^14So the priests and the Levites sanctified themselves to bring up the ark of the Lord God of Israel.

^15And the children of the Levites bare the ark of God upon their shoulders with the staves thereon, as Moses commanded according to the word of the Lord.

^16And David spake to the chief of the Levites to appoint their brethren to be the singers with instruments of musick, psalteries and harps and cymbals, sounding, by lifting up the voice with joy.

^17So the Levites appointed Heman the son of Joel; and of his brethren, Asaph the son of Berechiah; and of the sons of Merari their brethren, Ethan the son of Kushaiah;

^18And with them their brethren of the second degree, Zechariah, Ben, and Jaaziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, Eliab, and Benaiah, and Maaseiah, and Mattithiah, and Elipheleh, and Mikneiah, and Obededom, and Jeiel, the porters.

^19So the singers, Heman, Asaph, and Ethan, were appointed to sound with cymbals of brass;

^20And Zechariah, and Aziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, and Eliab, and Maaseiah, and Benaiah, with psalteries on Alamoth;

^21And Mattithiah, and Elipheleh, and Mikneiah, and Obededom, and Jeiel, and Azaziah, with harps on the Sheminith to excel.

^22And Chenaniah, chief of the Levites, was for song: he instructed about the song, because he was skilful.

^23And Berechiah and Elkanah were doorkeepers for the ark.

^24And Shebaniah, and Jehoshaphat, and Nethaneel, and Amasai, and Zechariah, and Benaiah, and Eliezer, the priests, did blow with the trumpets before the ark of God: and Obededom and Jehiah were doorkeepers for the ark.

^25So David, and the elders of Israel, and the captains over thousands, went to bring up the ark of the covenant of the Lord out of the house of Obededom with joy.

^26And it came to pass, when God helped the Levites that bare the ark of the covenant of the Lord, that they offered seven bullocks and seven rams.

^27And David was clothed with a robe of fine linen, and all the Levites that bare the ark, and the singers, and Chenaniah the master of the song with the singers: David also had upon him an ephod of linen.

^28Thus all Israel brought up the ark of the covenant of the Lord with shouting, and with sound of the cornet, and with trumpets, and with cymbals, making a noise with psalteries and harps.

^29And it came to pass, as the ark of the covenant of the Lord came to the city of David, that Michal, the daughter of Saul looking out at a window saw king David dancing and playing: and she despised him in her heart.

XVI

16^1So they brought the ark of God, and set it in the midst of the tent that David had pitched for it: and they offered burnt sacrifices and peace offerings before God.

^2And when David had made an end of offering the burnt offerings and the peace offerings, he blessed the people in the name of the Lord.

^3And he dealt to every one of Israel, both man and woman, to every one a loaf of bread, and a good piece of flesh, and a flagon of wine.

^4And he appointed certain of the Levites to minister before the ark of the Lord, and to record, and to thank and praise the Lord God of Israel:

^5Asaph the chief, and next to him Zechariah, Jeiel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Mattithiah, and Eliab, and Benaiah, and Obededom: and Jeiel with psalteries and with harps; but Asaph made a sound with cymbals;

^6Benaiah also and Jahaziel the priests with trumpets continually before the ark of the covenant of God.

^7Then on that day David delivered first this psalm to thank the Lord into the hand of Asaph and his brethren.

^8Give thanks unto the Lord, call upon his name, make known his deeds among the people.

^9Sing unto him, sing psalms unto him, talk ye of all his wondrous works.

^10Glory ye in his holy name: let the heart of them rejoice that seek the Lord.

^11Seek the Lord and his strength, seek his face continually.

^12Remember his marvellous works that he hath done, his wonders, and the judgments of his mouth;

^13O ye seed of Israel his servant, ye children of Jacob, his chosen ones.

^14He is the Lord our God; his judgments are in all the earth.

^15Be ye mindful always of his covenant; the word which he commanded to a thousand generations;

^16Even of the covenant which he made with Abraham, and of his oath unto Isaac;

^17And hath confirmed the same to Jacob for a law, and to Israel for an everlasting covenant,

^18Saying, Unto thee will I give the land of Canaan, the lot of your inheritance;

^19When ye were but few, even a few, and strangers in it.

^20And when they went from nation to nation, and from one kingdom to another people;

^21He suffered no man to do them wrong: yea, he reproved kings for their sakes,

^22Saying, Touch not mine anointed, and do my prophets no harm.

^23Sing unto the Lord, all the earth; shew forth from day to day his salvation.

^24Declare his glory among the heathen; his marvellous works among all nations.

^25For great is the Lord, and greatly to be praised: he also is to be feared above all gods.

^26For all the gods of the people are idols: but the Lord made the heavens.

^27Glory and honour are in his presence; strength and gladness are in his place.

^28Give unto the Lord, ye kindreds of the people, give unto the Lord glory and strength.

^29Give unto the Lord the glory due unto his name: bring an offering, and come before him: worship the Lord in the beauty of holiness.

^30Fear before him, all the earth: the world also shall be stable, that it be not moved.

^31Let the heavens be glad, and let the earth rejoice: and let men say among the nations, The Lord reigneth.

^32Let the sea roar, and the fulness thereof: let the fields rejoice, and all that is therein.

^33Then shall the trees of the wood sing out at the presence of the Lord, because he cometh to judge the earth.

^34O give thanks unto the Lord; for he is good; for his mercy endureth for ever.

^35And say ye, Save us, O God of our salvation, and gather us together, and deliver us from the heathen, that we may give thanks to thy holy name, and glory in thy praise.

^36Blessed be the Lord God of Israel for ever and ever. And all the people said, Amen, and praised the Lord.

^37So he left there before the ark of the covenant of the Lord Asaph and his brethren, to minister before the ark continually, as every day’s work required:

^38And Obededom with their brethren, threescore and eight; Obededom also the son of Jeduthun and Hosah to be porters:

^39And Zadok the priest, and his brethren the priests, before the tabernacle of the Lord in the high place that was at Gibeon,

^40To offer burnt offerings unto the Lord upon the altar of the burnt offering continually morning and evening, and to do according to all that is written in the law of the Lord, which he commanded Israel;

^41And with them Heman and Jeduthun, and the rest that were chosen, who were expressed by name, to give thanks to the Lord, because his mercy endureth for ever;

^42And with them Heman and Jeduthun with trumpets and cymbals for those that should make a sound, and with musical instruments of God. And the sons of Jeduthun were porters.

^43And all the people departed every man to his house: and David returned to bless his house.

XVII

17^1Now it came to pass, as David sat in his house, that David said to Nathan the prophet, Lo, I dwell in an house of cedars, but the ark of the covenant of the Lord remaineth under curtains.

^2Then Nathan said unto David, Do all that is in thine heart; for God is with thee.

^3And it came to pass the same night, that the word of God came to Nathan, saying,

^4Go and tell David my servant, Thus saith the Lord, Thou shalt not build me an house to dwell in:

^5For I have not dwelt in an house since the day that I brought up Israel unto this day; but have gone from tent to tent, and from one tabernacle to another.

^6Wheresoever I have walked with all Israel, spake I a word to any of the judges of Israel, whom I commanded to feed my people, saying, Why have ye not built me an house of cedars?

^7Now therefore thus shalt thou say unto my servant David, Thus saith the Lord of hosts, I took thee from the sheepcote, even from following the sheep, that thou shouldest be ruler over my people Israel:

^8And I have been with thee whithersoever thou hast walked, and have cut off all thine enemies from before thee, and have made thee a name like the name of the great men that are in the earth.

^9Also I will ordain a place for my people Israel, and will plant them, and they shall dwell in their place, and shall be moved no more; neither shall the children of wickedness waste them any more, as at the beginning,

^10And since the time that I commanded judges to be over my people Israel. Moreover I will subdue all thine enemies. Furthermore I tell thee that the Lord will build thee an house.

^11And it shall come to pass, when thy days be expired that thou must go to be with thy fathers, that I will raise up thy seed after thee, which shall be of thy sons; and I will establish his kingdom.

^12He shall build me an house, and I will stablish his throne for ever.

^13I will be his father, and he shall be my son: and I will not take my mercy away from him, as I took it from him that was before thee:

^14But I will settle him in mine house and in my kingdom for ever: and his throne shall be established for evermore.

^15According to all these words, and according to all this vision, so did Nathan speak unto David.

^16And David the king came and sat before the Lord, and said, Who am I, O Lord God, and what is mine house, that thou hast brought me hitherto?

^17And yet this was a small thing in thine eyes, O God; for thou hast also spoken of thy servant’s house for a great while to come, and hast regarded me according to the estate of a man of high degree, O Lord God.

^18What can David speak more to thee for the honour of thy servant? for thou knowest thy servant.

^19O Lord, for thy servant’s sake, and according to thine own heart, hast thou done all this greatness, in making known all these great things.

^20O Lord, there is none like thee, neither is there any God beside thee, according to all that we have heard with our ears.

^21And what one nation in the earth is like thy people Israel, whom God went to redeem to be his own people, to make thee a name of greatness and terribleness, by driving out nations from before thy people whom thou hast redeemed out of Egypt?

^22For thy people Israel didst thou make thine own people for ever; and thou, Lord, becamest their God.

^23Therefore now, Lord, let the thing that thou hast spoken concerning thy servant and concerning his house be established for ever, and do as thou hast said.

^24Let it even be established, that thy name may be magnified for ever, saying, The Lord of hosts is the God of Israel, even a God to Israel: and let the house of David thy servant be established before thee.

^25For thou, O my God, hast told thy servant that thou wilt build him an house: therefore thy servant hath found in his heart to pray before thee.

^26And now, Lord, thou art God, and hast promised this goodness unto thy servant:

^27Now therefore let it please thee to bless the house of thy servant, that it may be before thee for ever: for thou blessest, O Lord, and it shall be blessed for ever.

XVIII

18^1Now after this it came to pass, that David smote the Philistines, and subdued them, and took Gath and her towns out of the hand of the Philistines.

^2And he smote Moab; and the Moabites became David’s servants, and brought gifts.

^3And David smote Hadarezer king of Zobah unto Hamath, as he went to stablish his dominion by the river Euphrates.

^4And David took from him a thousand chariots, and seven thousand horsemen, and twenty thousand footmen: David also houghed all the chariot horses, but reserved of them an hundred chariots.

^5And when the Syrians of Damascus came to help Hadarezer king of Zobah, David slew of the Syrians two and twenty thousand men.

^6Then David put garrisons in Syriadamascus; and the Syrians became David’s servants, and brought gifts. Thus the Lord preserved David whithersoever he went.

^7And David took the shields of gold that were on the servants of Hadarezer, and brought them to Jerusalem.

^8Likewise from Tibhath, and from Chun, cities of Hadarezer, brought David very much brass, wherewith Solomon made the brasen sea, and the pillars, and the vessels of brass.

^9Now when Tou king of Hamath heard how David had smitten all the host of Hadarezer king of Zobah;

^10He sent Hadoram his son to king David, to enquire of his welfare, and to congratulate him, because he had fought against Hadarezer, and smitten him; (for Hadarezer had war with Tou;) and with him all manner of vessels of gold and silver and brass.

^11Them also king David dedicated unto the Lord, with the silver and the gold that he brought from all these nations; from Edom, and from Moab, and from the children of Ammon, and from the Philistines, and from Amalek.

^12Moreover Abishai the son of Zeruiah slew of the Edomites in the valley of salt eighteen thousand.

^13And he put garrisons in Edom; and all the Edomites became David’s servants. Thus the Lord preserved David whithersoever he went.

^14So David reigned over all Israel, and executed judgment and justice among all his people.

^15And Joab the son of Zeruiah was over the host; and Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud, recorder.

^16And Zadok the son of Ahitub, and Abimelech the son of Abiathar, were the priests; and Shavsha was scribe;

^17And Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the Cherethites and the Pelethites; and the sons of David were chief about the king.

XIX

19^1Now it came to pass after this, that Nahash the king of the children of Ammon died, and his son reigned in his stead.

^2And David said, I will shew kindness unto Hanun the son of Nahash, because his father shewed kindness to me. And David sent messengers to comfort him concerning his father. So the servants of David came into the land of the children of Ammon to Hanun, to comfort him.

^3But the princes of the children of Ammon said to Hanun, Thinkest thou that David doth honour thy father, that he hath sent comforters unto thee? are not his servants come unto thee for to search, and to overthrow, and to spy out the land?

^4Wherefore Hanun took David’s servants, and shaved them, and cut off their garments in the midst hard by their buttocks, and sent them away.

^5Then there went certain, and told David how the men were served. And he sent to meet them: for the men were greatly ashamed. And the king said, Tarry at Jericho until your beards be grown, and then return.

^6And when the children of Ammon saw that they had made themselves odious to David, Hanun and the children of Ammon sent a thousand talents of silver to hire them chariots and horsemen out of Mesopotamia, and out of Syriamaachah, and out of Zobah.

^7So they hired thirty and two thousand chariots, and the king of Maachah and his people; who came and pitched before Medeba. And the children of Ammon gathered themselves together from their cities, and came to battle.

^8And when David heard of it, he sent Joab, and all the host of the mighty men.

^9And the children of Ammon came out, and put the battle in array before the gate of the city: and the kings that were come were by themselves in the field.

^10Now when Joab saw that the battle was set against him before and behind, he chose out of all the choice of Israel, and put them in array against the Syrians.

^11And the rest of the people he delivered unto the hand of Abishai his brother, and they set themselves in array against the children of Ammon.

^12And he said, If the Syrians be too strong for me, then thou shalt help me: but if the children of Ammon be too strong for thee, then I will help thee.

^13Be of good courage, and let us behave ourselves valiantly for our people, and for the cities of our God: and let the Lord do that which is good in his sight.

^14So Joab and the people that were with him drew nigh before the Syrians unto the battle; and they fled before him.

^15And when the children of Ammon saw that the Syrians were fled, they likewise fled before Abishai his brother, and entered into the city. Then Joab came to Jerusalem.

^16And when the Syrians saw that they were put to the worse before Israel, they sent messengers, and drew forth the Syrians that were beyond the river: and Shophach the captain of the host of Hadarezer went before them.

^17And it was told David; and he gathered all Israel, and passed over Jordan, and came upon them, and set the battle in array against them. So when David had put the battle in array against the Syrians, they fought with him.

^18But the Syrians fled before Israel; and David slew of the Syrians seven thousand men which fought in chariots, and forty thousand footmen, and killed Shophach the captain of the host.

^19And when the servants of Hadarezer saw that they were put to the worse before Israel, they made peace with David, and became his servants: neither would the Syrians help the children of Ammon any more.

XX

20^1And it came to pass, that after the year was expired, at the time that kings go out to battle, Joab led forth the power of the army, and wasted the country of the children of Ammon, and came and besieged Rabbah. But David tarried at Jerusalem. And Joab smote Rabbah, and destroyed it.

^2And David took the crown of their king from off his head, and found it to weigh a talent of gold, and there were precious stones in it; and it was set upon David’s head: and he brought also exceeding much spoil out of the city.

^3And he brought out the people that were in it, and cut them with saws, and with harrows of iron, and with axes. Even so dealt David with all the cities of the children of Ammon. And David and all the people returned to Jerusalem.

^4And it came to pass after this, that there arose war at Gezer with the Philistines; at which time Sibbechai the Hushathite slew Sippai, that was of the children of the giant: and they were subdued.

^5And there was war again with the Philistines; and Elhanan the son of Jair slew Lahmi the brother of Goliath the Gittite, whose spear staff was like a weaver’s beam.

^6And yet again there was war at Gath, where was a man of great stature, whose fingers and toes were four and twenty, six on each hand, and six on each foot and he also was the son of the giant.

^7But when he defied Israel, Jonathan the son of Shimea David’s brother slew him.

^8These were born unto the giant in Gath; and they fell by the hand of David, and by the hand of his servants.

XXI

21^1And Satan stood up against Israel, and provoked David to number Israel.

^2And David said to Joab and to the rulers of the people, Go, number Israel from Beersheba even to Dan; and bring the number of them to me, that I may know it.

^3And Joab answered, The Lord make his people an hundred times so many more as they be: but, my lord the king, are they not all my lord’s servants? why then doth my lord require this thing? why will he be a cause of trespass to Israel?

^4Nevertheless the king’s word prevailed against Joab. Wherefore Joab departed, and went throughout all Israel, and came to Jerusalem.

^5And Joab gave the sum of the number of the people unto David. And all they of Israel were a thousand thousand and an hundred thousand men that drew sword: and Judah was four hundred threescore and ten thousand men that drew sword.

^6But Levi and Benjamin counted he not among them: for the king’s word was abominable to Joab.

^7And God was displeased with this thing; therefore he smote Israel.

^8And David said unto God, I have sinned greatly, because I have done this thing: but now, I beseech thee, do away the iniquity of thy servant; for I have done very foolishly.

^9And the Lord spake unto Gad, David’s seer, saying,

^10Go and tell David, saying, Thus saith the Lord, I offer thee three things: choose thee one of them, that I may do it unto thee.

^11So Gad came to David, and said unto him, Thus saith the Lord, Choose thee

^12Either three years’ famine; or three months to be destroyed before thy foes, while that the sword of thine enemies overtaketh thee; or else three days the sword of the Lord, even the pestilence, in the land, and the angel of the Lord destroying throughout all the coasts of Israel. Now therefore advise thyself what word I shall bring again to him that sent me.

^13And David said unto Gad, I am in a great strait: let me fall now into the hand of the Lord; for very great are his mercies: but let me not fall into the hand of man.

^14So the Lord sent pestilence upon Israel: and there fell of Israel seventy thousand men.

^15And God sent an angel unto Jerusalem to destroy it: and as he was destroying, the Lord beheld, and he repented him of the evil, and said to the angel that destroyed, It is enough, stay now thine hand. And the angel of the Lord stood by the threshingfloor of Ornan the Jebusite.

^16And David lifted up his eyes, and saw the angel of the Lord stand between the earth and the heaven, having a drawn sword in his hand stretched out over Jerusalem. Then David and the elders of Israel, who were clothed in sackcloth, fell upon their faces.

^17And David said unto God, Is it not I that commanded the people to be numbered? even I it is that have sinned and done evil indeed; but as for these sheep, what have they done? let thine hand, I pray thee, O Lord my God, be on me, and on my father’s house; but not on thy people, that they should be plagued.

^18Then the angel of the Lord commanded Gad to say to David, that David should go up, and set up an altar unto the Lord in the threshingfloor of Ornan the Jebusite.

^19And David went up at the saying of Gad, which he spake in the name of the Lord.

^20And Ornan turned back, and saw the angel; and his four sons with him hid themselves. Now Ornan was threshing wheat.

^21And as David came to Ornan, Ornan looked and saw David, and went out of the threshingfloor, and bowed himself to David with his face to the ground.

^22Then David said to Ornan, Grant me the place of this threshingfloor, that I may build an altar therein unto the Lord: thou shalt grant it me for the full price: that the plague may be stayed from the people.

^23And Ornan said unto David, Take it to thee, and let my lord the king do that which is good in his eyes: lo, I give thee the oxen also for burnt offerings, and the threshing instruments for wood, and the wheat for the meat offering; I give it all.

^24And king David said to Ornan, Nay; but I will verily buy it for the full price: for I will not take that which is thine for the Lord, nor offer burnt offerings without cost.

^25So David gave to Ornan for the place six hundred shekels of gold by weight.

^26And David built there an altar unto the Lord, and offered burnt offerings and peace offerings, and called upon the Lord; and he answered him from heaven by fire upon the altar of burnt offering.

^27And the Lord commanded the angel; and he put up his sword again into the sheath thereof.

^28At that time when David saw that the Lord had answered him in the threshingfloor of Ornan the Jebusite, then he sacrificed there.

^29For the tabernacle of the Lord, which Moses made in the wilderness, and the altar of the burnt offering, were at that season in the high place at Gibeon.

^30But David could not go before it to enquire of God: for he was afraid because of the sword of the angel of the Lord.

XXII

22^1Then David said, This is the house of the Lord God, and this is the altar of the burnt offering for Israel.

^2And David commanded to gather together the strangers that were in the land of Israel; and he set masons to hew wrought stones to build the house of God.

^3And David prepared iron in abundance for the nails for the doors of the gates, and for the joinings; and brass in abundance without weight;

^4Also cedar trees in abundance: for the Zidonians and they of Tyre brought much cedar wood to David.

^5And David said, Solomon my son is young and tender, and the house that is to be builded for the Lord must be exceeding magnifical, of fame and of glory throughout all countries: I will therefore now make preparation for it. So David prepared abundantly before his death.

^6Then he called for Solomon his son, and charged him to build an house for the Lord God of Israel.

^7And David said to Solomon, My son, as for me, it was in my mind to build an house unto the name of the Lord my God:

^8But the word of the Lord came to me, saying, Thou hast shed blood abundantly, and hast made great wars: thou shalt not build an house unto my name, because thou hast shed much blood upon the earth in my sight.

^9Behold, a son shall be born to thee, who shall be a man of rest; and I will give him rest from all his enemies round about: for his name shall be Solomon, and I will give peace and quietness unto Israel in his days.

^10He shall build an house for my name; and he shall be my son, and I will be his father; and I will establish the throne of his kingdom over Israel for ever.

^11Now, my son, the Lord be with thee; and prosper thou, and build the house of the Lord thy God, as he hath said of thee.

^12Only the Lord give thee wisdom and understanding, and give thee charge concerning Israel, that thou mayest keep the law of the Lord thy God.

^13Then shalt thou prosper, if thou takest heed to fulfil the statutes and judgments which the Lord charged Moses with concerning Israel: be strong, and of good courage; dread not, nor be dismayed.

^14Now, behold, in my trouble I have prepared for the house of the Lord an hundred thousand talents of gold, and a thousand thousand talents of silver; and of brass and iron without weight; for it is in abundance: timber also and stone have I prepared; and thou mayest add thereto.

^15Moreover there are workmen with thee in abundance, hewers and workers of stone and timber, and all manner of cunning men for every manner of work.

^16Of the gold, the silver, and the brass, and the iron, there is no number. Arise therefore, and be doing, and the Lord be with thee.

^17David also commanded all the princes of Israel to help Solomon his son, saying,

^18Is not the Lord your God with you? and hath he not given you rest on every side? for he hath given the inhabitants of the land into mine hand; and the land is subdued before the Lord, and before his people.

^19Now set your heart and your soul to seek the Lord your God; arise therefore, and build ye the sanctuary of the Lord God, to bring the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and the holy vessels of God, into the house that is to be built to the name of the Lord.

XXIII

23^1So when David was old and full of days, he made Solomon his son king over Israel.

^2And he gathered together all the princes of Israel, with the priests and the Levites.

^3Now the Levites were numbered from the age of thirty years and upward: and their number by their polls, man by man, was thirty and eight thousand.

^4Of which, twenty and four thousand were to set forward the work of the house of the Lord; and six thousand were officers and judges:

^5Moreover four thousand were porters; and four thousand praised the Lord with the instruments which I made, said David, to praise therewith.

^6And David divided them into courses among the sons of Levi, namely, Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.

^7Of the Gershonites were, Laadan, and Shimei.

^8The sons of Laadan; the chief was Jehiel, and Zetham, and Joel, three.

^9The sons of Shimei; Shelomith, and Haziel, and Haran, three. These were the chief of the fathers of Laadan.

^10And the sons of Shimei were, Jahath, Zina, and Jeush, and Beriah. These four were the sons of Shimei.

^11And Jahath was the chief, and Zizah the second: but Jeush and Beriah had not many sons; therefore they were in one reckoning, according to their father’s house.

^12The sons of Kohath; Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel, four.

^13The sons of Amram; Aaron and Moses: and Aaron was separated, that he should sanctify the most holy things, he and his sons for ever, to burn incense before the Lord, to minister unto him, and to bless in his name for ever.

^14Now concerning Moses the man of God, his sons were named of the tribe of Levi.

^15The sons of Moses were, Gershom, and Eliezer.

^16Of the sons of Gershom, Shebuel was the chief.

^17And the sons of Eliezer were, Rehabiah the chief. And Eliezer had none other sons; but the sons of Rehabiah were very many.

^18Of the sons of Izhar; Shelomith the chief.

^19Of the sons of Hebron; Jeriah the first, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, and Jekameam the fourth.

^20Of the sons of Uzziel; Micah the first and Jesiah the second.

^21The sons of Merari; Mahli, and Mushi. The sons of Mahli; Eleazar, and Kish.

^22And Eleazar died, and had no sons, but daughters: and their brethren the sons of Kish took them.

^23The sons of Mushi; Mahli, and Eder, and Jeremoth, three.

^24These were the sons of Levi after the house of their fathers; even the chief of the fathers, as they were counted by number of names by their polls, that did the work for the service of the house of the Lord, from the age of twenty years and upward.

^25For David said, The Lord God of Israel hath given rest unto his people, that they may dwell in Jerusalem for ever:

^26And also unto the Levites; they shall no more carry the tabernacle, nor any vessels of it for the service thereof.

^27For by the last words of David the Levites were numbered from twenty years old and above:

^28Because their office was to wait on the sons of Aaron for the service of the house of the Lord, in the courts, and in the chambers, and in the purifying of all holy things, and the work of the service of the house of God;

^29Both for the shewbread, and for the fine flour for meat offering, and for the unleavened cakes, and for that which is baked in the pan, and for that which is fried, and for all manner of measure and size;

^30And to stand every morning to thank and praise the Lord, and likewise at even:

^31And to offer all burnt sacrifices unto the Lord in the sabbaths, in the new moons, and on the set feasts, by number, according to the order commanded unto them, continually before the Lord:

^32And that they should keep the charge of the tabernacle of the congregation, and the charge of the holy place, and the charge of the sons of Aaron their brethren, in the service of the house of the Lord.

XXIV

24^1Now these are the divisions of the sons of Aaron. The sons of Aaron; Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.

^2But Nadab and Abihu died before their father, and had no children: therefore Eleazar and Ithamar executed the priest’s office.

^3And David distributed them, both Zadok of the sons of Eleazar, and Ahimelech of the sons of Ithamar, according to their offices in their service.

^4And there were more chief men found of the sons of Eleazar than of the sons of Ithamar, and thus were they divided. Among the sons of Eleazar there were sixteen chief men of the house of their fathers, and eight among the sons of Ithamar according to the house of their fathers.

^5Thus were they divided by lot, one sort with another; for the governors of the sanctuary, and governors of the house of God, were of the sons of Eleazar, and of the sons of Ithamar.

^6And Shemaiah the son of Nethaneel the scribe, one of the Levites, wrote them before the king, and the princes, and Zadok the priest, and Ahimelech the son of Abiathar, and before the chief of the fathers of the priests and Levites: one principal household being taken for Eleazar, and one taken for Ithamar.

^7Now the first lot came forth to Jehoiarib, the second to Jedaiah,

^8The third to Harim, the fourth to Seorim,

^9The fifth to Malchijah, the sixth to Mijamin,

^10The seventh to Hakkoz, the eighth to Abijah,

^11The ninth to Jeshuah, the tenth to Shecaniah,

^12The eleventh to Eliashib, the twelfth to Jakim,

^13The thirteenth to Huppah, the fourteenth to Jeshebeab,

^14The fifteenth to Bilgah, the sixteenth to Immer,

^15The seventeenth to Hezir, the eighteenth to Aphses,

^16The nineteenth to Pethahiah, the twentieth to Jehezekel,

^17The one and twentieth to Jachin, the two and twentieth to Gamul,

^18The three and twentieth to Delaiah, the four and twentieth to Maaziah.

^19These were the orderings of them in their service to come into the house of the Lord, according to their manner, under Aaron their father, as the Lord God of Israel had commanded him.

^20And the rest of the sons of Levi were these: Of the sons of Amram; Shubael: of the sons of Shubael; Jehdeiah.

^21Concerning Rehabiah: of the sons of Rehabiah, the first was Isshiah.

^22Of the Izharites; Shelomoth: of the sons of Shelomoth; Jahath.

^23And the sons of Hebron; Jeriah the first, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, Jekameam the fourth.

^24Of the sons of Uzziel; Michah: of the sons of Michah; Shamir.

^25The brother of Michah was Isshiah: of the sons of Isshiah; Zechariah.

^26The sons of Merari were Mahli and Mushi: the sons of Jaaziah; Beno.

^27The sons of Merari by Jaaziah; Beno, and Shoham, and Zaccur, and Ibri.

^28Of Mahli came Eleazar, who had no sons.

^29Concerning Kish: the son of Kish was Jerahmeel.

^30The sons also of Mushi; Mahli, and Eder, and Jerimoth. These were the sons of the Levites after the house of their fathers.

^31These likewise cast lots over against their brethren the sons of Aaron in the presence of David the king, and Zadok, and Ahimelech, and the chief of the fathers of the priests and Levites, even the principal fathers over against their younger brethren.

XXV

25^1Moreover David and the captains of the host separated to the service of the sons of Asaph, and of Heman, and of Jeduthun, who should prophesy with harps, with psalteries, and with cymbals: and the number of the workmen according to their service was:

^2Of the sons of Asaph; Zaccur, and Joseph, and Nethaniah, and Asarelah, the sons of Asaph under the hands of Asaph, which prophesied according to the order of the king.

^3Of Jeduthun: the sons of Jeduthun; Gedaliah, and Zeri, and Jeshaiah, Hashabiah, and Mattithiah, six, under the hands of their father Jeduthun, who prophesied with a harp, to give thanks and to praise the Lord.

^4Of Heman: the sons of Heman: Bukkiah, Mattaniah, Uzziel, Shebuel, and Jerimoth, Hananiah, Hanani, Eliathah, Giddalti, and Romamtiezer, Joshbekashah, Mallothi, Hothir, and Mahazioth:

^5All these were the sons of Heman the king’s seer in the words of God, to lift up the horn. And God gave to Heman fourteen sons and three daughters.

^6All these were under the hands of their father for song in the house of the Lord, with cymbals, psalteries, and harps, for the service of the house of God, according to the king’s order to Asaph, Jeduthun, and Heman.

^7So the number of them, with their brethren that were instructed in the songs of the Lord, even all that were cunning, was two hundred fourscore and eight.

^8And they cast lots, ward against ward, as well the small as the great, the teacher as the scholar.

^9Now the first lot came forth for Asaph to Joseph: the second to Gedaliah, who with his brethren and sons were twelve:

^10The third to Zaccur, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^11The fourth to Izri, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^12The fifth to Nethaniah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^13The sixth to Bukkiah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^14The seventh to Jesharelah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^15The eighth to Jeshaiah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^16The ninth to Mattaniah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^17The tenth to Shimei, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^18The eleventh to Azareel, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^19The twelfth to Hashabiah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^20The thirteenth to Shubael, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^21The fourteenth to Mattithiah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^22The fifteenth to Jeremoth, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^23The sixteenth to Hananiah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^24The seventeenth to Joshbekashah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^25The eighteenth to Hanani, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^26The nineteenth to Mallothi, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^27The twentieth to Eliathah, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^28The one and twentieth to Hothir, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^29The two and twentieth to Giddalti, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^30The three and twentieth to Mahazioth, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve:

^31The four and twentieth to Romamtiezer, he, his sons, and his brethren, were twelve.

XXVI

26^1Concerning the divisions of the porters: Of the Korhites was Meshelemiah the son of Kore, of the sons of Asaph.

^2And the sons of Meshelemiah were, Zechariah the firstborn, Jediael the second, Zebadiah the third, Jathniel the fourth,

^3Elam the fifth, Jehohanan the sixth, Elioenai the seventh.

^4Moreover the sons of Obededom were, Shemaiah the firstborn, Jehozabad the second, Joah the third, and Sacar the fourth, and Nethaneel the fifth.

^5Ammiel the sixth, Issachar the seventh, Peulthai the eighth: for God blessed him.

^6Also unto Shemaiah his son were sons born, that ruled throughout the house of their father: for they were mighty men of valour.

^7The sons of Shemaiah; Othni, and Rephael, and Obed, Elzabad, whose brethren were strong men, Elihu, and Semachiah.

^8All these of the sons of Obededom: they and their sons and their brethren, able men for strength for the service, were threescore and two of Obededom.

^9And Meshelemiah had sons and brethren, strong men, eighteen.

^10Also Hosah, of the children of Merari, had sons; Simri the chief, (for though he was not the firstborn, yet his father made him the chief;)

^11Hilkiah the second, Tebaliah the third, Zechariah the fourth: all the sons and brethren of Hosah were thirteen.

^12Among these were the divisions of the porters, even among the chief men, having wards one against another, to minister in the house of the Lord.

^13And they cast lots, as well the small as the great, according to the house of their fathers, for every gate.

^14And the lot eastward fell to Shelemiah. Then for Zechariah his son, a wise counsellor, they cast lots; and his lot came out northward.

^15To Obededom southward; and to his sons the house of Asuppim.

^16To Shuppim and Hosah the lot came forth westward, with the gate Shallecheth, by the causeway of the going up, ward against ward.

^17Eastward were six Levites, northward four a day, southward four a day, and toward Asuppim two and two.

^18At Parbar westward, four at the causeway, and two at Parbar.

^19These are the divisions of the porters among the sons of Kore, and among the sons of Merari.

^20And of the Levites, Ahijah was over the treasures of the house of God, and over the treasures of the dedicated things.

^21As concerning the sons of Laadan; the sons of the Gershonite Laadan, chief fathers, even of Laadan the Gershonite, were Jehieli.

^22The sons of Jehieli; Zetham, and Joel his brother, which were over the treasures of the house of the Lord.

^23Of the Amramites, and the Izharites, the Hebronites, and the Uzzielites:

^24And Shebuel the son of Gershom, the son of Moses, was ruler of the treasures.

^25And his brethren by Eliezer; Rehabiah his son, and Jeshaiah his son, and Joram his son, and Zichri his son, and Shelomith his son.

^26Which Shelomith and his brethren were over all the treasures of the dedicated things, which David the king, and the chief fathers, the captains over thousands and hundreds, and the captains of the host, had dedicated.

^27Out of the spoils won in battles did they dedicate to maintain the house of the Lord.

^28And all that Samuel the seer, and Saul the son of Kish, and Abner the son of Ner, and Joab the son of Zeruiah, had dedicated; and whosoever had dedicated any thing, it was under the hand of Shelomith, and of his brethren.

^29Of the Izharites, Chenaniah and his sons were for the outward business over Israel, for officers and judges.

^30And of the Hebronites, Hashabiah and his brethren, men of valour, a thousand and seven hundred, were officers among them of Israel on this side Jordan westward in all the business of the Lord, and in the service of the king.

^31Among the Hebronites was Jerijah the chief, even among the Hebronites, according to the generations of his fathers. In the fortieth year of the reign of David they were sought for, and there were found among them mighty men of valour at Jazer of Gilead.

^32And his brethren, men of valour, were two thousand and seven hundred chief fathers, whom king David made rulers over the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half tribe of Manasseh, for every matter pertaining to God, and affairs of the king.

XXVII

27^1Now the children of Israel after their number, to wit, the chief fathers and captains of thousands and hundreds, and their officers that served the king in any matter of the courses, which came in and went out month by month throughout all the months of the year, of every course were twenty and four thousand.

^2Over the first course for the first month was Jashobeam the son of Zabdiel: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.

^3Of the children of Perez was the chief of all the captains of the host for the first month.

^4And over the course of the second month was Dodai an Ahohite, and of his course was Mikloth also the ruler: in his course likewise were twenty and four thousand.

^5The third captain of the host for the third month was Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, a chief priest: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.

^6This is that Benaiah, who was mighty among the thirty, and above the thirty: and in his course was Ammizabad his son.

^7The fourth captain for the fourth month was Asahel the brother of Joab, and Zebadiah his son after him: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.

^8The fifth captain for the fifth month was Shamhuth the Izrahite: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.

^9The sixth captain for the sixth month was Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.

^10The seventh captain for the seventh month was Helez the Pelonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.

^11The eighth captain for the eighth month was Sibbecai the Hushathite, of the Zarhites: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.

^12The ninth captain for the ninth month was Abiezer the Anetothite, of the Benjamites: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.

^13The tenth captain for the tenth month was Maharai the Netophathite, of the Zarhites: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.

^14The eleventh captain for the eleventh month was Benaiah the Pirathonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.

^15The twelfth captain for the twelfth month was Heldai the Netophathite, of Othniel: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.

^16Furthermore over the tribes of Israel: the ruler of the Reubenites was Eliezer the son of Zichri: of the Simeonites, Shephatiah the son of Maachah:

^17Of the Levites, Hashabiah the son of Kemuel: of the Aaronites, Zadok:

^18Of Judah, Elihu, one of the brethren of David: of Issachar, Omri the son of Michael:

^19Of Zebulun, Ishmaiah the son of Obadiah: of Naphtali, Jerimoth the son of Azriel:

^20Of the children of Ephraim, Hoshea the son of Azaziah: of the half tribe of Manasseh, Joel the son of Pedaiah:

^21Of the half tribe of Manasseh in Gilead, Iddo the son of Zechariah: of Benjamin, Jaasiel the son of Abner:

^22Of Dan, Azareel the son of Jeroham. These were the princes of the tribes of Israel.

^23But David took not the number of them from twenty years old and under: because the Lord had said he would increase Israel like to the stars of the heavens.

^24Joab the son of Zeruiah began to number, but he finished not, because there fell wrath for it against Israel; neither was the number put in the account of the chronicles of king David.

^25And over the king’s treasures was Azmaveth the son of Adiel: and over the storehouses in the fields, in the cities, and in the villages, and in the castles, was Jehonathan the son of Uzziah:

^26And over them that did the work of the field for tillage of the ground was Ezri the son of Chelub:

^27And over the vineyards was Shimei the Ramathite: over the increase of the vineyards for the wine cellars was Zabdi the Shiphmite:

^28And over the olive trees and the sycomore trees that were in the low plains was Baalhanan the Gederite: and over the cellars of oil was Joash:

^29And over the herds that fed in Sharon was Shitrai the Sharonite: and over the herds that were in the valleys was Shaphat the son of Adlai:

^30Over the camels also was Obil the Ishmaelite: and over the asses was Jehdeiah the Meronothite:

^31And over the flocks was Jaziz the Hagerite. All these were the rulers of the substance which was king David’s.

^32Also Jonathan David’s uncle was a counsellor, a wise man, and a scribe: and Jehiel the son of Hachmoni was with the king’s sons:

^33And Ahithophel was the king’s counsellor: and Hushai the Archite was the king’s companion:

^34And after Ahithophel was Jehoiada the son of Benaiah, and Abiathar: and the general of the king’s army was Joab.

XXVIII

28^1And David assembled all the princes of Israel, the princes of the tribes, and the captains of the companies that ministered to the king by course, and the captains over the thousands, and captains over the hundreds, and the stewards over all the substance and possession of the king, and of his sons, with the officers, and with the mighty men, and with all the valiant men, unto Jerusalem.

^2Then David the king stood up upon his feet, and said, Hear me, my brethren, and my people: As for me, I had in mine heart to build an house of rest for the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and for the footstool of our God, and had made ready for the building:

^3But God said unto me, Thou shalt not build an house for my name, because thou hast been a man of war, and hast shed blood.

^4Howbeit the Lord God of Israel chose me before all the house of my father to be king over Israel for ever: for he hath chosen Judah to be the ruler; and of the house of Judah, the house of my father; and among the sons of my father he liked me to make me king over all Israel:

^5And of all my sons, (for the Lord hath given me many sons,) he hath chosen Solomon my son to sit upon the throne of the kingdom of the Lord over Israel.

^6And he said unto me, Solomon thy son, he shall build my house and my courts: for I have chosen him to be my son, and I will be his father.

^7Moreover I will establish his kingdom for ever, if he be constant to do my commandments and my judgments, as at this day.

^8Now therefore in the sight of all Israel the congregation of the Lord, and in the audience of our God, keep and seek for all the commandments of the Lord your God: that ye may possess this good land, and leave it for an inheritance for your children after you for ever.

^9And thou, Solomon my son, know thou the God of thy father, and serve him with a perfect heart and with a willing mind: for the Lord searcheth all hearts, and understandeth all the imaginations of the thoughts: if thou seek him, he will be found of thee; but if thou forsake him, he will cast thee off for ever.

^10Take heed now; for the Lord hath chosen thee to build an house for the sanctuary: be strong, and do it.

^11Then David gave to Solomon his son the pattern of the porch, and of the houses thereof, and of the treasuries thereof, and of the upper chambers thereof, and of the inner parlours thereof, and of the place of the mercy seat,

^12And the pattern of all that he had by the spirit, of the courts of the house of the Lord, and of all the chambers round about, of the treasuries of the house of God, and of the treasuries of the dedicated things:

^13Also for the courses of the priests and the Levites, and for all the work of the service of the house of the Lord, and for all the vessels of service in the house of the Lord.

^14He gave of gold by weight for things of gold, for all instruments of all manner of service; silver also for all instruments of silver by weight, for all instruments of every kind of service:

^15Even the weight for the candlesticks of gold, and for their lamps of gold, by weight for every candlestick, and for the lamps thereof: and for the candlesticks of silver by weight, both for the candlestick, and also for the lamps thereof, according to the use of every candlestick.

^16And by weight he gave gold for the tables of shewbread, for every table; and likewise silver for the tables of silver:

^17Also pure gold for the fleshhooks, and the bowls, and the cups: and for the golden basons he gave gold by weight for every bason; and likewise silver by weight for every bason of silver:

^18And for the altar of incense refined gold by weight; and gold for the pattern of the chariot of the cherubims, that spread out their wings, and covered the ark of the covenant of the Lord.

^19All this, said David, the Lord made me understand in writing by his hand upon me, even all the works of this pattern.

^20And David said to Solomon his son, Be strong and of good courage, and do it: fear not, nor be dismayed: for the Lord God, even my God, will be with thee; he will not fail thee, nor forsake thee, until thou hast finished all the work for the service of the house of the Lord.

^21And, behold, the courses of the priests and the Levites, even they shall be with thee for all the service of the house of God: and there shall be with thee for all manner of workmanship every willing skilful man, for any manner of service: also the princes and all the people will be wholly at thy commandment.

XXIX

29^1Furthermore David the king said unto all the congregation, Solomon my son, whom alone God hath chosen, is yet young and tender, and the work is great: for the palace is not for man, but for the Lord God.

^2Now I have prepared with all my might for the house of my God the gold for things to be made of gold, and the silver for things of silver, and the brass for things of brass, the iron for things of iron, and wood for things of wood; onyx stones, and stones to be set, glistering stones, and of divers colours, and all manner of precious stones, and marble stones in abundance.

^3Moreover, because I have set my affection to the house of my God, I have of mine own proper good, of gold and silver, which I have given to the house of my God, over and above all that I have prepared for the holy house.

^4Even three thousand talents of gold, of the gold of Ophir, and seven thousand talents of refined silver, to overlay the walls of the houses withal:

^5The gold for things of gold, and the silver for things of silver, and for all manner of work to be made by the hands of artificers. And who then is willing to consecrate his service this day unto the Lord?

^6Then the chief of the fathers and princes of the tribes of Israel and the captains of thousands and of hundreds, with the rulers of the king’s work, offered willingly,

^7And gave for the service of the house of God of gold five thousand talents and ten thousand drams, and of silver ten thousand talents, and of brass eighteen thousand talents, and one hundred thousand talents of iron.

^8And they with whom precious stones were found gave them to the treasure of the house of the Lord, by the hand of Jehiel the Gershonite.

^9Then the people rejoiced, for that they offered willingly, because with perfect heart they offered willingly to the Lord: and David the king also rejoiced with great joy.

^10Wherefore David blessed the Lord before all the congregation: and David said, Blessed be thou, Lord God of Israel our father, for ever and ever.

^11Thine, O Lord is the greatness, and the power, and the glory, and the victory, and the majesty: for all that is in the heaven and in the earth is thine; thine is the kingdom, O Lord, and thou art exalted as head above all.

^12Both riches and honour come of thee, and thou reignest over all; and in thine hand is power and might; and in thine hand it is to make great, and to give strength unto all.

^13Now therefore, our God, we thank thee, and praise thy glorious name.

^14But who am I, and what is my people, that we should be able to offer so willingly after this sort? for all things come of thee, and of thine own have we given thee.

^15For we are strangers before thee, and sojourners, as were all our fathers: our days on the earth are as a shadow, and there is none abiding.

^16O Lord our God, all this store that we have prepared to build thee an house for thine holy name cometh of thine hand, and is all thine own.

^17I know also, my God, that thou triest the heart, and hast pleasure in uprightness. As for me, in the uprightness of mine heart I have willingly offered all these things: and now have I seen with joy thy people, which are present here, to offer willingly unto thee.

^18O Lord God of Abraham, Isaac, and of Israel, our fathers, keep this for ever in the imagination of the thoughts of the heart of thy people, and prepare their heart unto thee:

^19And give unto Solomon my son a perfect heart, to keep thy commandments, thy testimonies, and thy statutes, and to do all these things, and to build the palace, for the which I have made provision.

^20And David said to all the congregation, Now bless the Lord your God. And all the congregation blessed the Lord God of their fathers, and bowed down their heads, and worshipped the Lord, and the king.

^21And they sacrificed sacrifices unto the Lord, and offered burnt offerings unto the Lord, on the morrow after that day, even a thousand bullocks, a thousand rams, and a thousand lambs, with their drink offerings, and sacrifices in abundance for all Israel:

^22And did eat and drink before the Lord on that day with great gladness. And they made Solomon the son of David king the second time, and anointed him unto the Lord to be the chief governor, and Zadok to be priest.

^23Then Solomon sat on the throne of the Lord as king instead of David his father, and prospered; and all Israel obeyed him.

^24And all the princes, and the mighty men, and all the sons likewise of king David, submitted themselves unto Solomon the king.

^25And the Lord magnified Solomon exceedingly in the sight of all Israel, and bestowed upon him such royal majesty as had not been on any king before him in Israel.

^26Thus David the son of Jesse reigned over all Israel.

^27And the time that he reigned over Israel was forty years; seven years reigned he in Hebron, and thirty and three years reigned he in Jerusalem.

^28And he died in a good old age, full of days, riches, and honour: and Solomon his son reigned in his stead.

^29Now the acts of David the king, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of Samuel the seer, and in the book of Nathan the prophet, and in the book of Gad the seer,

^30With all his reign and his might, and the times that went over him, and over Israel, and over all the kingdoms of the countries.

Ezra

The Book of

Ezra

I

1^1Now in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, that the word of the Lord by the mouth of Jeremiah might be fulfilled, the Lord stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, that he made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom, and put it also in writing, saying,

^2Thus saith Cyrus king of Persia, The Lord God of heaven hath given me all the kingdoms of the earth; and he hath charged me to build him an house at Jerusalem, which is in Judah.

^3Who is there among you of all his people? his God be with him, and let him go up to Jerusalem, which is in Judah, and build the house of the Lord God of Israel, (he is the God,) which is in Jerusalem.

^4And whosoever remaineth in any place where he sojourneth, let the men of his place help him with silver, and with gold, and with goods, and with beasts, beside the freewill offering for the house of God that is in Jerusalem.

^5Then rose up the chief of the fathers of Judah and Benjamin, and the priests, and the Levites, with all them whose spirit God had raised, to go up to build the house of the Lord which is in Jerusalem.

^6And all they that were about them strengthened their hands with vessels of silver, with gold, with goods, and with beasts, and with precious things, beside all that was willingly offered.

^7Also Cyrus the king brought forth the vessels of the house of the Lord, which Nebuchadnezzar had brought forth out of Jerusalem, and had put them in the house of his gods;

^8Even those did Cyrus king of Persia bring forth by the hand of Mithredath the treasurer, and numbered them unto Sheshbazzar, the prince of Judah.

^9And this is the number of them: thirty chargers of gold, a thousand chargers of silver, nine and twenty knives,

^10Thirty basons of gold, silver basons of a second sort four hundred and ten, and other vessels a thousand.

^11All the vessels of gold and of silver were five thousand and four hundred. All these did Sheshbazzar bring up with them of the captivity that were brought up from Babylon unto Jerusalem.

II

2^1Now these are the children of the province that went up out of the captivity, of those which had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away unto Babylon, and came again unto Jerusalem and Judah, every one unto his city;

^2Which came with Zerubbabel: Jeshua, Nehemiah, Seraiah, Reelaiah, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mizpar, Bigvai, Rehum, Baanah. The number of the men of the people of Israel:

^3The children of Parosh, two thousand an hundred seventy and two.

^4The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy and two.

^5The children of Arah, seven hundred seventy and five.

^6The children of Pahathmoab, of the children of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand eight hundred and twelve.

^7The children of Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four.

^8The children of Zattu, nine hundred forty and five.

^9The children of Zaccai, seven hundred and threescore.

^10The children of Bani, six hundred forty and two.

^11The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty and three.

^12The children of Azgad, a thousand two hundred twenty and two.

^13The children of Adonikam, six hundred sixty and six.

^14The children of Bigvai, two thousand fifty and six.

^15The children of Adin, four hundred fifty and four.

^16The children of Ater of Hezekiah, ninety and eight.

^17The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty and three.

^18The children of Jorah, an hundred and twelve.

^19The children of Hashum, two hundred twenty and three.

^20The children of Gibbar, ninety and five.

^21The children of Bethlehem, an hundred twenty and three.

^22The men of Netophah, fifty and six.

^23The men of Anathoth, an hundred twenty and eight.

^24The children of Azmaveth, forty and two.

^25The children of Kirjatharim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred and forty and three.

^26The children of Ramah and Gaba, six hundred twenty and one.

^27The men of Michmas, an hundred twenty and two.

^28The men of Bethel and Ai, two hundred twenty and three.

^29The children of Nebo, fifty and two.

^30The children of Magbish, an hundred fifty and six.

^31The children of the other Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four.

^32The children of Harim, three hundred and twenty.

^33The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty and five.

^34The children of Jericho, three hundred forty and five.

^35The children of Senaah, three thousand and six hundred and thirty.

^36The priests: the children of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy and three.

^37The children of Immer, a thousand fifty and two.

^38The children of Pashur, a thousand two hundred forty and seven.

^39The children of Harim, a thousand and seventeen.

^40The Levites: the children of Jeshua and Kadmiel, of the children of Hodaviah, seventy and four.

^41The singers: the children of Asaph, an hundred twenty and eight.

^42The children of the porters: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, in all an hundred thirty and nine.

^43The Nethinims: the children of Ziha, the children of Hasupha, the children of Tabbaoth,

^44The children of Keros, the children of Siaha, the children of Padon,

^45The children of Lebanah, the children of Hagabah, the children of Akkub,

^46The children of Hagab, the children of Shalmai, the children of Hanan,

^47The children of Giddel, the children of Gahar, the children of Reaiah,

^48The children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda, the children of Gazzam,

^49The children of Uzza, the children of Paseah, the children of Besai,

^50The children of Asnah, the children of Mehunim, the children of Nephusim,

^51The children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur,

^52The children of Bazluth, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha,

^53The children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Thamah,

^54The children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.

^55The children of Solomon’s servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Sophereth, the children of Peruda,

^56The children of Jaalah, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel,

^57The children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth of Zebaim, the children of Ami.

^58All the Nethinims, and the children of Solomon’s servants, were three hundred ninety and two.

^59And these were they which went up from Telmelah, Telharsa, Cherub, Addan, and Immer: but they could not shew their father’s house, and their seed, whether they were of Israel:

^60The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred fifty and two.

^61And of the children of the priests: the children of Habaiah, the children of Koz, the children of Barzillai; which took a wife of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite, and was called after their name:

^62These sought their register among those that were reckoned by genealogy, but they were not found: therefore were they, as polluted, put from the priesthood.

^63And the Tirshatha said unto them, that they should not eat of the most holy things, till there stood up a priest with Urim and with Thummim.

^64The whole congregation together was forty and two thousand three hundred and threescore,

^65Beside their servants and their maids, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred thirty and seven: and there were among them two hundred singing men and singing women.

^66Their horses were seven hundred thirty and six; their mules, two hundred forty and five;

^67Their camels, four hundred thirty and five; their asses, six thousand seven hundred and twenty.

^68And some of the chief of the fathers, when they came to the house of the Lord which is at Jerusalem, offered freely for the house of God to set it up in his place:

^69They gave after their ability unto the treasure of the work threescore and one thousand drams of gold, and five thousand pound of silver, and one hundred priests’ garments.

^70So the priests, and the Levites, and some of the people, and the singers, and the porters, and the Nethinims, dwelt in their cities, and all Israel in their cities.

III

3^1And when the seventh month was come, and the children of Israel were in the cities, the people gathered themselves together as one man to Jerusalem.

^2Then stood up Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and his brethren the priests, and Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and his brethren, and builded the altar of the God of Israel, to offer burnt offerings thereon, as it is written in the law of Moses the man of God.

^3And they set the altar upon his bases; for fear was upon them because of the people of those countries: and they offered burnt offerings thereon unto the Lord, even burnt offerings morning and evening.

^4They kept also the feast of tabernacles, as it is written, and offered the daily burnt offerings by number, according to the custom, as the duty of every day required;

^5And afterward offered the continual burnt offering, both of the new moons, and of all the set feasts of the Lord that were consecrated, and of every one that willingly offered a freewill offering unto the Lord.

^6From the first day of the seventh month began they to offer burnt offerings unto the Lord. But the foundation of the temple of the Lord was not yet laid.

^7They gave money also unto the masons, and to the carpenters; and meat, and drink, and oil, unto them of Zidon, and to them of Tyre, to bring cedar trees from Lebanon to the sea of Joppa, according to the grant that they had of Cyrus king of Persia.

^8Now in the second year of their coming unto the house of God at Jerusalem, in the second month, began Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and the remnant of their brethren the priests and the Levites, and all they that were come out of the captivity unto Jerusalem; and appointed the Levites, from twenty years old and upward, to set forward the work of the house of the Lord.

^9Then stood Jeshua with his sons and his brethren, Kadmiel and his sons, the sons of Judah, together, to set forward the workmen in the house of God: the sons of Henadad, with their sons and their brethren the Levites.

^10And when the builders laid the foundation of the temple of the Lord, they set the priests in their apparel with trumpets, and the Levites the sons of Asaph with cymbals, to praise the Lord, after the ordinance of David king of Israel.

^11And they sang together by course in praising and giving thanks unto the Lord; because he is good, for his mercy endureth for ever toward Israel. And all the people shouted with a great shout, when they praised the Lord, because the foundation of the house of the Lord was laid.

^12But many of the priests and Levites and chief of the fathers, who were ancient men, that had seen the first house, when the foundation of this house was laid before their eyes, wept with a loud voice; and many shouted aloud for joy:

^13So that the people could not discern the noise of the shout of joy from the noise of the weeping of the people: for the people shouted with a loud shout, and the noise was heard afar off.

IV

4^1Now when the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin heard that the children of the captivity builded the temple unto the Lord God of Israel;

^2Then they came to Zerubbabel, and to the chief of the fathers, and said unto them, Let us build with you: for we seek your God, as ye do; and we do sacrifice unto him since the days of Esarhaddon king of Assur, which brought us up hither.

^3But Zerubbabel, and Jeshua, and the rest of the chief of the fathers of Israel, said unto them, Ye have nothing to do with us to build an house unto our God; but we ourselves together will build unto the Lord God of Israel, as king Cyrus the king of Persia hath commanded us.

^4Then the people of the land weakened the hands of the people of Judah, and troubled them in building,

^5And hired counsellors against them, to frustrate their purpose, all the days of Cyrus king of Persia, even until the reign of Darius king of Persia.

^6And in the reign of Ahasuerus, in the beginning of his reign, wrote they unto him an accusation against the inhabitants of Judah and Jerusalem.

^7And in the days of Artaxerxes wrote Bishlam, Mithredath, Tabeel, and the rest of their companions, unto Artaxerxes king of Persia; and the writing of the letter was written in the Syrian tongue, and interpreted in the Syrian tongue.

^8Rehum the chancellor and Shimshai the scribe wrote a letter against Jerusalem to Artaxerxes the king in this sort:

^9Then wrote Rehum the chancellor, and Shimshai the scribe, and the rest of their companions; the Dinaites, the Apharsathchites, the Tarpelites, the Apharsites, the Archevites, the Babylonians, the Susanchites, the Dehavites, and the Elamites,

^10And the rest of the nations whom the great and noble Asnapper brought over, and set in the cities of Samaria, and the rest that are on this side the river, and at such a time.

^11This is the copy of the letter that they sent unto him, even unto Artaxerxes the king; Thy servants the men on this side the river, and at such a time.

^12Be it known unto the king, that the Jews which came up from thee to us are come unto Jerusalem, building the rebellious and the bad city, and have set up the walls thereof, and joined the foundations.

^13Be it known now unto the king, that, if this city be builded, and the walls set up again, then will they not pay toll, tribute, and custom, and so thou shalt endamage the revenue of the kings.

^14Now because we have maintenance from the king’s palace, and it was not meet for us to see the king’s dishonour, therefore have we sent and certified the king;

^15That search may be made in the book of the records of thy fathers: so shalt thou find in the book of the records, and know that this city is a rebellious city, and hurtful unto kings and provinces, and that they have moved sedition within the same of old time: for which cause was this city destroyed.

^16We certify the king that, if this city be builded again, and the walls thereof set up, by this means thou shalt have no portion on this side the river.

^17Then sent the king an answer unto Rehum the chancellor, and to Shimshai the scribe, and to the rest of their companions that dwell in Samaria, and unto the rest beyond the river, Peace, and at such a time.

^18The letter which ye sent unto us hath been plainly read before me.

^19And I commanded, and search hath been made, and it is found that this city of old time hath made insurrection against kings, and that rebellion and sedition have been made therein.

^20There have been mighty kings also over Jerusalem, which have ruled over all countries beyond the river; and toll, tribute, and custom, was paid unto them.

^21Give ye now commandment to cause these men to cease, and that this city be not builded, until another commandment shall be given from me.

^22Take heed now that ye fail not to do this: why should damage grow to the hurt of the kings?

^23Now when the copy of king Artaxerxes’ letter was read before Rehum, and Shimshai the scribe, and their companions, they went up in haste to Jerusalem unto the Jews, and made them to cease by force and power.

^24Then ceased the work of the house of God which is at Jerusalem. So it ceased unto the second year of the reign of Darius king of Persia.

V

5^1Then the prophets, Haggai the prophet, and Zechariah the son of Iddo, prophesied unto the Jews that were in Judah and Jerusalem in the name of the God of Israel, even unto them.

^2Then rose up Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and began to build the house of God which is at Jerusalem: and with them were the prophets of God helping them.

^3At the same time came to them Tatnai, governor on this side the river, and Shetharboznai and their companions, and said thus unto them, Who hath commanded you to build this house, and to make up this wall?

^4Then said we unto them after this manner, What are the names of the men that make this building?

^5But the eye of their God was upon the elders of the Jews, that they could not cause them to cease, till the matter came to Darius: and then they returned answer by letter concerning this matter.

^6The copy of the letter that Tatnai, governor on this side the river, and Shetharboznai and his companions the Apharsachites, which were on this side the river, sent unto Darius the king:

^7They sent a letter unto him, wherein was written thus; Unto Darius the king, all peace.

^8Be it known unto the king, that we went into the province of Judea, to the house of the great God, which is builded with great stones, and timber is laid in the walls, and this work goeth fast on, and prospereth in their hands.

^9Then asked we those elders, and said unto them thus, Who commanded you to build this house, and to make up these walls?

^10We asked their names also, to certify thee, that we might write the names of the men that were the chief of them.

^11And thus they returned us answer, saying, We are the servants of the God of heaven and earth, and build the house that was builded these many years ago, which a great king of Israel builded and set up.

^12But after that our fathers had provoked the God of heaven unto wrath, he gave them into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, the Chaldean, who destroyed this house, and carried the people away into Babylon.

^13But in the first year of Cyrus the king of Babylon the same king Cyrus made a decree to build this house of God.

^14And the vessels also of gold and silver of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took out of the temple that was in Jerusalem, and brought them into the temple of Babylon, those did Cyrus the king take out of the temple of Babylon, and they were delivered unto one, whose name was Sheshbazzar, whom he had made governor;

^15And said unto him, Take these vessels, go, carry them into the temple that is in Jerusalem, and let the house of God be builded in his place.

^16Then came the same Sheshbazzar, and laid the foundation of the house of God which is in Jerusalem: and since that time even until now hath it been in building, and yet it is not finished.

^17Now therefore, if it seem good to the king, let there be search made in the king’s treasure house, which is there at Babylon, whether it be so, that a decree was made of Cyrus the king to build this house of God at Jerusalem, and let the king send his pleasure to us concerning this matter.

VI

6^1Then Darius the king made a decree, and search was made in the house of the rolls, where the treasures were laid up in Babylon.

^2And there was found at Achmetha, in the palace that is in the province of the Medes, a roll, and therein was a record thus written:

^3In the first year of Cyrus the king the same Cyrus the king made a decree concerning the house of God at Jerusalem, Let the house be builded, the place where they offered sacrifices, and let the foundations thereof be strongly laid; the height thereof threescore cubits, and the breadth thereof threescore cubits;

^4With three rows of great stones, and a row of new timber: and let the expenses be given out of the king’s house:

^5And also let the golden and silver vessels of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took forth out of the temple which is at Jerusalem, and brought unto Babylon, be restored, and brought again unto the temple which is at Jerusalem, every one to his place, and place them in the house of God.

^6Now therefore, Tatnai, governor beyond the river, Shetharboznai, and your companions the Apharsachites, which are beyond the river, be ye far from thence:

^7Let the work of this house of God alone; let the governor of the Jews and the elders of the Jews build this house of God in his place.

^8Moreover I make a decree what ye shall do to the elders of these Jews for the building of this house of God: that of the king’s goods, even of the tribute beyond the river, forthwith expenses be given unto these men, that they be not hindered.

^9And that which they have need of, both young bullocks, and rams, and lambs, for the burnt offerings of the God of heaven, wheat, salt, wine, and oil, according to the appointment of the priests which are at Jerusalem, let it be given them day by day without fail:

^10That they may offer sacrifices of sweet savours unto the God of heaven, and pray for the life of the king, and of his sons.

^11Also I have made a decree, that whosoever shall alter this word, let timber be pulled down from his house, and being set up, let him be hanged thereon; and let his house be made a dunghill for this.

^12And the God that hath caused his name to dwell there destroy all kings and people, that shall put to their hand to alter and to destroy this house of God which is at Jerusalem. I Darius have made a decree; let it be done with speed.

^13Then Tatnai, governor on this side the river, Shetharboznai, and their companions, according to that which Darius the king had sent, so they did speedily.

^14And the elders of the Jews builded, and they prospered through the prophesying of Haggai the prophet and Zechariah the son of Iddo. And they builded, and finished it, according to the commandment of the God of Israel, and according to the commandment of Cyrus, and Darius, and Artaxerxes king of Persia.

^15And this house was finished on the third day of the month Adar, which was in the sixth year of the reign of Darius the king.

^16And the children of Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the rest of the children of the captivity, kept the dedication of this house of God with joy.

^17And offered at the dedication of this house of God an hundred bullocks, two hundred rams, four hundred lambs; and for a sin offering for all Israel, twelve he goats, according to the number of the tribes of Israel.

^18And they set the priests in their divisions, and the Levites in their courses, for the service of God, which is at Jerusalem; as it is written in the book of Moses.

^19And the children of the captivity kept the passover upon the fourteenth day of the first month.

^20For the priests and the Levites were purified together, all of them were pure, and killed the passover for all the children of the captivity, and for their brethren the priests, and for themselves.

^21And the children of Israel, which were come again out of captivity, and all such as had separated themselves unto them from the filthiness of the heathen of the land, to seek the Lord God of Israel, did eat,

^22And kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days with joy: for the Lord had made them joyful, and turned the heart of the king of Assyria unto them, to strengthen their hands in the work of the house of God, the God of Israel.

VII

7^1Now after these things, in the reign of Artaxerxes king of Persia, Ezra the son of Seraiah, the son of Azariah, the son of Hilkiah,

^2The son of Shallum, the son of Zadok, the son of Ahitub,

^3The son of Amariah, the son of Azariah, the son of Meraioth,

^4The son of Zerahiah, the son of Uzzi, the son of Bukki,

^5The son of Abishua, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the chief priest:

^6This Ezra went up from Babylon; and he was a ready scribe in the law of Moses, which the Lord God of Israel had given: and the king granted him all his request, according to the hand of the Lord his God upon him.

^7And there went up some of the children of Israel, and of the priests, and the Levites, and the singers, and the porters, and the Nethinims, unto Jerusalem, in the seventh year of Artaxerxes the king.

^8And he came to Jerusalem in the fifth month, which was in the seventh year of the king.

^9For upon the first day of the first month began he to go up from Babylon, and on the first day of the fifth month came he to Jerusalem, according to the good hand of his God upon him.

^10For Ezra had prepared his heart to seek the law of the Lord, and to do it, and to teach in Israel statutes and judgments.

^11Now this is the copy of the letter that the king Artaxerxes gave unto Ezra the priest, the scribe, even a scribe of the words of the commandments of the Lord, and of his statutes to Israel.

^12Artaxerxes, king of kings, unto Ezra the priest, a scribe of the law of the God of heaven, perfect peace, and at such a time.

^13I make a decree, that all they of the people of Israel, and of his priests and Levites, in my realm, which are minded of their own freewill to go up to Jerusalem, go with thee.

^14Forasmuch as thou art sent of the king, and of his seven counsellors, to enquire concerning Judah and Jerusalem, according to the law of thy God which is in thine hand;

^15And to carry the silver and gold, which the king and his counsellors have freely offered unto the God of Israel, whose habitation is in Jerusalem,

^16And all the silver and gold that thou canst find in all the province of Babylon, with the freewill offering of the people, and of the priests, offering willingly for the house of their God which is in Jerusalem:

^17That thou mayest buy speedily with this money bullocks, rams, lambs, with their meat offerings and their drink offerings, and offer them upon the altar of the house of your God which is in Jerusalem.

^18And whatsoever shall seem good to thee, and to thy brethren, to do with the rest of the silver and the gold, that do after the will of your God.

^19The vessels also that are given thee for the service of the house of thy God, those deliver thou before the God of Jerusalem.

^20And whatsoever more shall be needful for the house of thy God, which thou shalt have occasion to bestow, bestow it out of the king’s treasure house.

^21And I, even I Artaxerxes the king, do make a decree to all the treasurers which are beyond the river, that whatsoever Ezra the priest, the scribe of the law of the God of heaven, shall require of you, it be done speedily,

^22Unto an hundred talents of silver, and to an hundred measures of wheat, and to an hundred baths of wine, and to an hundred baths of oil, and salt without prescribing how much.

^23Whatsoever is commanded by the God of heaven, let it be diligently done for the house of the God of heaven: for why should there be wrath against the realm of the king and his sons?

^24Also we certify you, that touching any of the priests and Levites, singers, porters, Nethinims, or ministers of this house of God, it shall not be lawful to impose toll, tribute, or custom, upon them.

^25And thou, Ezra, after the wisdom of thy God, that is in thine hand, set magistrates and judges, which may judge all the people that are beyond the river, all such as know the laws of thy God; and teach ye them that know them not.

^26And whosoever will not do the law of thy God, and the law of the king, let judgment be executed speedily upon him, whether it be unto death, or to banishment, or to confiscation of goods, or to imprisonment.

^27Blessed be the Lord God of our fathers, which hath put such a thing as this in the king’s heart, to beautify the house of the Lord which is in Jerusalem:

^28And hath extended mercy unto me before the king, and his counsellors, and before all the king’s mighty princes. And I was strengthened as the hand of the Lord my God was upon me, and I gathered together out of Israel chief men to go up with me.

VIII

8^1These are now the chief of their fathers, and this is the genealogy of them that went up with me from Babylon, in the reign of Artaxerxes the king.

^2Of the sons of Phinehas; Gershom: of the sons of Ithamar; Daniel: of the sons of David; Hattush.

^3Of the sons of Shechaniah, of the sons of Pharosh; Zechariah: and with him were reckoned by genealogy of the males an hundred and fifty.

^4Of the sons of Pahathmoab; Elihoenai the son of Zerahiah, and with him two hundred males.

^5Of the sons of Shechaniah; the son of Jahaziel, and with him three hundred males.

^6Of the sons also of Adin; Ebed the son of Jonathan, and with him fifty males.

^7And of the sons of Elam; Jeshaiah the son of Athaliah, and with him seventy males.

^8And of the sons of Shephatiah; Zebadiah the son of Michael, and with him fourscore males.

^9Of the sons of Joab; Obadiah the son of Jehiel, and with him two hundred and eighteen males.

^10And of the sons of Shelomith; the son of Josiphiah, and with him an hundred and threescore males.

^11And of the sons of Bebai; Zechariah the son of Bebai, and with him twenty and eight males.

^12And of the sons of Azgad; Johanan the son of Hakkatan, and with him an hundred and ten males.

^13And of the last sons of Adonikam, whose names are these, Eliphelet, Jeiel, and Shemaiah, and with them threescore males.

^14Of the sons also of Bigvai; Uthai, and Zabbud, and with them seventy males.

^15And I gathered them together to the river that runneth to Ahava; and there abode we in tents three days: and I viewed the people, and the priests, and found there none of the sons of Levi.

^16Then sent I for Eliezer, for Ariel, for Shemaiah, and for Elnathan, and for Jarib, and for Elnathan, and for Nathan, and for Zechariah, and for Meshullam, chief men; also for Joiarib, and for Elnathan, men of understanding.

^17And I sent them with commandment unto Iddo the chief at the place Casiphia, and I told them what they should say unto Iddo, and to his brethren the Nethinims, at the place Casiphia, that they should bring unto us ministers for the house of our God.

^18And by the good hand of our God upon us they brought us a man of understanding, of the sons of Mahli, the son of Levi, the son of Israel; and Sherebiah, with his sons and his brethren, eighteen;

^19And Hashabiah, and with him Jeshaiah of the sons of Merari, his brethren and their sons, twenty;

^20Also of the Nethinims, whom David and the princes had appointed for the service of the Levites, two hundred and twenty Nethinims: all of them were expressed by name.

^21Then I proclaimed a fast there, at the river of Ahava, that we might afflict ourselves before our God, to seek of him a right way for us, and for our little ones, and for all our substance.

^22For I was ashamed to require of the king a band of soldiers and horsemen to help us against the enemy in the way: because we had spoken unto the king, saying, The hand of our God is upon all them for good that seek him; but his power and his wrath is against all them that forsake him.

^23So we fasted and besought our God for this: and he was intreated of us.

^24Then I separated twelve of the chief of the priests, Sherebiah, Hashabiah, and ten of their brethren with them,

^25And weighed unto them the silver, and the gold, and the vessels, even the offering of the house of our God, which the king, and his counsellors, and his lords, and all Israel there present, had offered:

^26I even weighed unto their hand six hundred and fifty talents of silver, and silver vessels an hundred talents, and of gold an hundred talents;

^27Also twenty basons of gold, of a thousand drams; and two vessels of fine copper, precious as gold.

^28And I said unto them, Ye are holy unto the Lord; the vessels are holy also; and the silver and the gold are a freewill offering unto the Lord God of your fathers.

^29Watch ye, and keep them, until ye weigh them before the chief of the priests and the Levites, and chief of the fathers of Israel, at Jerusalem, in the chambers of the house of the Lord.

^30So took the priests and the Levites the weight of the silver, and the gold, and the vessels, to bring them to Jerusalem unto the house of our God.

^31Then we departed from the river of Ahava on the twelfth day of the first month, to go unto Jerusalem: and the hand of our God was upon us, and he delivered us from the hand of the enemy, and of such as lay in wait by the way.

^32And we came to Jerusalem, and abode there three days.

^33Now on the fourth day was the silver and the gold and the vessels weighed in the house of our God by the hand of Meremoth the son of Uriah the priest; and with him was Eleazar the son of Phinehas; and with them was Jozabad the son of Jeshua, and Noadiah the son of Binnui, Levites;

^34By number and by weight of every one: and all the weight was written at that time.

^35Also the children of those that had been carried away, which were come out of the captivity, offered burnt offerings unto the God of Israel, twelve bullocks for all Israel, ninety and six rams, seventy and seven lambs, twelve he goats for a sin offering: all this was a burnt offering unto the Lord.

^36And they delivered the king’s commissions unto the king’s lieutenants, and to the governors on this side the river: and they furthered the people, and the house of God.

IX

9^1Now when these things were done, the princes came to me, saying, The people of Israel, and the priests, and the Levites, have not separated themselves from the people of the lands, doing according to their abominations, even of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Jebusites, the Ammonites, the Moabites, the Egyptians, and the Amorites.

^2For they have taken of their daughters for themselves, and for their sons: so that the holy seed have mingled themselves with the people of those lands: yea, the hand of the princes and rulers hath been chief in this trespass.

^3And when I heard this thing, I rent my garment and my mantle, and plucked off the hair of my head and of my beard, and sat down astonied.

^4Then were assembled unto me every one that trembled at the words of the God of Israel, because of the transgression of those that had been carried away; and I sat astonied until the evening sacrifice.

^5And at the evening sacrifice I arose up from my heaviness; and having rent my garment and my mantle, I fell upon my knees, and spread out my hands unto the Lord my God,

^6And said, O my God, I am ashamed and blush to lift up my face to thee, my God: for our iniquities are increased over our head, and our trespass is grown up unto the heavens.

^7Since the days of our fathers have we been in a great trespass unto this day; and for our iniquities have we, our kings, and our priests, been delivered into the hand of the kings of the lands, to the sword, to captivity, and to a spoil, and to confusion of face, as it is this day.

^8And now for a little space grace hath been shewed from the Lord our God, to leave us a remnant to escape, and to give us a nail in his holy place, that our God may lighten our eyes, and give us a little reviving in our bondage.

^9For we were bondmen; yet our God hath not forsaken us in our bondage, but hath extended mercy unto us in the sight of the kings of Persia, to give us a reviving, to set up the house of our God, and to repair the desolations thereof, and to give us a wall in Judah and in Jerusalem.

^10And now, O our God, what shall we say after this? for we have forsaken thy commandments,

^11Which thou hast commanded by thy servants the prophets, saying, The land, unto which ye go to possess it, is an unclean land with the filthiness of the people of the lands, with their abominations, which have filled it from one end to another with their uncleanness.

^12Now therefore give not your daughters unto their sons, neither take their daughters unto your sons, nor seek their peace or their wealth for ever: that ye may be strong, and eat the good of the land, and leave it for an inheritance to your children for ever.

^13And after all that is come upon us for our evil deeds, and for our great trespass, seeing that thou our God hast punished us less than our iniquities deserve, and hast given us such deliverance as this;

^14Should we again break thy commandments, and join in affinity with the people of these abominations? wouldest not thou be angry with us till thou hadst consumed us, so that there should be no remnant nor escaping?

^15O Lord God of Israel, thou art righteous: for we remain yet escaped, as it is this day: behold, we are before thee in our trespasses: for we cannot stand before thee because of this.

X

10^1Now when Ezra had prayed, and when he had confessed, weeping and casting himself down before the house of God, there assembled unto him out of Israel a very great congregation of men and women and children: for the people wept very sore.

^2And Shechaniah the son of Jehiel, one of the sons of Elam, answered and said unto Ezra, We have trespassed against our God, and have taken strange wives of the people of the land: yet now there is hope in Israel concerning this thing.

^3Now therefore let us make a covenant with our God to put away all the wives, and such as are born of them, according to the counsel of my lord, and of those that tremble at the commandment of our God; and let it be done according to the law.

^4Arise; for this matter belongeth unto thee: we also will be with thee: be of good courage, and do it.

^5Then arose Ezra, and made the chief priests, the Levites, and all Israel, to swear that they should do according to this word. And they sware.

^6Then Ezra rose up from before the house of God, and went into the chamber of Johanan the son of Eliashib: and when he came thither, he did eat no bread, nor drink water: for he mourned because of the transgression of them that had been carried away.

^7And they made proclamation throughout Judah and Jerusalem unto all the children of the captivity, that they should gather themselves together unto Jerusalem;

^8And that whosoever would not come within three days, according to the counsel of the princes and the elders, all his substance should be forfeited, and himself separated from the congregation of those that had been carried away.

^9Then all the men of Judah and Benjamin gathered themselves together unto Jerusalem within three days. It was the ninth month, on the twentieth day of the month; and all the people sat in the street of the house of God, trembling because of this matter, and for the great rain.

^10And Ezra the priest stood up, and said unto them, Ye have transgressed, and have taken strange wives, to increase the trespass of Israel.

^11Now therefore make confession unto the Lord God of your fathers, and do his pleasure: and separate yourselves from the people of the land, and from the strange wives.

^12Then all the congregation answered and said with a loud voice, As thou hast said, so must we do.

^13But the people are many, and it is a time of much rain, and we are not able to stand without, neither is this a work of one day or two: for we are many that have transgressed in this thing.

^14Let now our rulers of all the congregation stand, and let all them which have taken strange wives in our cities come at appointed times, and with them the elders of every city, and the judges thereof, until the fierce wrath of our God for this matter be turned from us.

^15Only Jonathan the son of Asahel and Jahaziah the son of Tikvah were employed about this matter: and Meshullam and Shabbethai the Levite helped them.

^16And the children of the captivity did so. And Ezra the priest, with certain chief of the fathers, after the house of their fathers, and all of them by their names, were separated, and sat down in the first day of the tenth month to examine the matter.

^17And they made an end with all the men that had taken strange wives by the first day of the first month.

^18And among the sons of the priests there were found that had taken strange wives: namely, of the sons of Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and his brethren; Maaseiah, and Eliezer, and Jarib, and Gedaliah.

^19And they gave their hands that they would put away their wives; and being guilty, they offered a ram of the flock for their trespass.

^20And of the sons of Immer; Hanani, and Zebadiah.

^21And of the sons of Harim; Maaseiah, and Elijah, and Shemaiah, and Jehiel, and Uzziah.

^22And of the sons of Pashur; Elioenai, Maaseiah, Ishmael, Nethaneel, Jozabad, and Elasah.

^23Also of the Levites; Jozabad, and Shimei, and Kelaiah, (the same is Kelita,) Pethahiah, Judah, and Eliezer.

^24Of the singers also; Eliashib: and of the porters; Shallum, and Telem, and Uri.

^25Moreover of Israel: of the sons of Parosh; Ramiah, and Jeziah, and Malchiah, and Miamin, and Eleazar, and Malchijah, and Benaiah.

^26And of the sons of Elam; Mattaniah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, and Abdi, and Jeremoth, and Eliah.

^27And of the sons of Zattu; Elioenai, Eliashib, Mattaniah, and Jeremoth, and Zabad, and Aziza.

^28Of the sons also of Bebai; Jehohanan, Hananiah, Zabbai, and Athlai.

^29And of the sons of Bani; Meshullam, Malluch, and Adaiah, Jashub, and Sheal, and Ramoth.

^30And of the sons of Pahathmoab; Adna, and Chelal, Benaiah, Maaseiah, Mattaniah, Bezaleel, and Binnui, and Manasseh.

^31And of the sons of Harim; Eliezer, Ishijah, Malchiah, Shemaiah, Shimeon,

^32Benjamin, Malluch, and Shemariah.

^33Of the sons of Hashum; Mattenai, Mattathah, Zabad, Eliphelet, Jeremai, Manasseh, and Shimei.

^34Of the sons of Bani; Maadai, Amram, and Uel,

^35Benaiah, Bedeiah, Chelluh,

^36Vaniah, Meremoth, Eliashib,

^37Mattaniah, Mattenai, and Jaasau,

^38And Bani, and Binnui, Shimei,

^39And Shelemiah, and Nathan, and Adaiah,

^40Machnadebai, Shashai, Sharai,

^41Azareel, and Shelemiah, Shemariah,

^42Shallum, Amariah, and Joseph.

^43Of the sons of Nebo; Jeiel, Mattithiah, Zabad, Zebina, Jadau, and Joel, Benaiah.

^44All these had taken strange wives: and some of them had wives by whom they had children.

Nehemiah

The Book of

Nehemiah

I

^1The words of Nehemiah the son of Hachaliah. And it came to pass in the month Chisleu, in the twentieth year, as I was in Shushan the palace,

^2That Hanani, one of my brethren, came, he and certain men of Judah; and I asked them concerning the Jews that had escaped, which were left of the captivity, and concerning Jerusalem.

^3And they said unto me, The remnant that are left of the captivity there in the province are in great affliction and reproach: the wall of Jerusalem also is broken down, and the gates thereof are burned with fire.

^4And it came to pass, when I heard these words, that I sat down and wept, and mourned certain days, and fasted, and prayed before the God of heaven,

^5And said, I beseech thee, O Lord God of heaven, the great and terrible God, that keepeth covenant and mercy for them that love him and observe his commandments:

^6Let thine ear now be attentive, and thine eyes open, that thou mayest hear the prayer of thy servant, which I pray before thee now, day and night, for the children of Israel thy servants, and confess the sins of the children of Israel, which we have sinned against thee: both I and my father’s house have sinned.

^7We have dealt very corruptly against thee, and have not kept the commandments, nor the statutes, nor the judgments, which thou commandedst thy servant Moses.

^8Remember, I beseech thee, the word that thou commandedst thy servant Moses, saying, If ye transgress, I will scatter you abroad among the nations:

^9But if ye turn unto me, and keep my commandments, and do them; though there were of you cast out unto the uttermost part of the heaven, yet will I gather them from thence, and will bring them unto the place that I have chosen to set my name there.

^10Now these are thy servants and thy people, whom thou hast redeemed by thy great power, and by thy strong hand.

^11O Lord, I beseech thee, let now thine ear be attentive to the prayer of thy servant, and to the prayer of thy servants, who desire to fear thy name: and prosper, I pray thee, thy servant this day, and grant him mercy in the sight of this man. For I was the king’s cupbearer.

II

^1And it came to pass in the month Nisan, in the twentieth year of Artaxerxes the king, that wine was before him: and I took up the wine, and gave it unto the king. Now I had not been beforetime sad in his presence.

^2Wherefore the king said unto me, Why is thy countenance sad, seeing thou art not sick? this is nothing else but sorrow of heart. Then I was very sore afraid,

^3And said unto the king, Let the king live for ever: why should not my countenance be sad, when the city, the place of my fathers’ sepulchres, lieth waste, and the gates thereof are consumed with fire?

^4Then the king said unto me, For what dost thou make request? So I prayed to the God of heaven.

^5And I said unto the king, If it please the king, and if thy servant have found favour in thy sight, that thou wouldest send me unto Judah, unto the city of my fathers’ sepulchres, that I may build it.

^6And the king said unto me, (the queen also sitting by him,) For how long shall thy journey be? and when wilt thou return? So it pleased the king to send me; and I set him a time.

^7Moreover I said unto the king, If it please the king, let letters be given me to the governors beyond the river, that they may convey me over till I come into Judah;

^8And a letter unto Asaph the keeper of the king’s forest, that he may give me timber to make beams for the gates of the palace which appertained to the house, and for the wall of the city, and for the house that I shall enter into. And the king granted me, according to the good hand of my God upon me.

^9Then I came to the governors beyond the river, and gave them the king’s letters. Now the king had sent captains of the army and horsemen with me.

^10When Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, heard of it, it grieved them exceedingly that there was come a man to seek the welfare of the children of Israel.

^11So I came to Jerusalem, and was there three days.

^12And I arose in the night, I and some few men with me; neither told I any man what my God had put in my heart to do at Jerusalem: neither was there any beast with me, save the beast that I rode upon.

^13And I went out by night by the gate of the valley, even before the dragon well, and to the dung port, and viewed the walls of Jerusalem, which were broken down, and the gates thereof were consumed with fire.

^14Then I went on to the gate of the fountain, and to the king’s pool: but there was no place for the beast that was under me to pass.

^15Then went I up in the night by the brook, and viewed the wall, and turned back, and entered by the gate of the valley, and so returned.

^16And the rulers knew not whither I went, or what I did; neither had I as yet told it to the Jews, nor to the priests, nor to the nobles, nor to the rulers, nor to the rest that did the work.

^17Then said I unto them, Ye see the distress that we are in, how Jerusalem lieth waste, and the gates thereof are burned with fire: come, and let us build up the wall of Jerusalem, that we be no more a reproach.

^18Then I told them of the hand of my God which was good upon me; as also the king’s words that he had spoken unto me. And they said, Let us rise up and build. So they strengthened their hands for this good work.

^19But when Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, and Geshem the Arabian, heard it, they laughed us to scorn, and despised us, and said, What is this thing that ye do? will ye rebel against the king?

^20Then answered I them, and said unto them, The God of heaven, he will prosper us; therefore we his servants will arise and build: but ye have no portion, nor right, nor memorial, in Jerusalem.

III

^1Then Eliashib the high priest rose up with his brethren the priests, and they builded the sheep gate; they sanctified it, and set up the doors of it; even unto the tower of Meah they sanctified it, unto the tower of Hananeel.

^2And next unto him builded the men of Jericho. And next to them builded Zaccur the son of Imri.

^3But the fish gate did the sons of Hassenaah build, who also laid the beams thereof, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof.

^4And next unto them repaired Meremoth the son of Urijah, the son of Koz. And next unto them repaired Meshullam the son of Berechiah, the son of Meshezabeel. And next unto them repaired Zadok the son of Baana.

^5And next unto them the Tekoites repaired; but their nobles put not their necks to the work of their Lord.

^6Moreover the old gate repaired Jehoiada the son of Paseah, and Meshullam the son of Besodeiah; they laid the beams thereof, and set up the doors thereof, and the locks thereof, and the bars thereof.

^7And next unto them repaired Melatiah the Gibeonite, and Jadon the Meronothite, the men of Gibeon, and of Mizpah, unto the throne of the governor on this side the river.

^8Next unto him repaired Uzziel the son of Harhaiah, of the goldsmiths. Next unto him also repaired Hananiah the son of one of the apothecaries, and they fortified Jerusalem unto the broad wall.

^9And next unto them repaired Rephaiah the son of Hur, the ruler of the half part of Jerusalem.

^10And next unto them repaired Jedaiah the son of Harumaph, even over against his house. And next unto him repaired Hattush the son of Hashabniah.

^11Malchijah the son of Harim, and Hashub the son of Pahathmoab, repaired the other piece, and the tower of the furnaces.

^12And next unto him repaired Shallum the son of Halohesh, the ruler of the half part of Jerusalem, he and his daughters.

^13The valley gate repaired Hanun, and the inhabitants of Zanoah; they built it, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof, and a thousand cubits on the wall unto the dung gate.

^14But the dung gate repaired Malchiah the son of Rechab, the ruler of part of Bethhaccerem; he built it, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof.

^15But the gate of the fountain repaired Shallun the son of Colhozeh, the ruler of part of Mizpah; he built it, and covered it, and set up the doors thereof, the locks thereof, and the bars thereof, and the wall of the pool of Siloah by the king’s garden, and unto the stairs that go down from the city of David.

^16After him repaired Nehemiah the son of Azbuk, the ruler of the half part of Bethzur, unto the place over against the sepulchres of David, and to the pool that was made, and unto the house of the mighty.

^17After him repaired the Levites, Rehum the son of Bani. Next unto him repaired Hashabiah, the ruler of the half part of Keilah, in his part.

^18After him repaired their brethren, Bavai the son of Henadad, the ruler of the half part of Keilah.

^19And next to him repaired Ezer the son of Jeshua, the ruler of Mizpah, another piece over against the going up to the armoury at the turning of the wall.

^20After him Baruch the son of Zabbai earnestly repaired the other piece, from the turning of the wall unto the door of the house of Eliashib the high priest.

^21After him repaired Meremoth the son of Urijah the son of Koz another piece, from the door of the house of Eliashib even to the end of the house of Eliashib.

^22And after him repaired the priests, the men of the plain.

^23After him repaired Benjamin and Hashub over against their house. After him repaired Azariah the son of Maaseiah the son of Ananiah by his house.

^24After him repaired Binnui the son of Henadad another piece, from the house of Azariah unto the turning of the wall, even unto the corner.

^25Palal the son of Uzai, over against the turning of the wall, and the tower which lieth out from the king’s high house, that was by the court of the prison. After him Pedaiah the son of Parosh.

^26Moreover the Nethinims dwelt in Ophel, unto the place over against the water gate toward the east, and the tower that lieth out.

^27After them the Tekoites repaired another piece, over against the great tower that lieth out, even unto the wall of Ophel.

^28From above the horse gate repaired the priests, every one over against his house.

^29After them repaired Zadok the son of Immer over against his house. After him repaired also Shemaiah the son of Shechaniah, the keeper of the east gate.

^30After him repaired Hananiah the son of Shelemiah, and Hanun the sixth son of Zalaph, another piece. After him repaired Meshullam the son of Berechiah over against his chamber.

^31After him repaired Malchiah the goldsmith’s son unto the place of the Nethinims, and of the merchants, over against the gate Miphkad, and to the going up of the corner.

^32And between the going up of the corner unto the sheep gate repaired the goldsmiths and the merchants.

IV

^1But it came to pass, that when Sanballat heard that we builded the wall, he was wroth, and took great indignation, and mocked the Jews.

^2And he spake before his brethren and the army of Samaria, and said, What do these feeble Jews? will they fortify themselves? will they sacrifice? will they make an end in a day? will they revive the stones out of the heaps of the rubbish which are burned?

^3Now Tobiah the Ammonite was by him, and he said, Even that which they build, if a fox go up, he shall even break down their stone wall.

^4Hear, O our God; for we are despised: and turn their reproach upon their own head, and give them for a prey in the land of captivity:

^5And cover not their iniquity, and let not their sin be blotted out from before thee: for they have provoked thee to anger before the builders.

^6So built we the wall; and all the wall was joined together unto the half thereof: for the people had a mind to work.

^7But it came to pass, that when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and the Arabians, and the Ammonites, and the Ashdodites, heard that the walls of Jerusalem were made up, and that the breaches began to be stopped, then they were very wroth,

^8And conspired all of them together to come and to fight against Jerusalem, and to hinder it.

^9Nevertheless we made our prayer unto our God, and set a watch against them day and night, because of them.

^10And Judah said, The strength of the bearers of burdens is decayed, and there is much rubbish; so that we are not able to build the wall.

^11And our adversaries said, They shall not know, neither see, till we come in the midst among them, and slay them, and cause the work to cease.

^12And it came to pass, that when the Jews which dwelt by them came, they said unto us ten times, From all places whence ye shall return unto us they will be upon you.

^13Therefore set I in the lower places behind the wall, and on the higher places, I even set the people after their families with their swords, their spears, and their bows.

^14And I looked, and rose up, and said unto the nobles, and to the rulers, and to the rest of the people, Be not ye afraid of them: remember the Lord, which is great and terrible, and fight for your brethren, your sons, and your daughters, your wives, and your houses.

^15And it came to pass, when our enemies heard that it was known unto us, and God had brought their counsel to nought, that we returned all of us to the wall, every one unto his work.

^16And it came to pass from that time forth, that the half of my servants wrought in the work, and the other half of them held both the spears, the shields, and the bows, and the habergeons; and the rulers were behind all the house of Judah.

^17They which builded on the wall, and they that bare burdens, with those that laded, every one with one of his hands wrought in the work, and with the other hand held a weapon.

^18For the builders, every one had his sword girded by his side, and so builded. And he that sounded the trumpet was by me.

^19And I said unto the nobles, and to the rulers, and to the rest of the people, The work is great and large, and we are separated upon the wall, one far from another.

^20In what place therefore ye hear the sound of the trumpet, resort ye thither unto us: our God shall fight for us.

^21So we laboured in the work: and half of them held the spears from the rising of the morning till the stars appeared.

^22Likewise at the same time said I unto the people, Let every one with his servant lodge within Jerusalem, that in the night they may be a guard to us, and labour on the day.

^23So neither I, nor my brethren, nor my servants, nor the men of the guard which followed me, none of us put off our clothes, saving that every one put them off for washing.

V

^1And there was a great cry of the people and of their wives against their brethren the Jews.

^2For there were that said, We, our sons, and our daughters, are many: therefore we take up corn for them, that we may eat, and live.

^3Some also there were that said, We have mortgaged our lands, vineyards, and houses, that we might buy corn, because of the dearth.

^4There were also that said, We have borrowed money for the king’s tribute, and that upon our lands and vineyards.

^5Yet now our flesh is as the flesh of our brethren, our children as their children: and, lo, we bring into bondage our sons and our daughters to be servants, and some of our daughters are brought unto bondage already: neither is it in our power to redeem them; for other men have our lands and vineyards.

^6And I was very angry when I heard their cry and these words.

^7Then I consulted with myself, and I rebuked the nobles, and the rulers, and said unto them, Ye exact usury, every one of his brother. And I set a great assembly against them.

^8And I said unto them, We after our ability have redeemed our brethren the Jews, which were sold unto the heathen; and will ye even sell your brethren? or shall they be sold unto us? Then held they their peace, and found nothing to answer.

^9Also I said, It is not good that ye do: ought ye not to walk in the fear of our God because of the reproach of the heathen our enemies?

^10I likewise, and my brethren, and my servants, might exact of them money and corn: I pray you, let us leave off this usury.

^11Restore, I pray you, to them, even this day, their lands, their vineyards, their oliveyards, and their houses, also the hundredth part of the money, and of the corn, the wine, and the oil, that ye exact of them.

^12Then said they, We will restore them, and will require nothing of them; so will we do as thou sayest. Then I called the priests, and took an oath of them, that they should do according to this promise.

^13Also I shook my lap, and said, So God shake out every man from his house, and from his labour, that performeth not this promise, even thus be he shaken out, and emptied. And all the congregation said, Amen, and praised the Lord. And the people did according to this promise.

^14Moreover from the time that I was appointed to be their governor in the land of Judah, from the twentieth year even unto the two and thirtieth year of Artaxerxes the king, that is, twelve years, I and my brethren have not eaten the bread of the governor.

^15But the former governors that had been before me were chargeable unto the people, and had taken of them bread and wine, beside forty shekels of silver; yea, even their servants bare rule over the people: but so did not I, because of the fear of God.

^16Yea, also I continued in the work of this wall, neither bought we any land: and all my servants were gathered thither unto the work.

^17Moreover there were at my table an hundred and fifty of the Jews and rulers, beside those that came unto us from among the heathen that are about us.

^18Now that which was prepared for me daily was one ox and six choice sheep; also fowls were prepared for me, and once in ten days store of all sorts of wine: yet for all this required not I the bread of the governor, because the bondage was heavy upon this people.

^19Think upon me, my God, for good, according to all that I have done for this people.

VI

^1Now it came to pass when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and Geshem the Arabian, and the rest of our enemies, heard that I had builded the wall, and that there was no breach left therein; (though at that time I had not set up the doors upon the gates;)

^2That Sanballat and Geshem sent unto me, saying, Come, let us meet together in some one of the villages in the plain of Ono. But they thought to do me mischief.

^3And I sent messengers unto them, saying, I am doing a great work, so that I cannot come down: why should the work cease, whilst I leave it, and come down to you?

^4Yet they sent unto me four times after this sort; and I answered them after the same manner.

^5Then sent Sanballat his servant unto me in like manner the fifth time with an open letter in his hand;

^6Wherein was written, It is reported among the heathen, and Gashmu saith it, that thou and the Jews think to rebel: for which cause thou buildest the wall, that thou mayest be their king, according to these words.

^7And thou hast also appointed prophets to preach of thee at Jerusalem, saying, There is a king in Judah: and now shall it be reported to the king according to these words. Come now therefore, and let us take counsel together.

^8Then I sent unto him, saying, There are no such things done as thou sayest, but thou feignest them out of thine own heart.

^9For they all made us afraid, saying, Their hands shall be weakened from the work, that it be not done. Now therefore, O God, strengthen my hands.

^10Afterward I came unto the house of Shemaiah the son of Delaiah the son of Mehetabeel, who was shut up; and he said, Let us meet together in the house of God, within the temple, and let us shut the doors of the temple: for they will come to slay thee; yea, in the night will they come to slay thee.

^11And I said, Should such a man as I flee? and who is there, that, being as I am, would go into the temple to save his life? I will not go in.

^12And, lo, I perceived that God had not sent him; but that he pronounced this prophecy against me: for Tobiah and Sanballat had hired him.

^13Therefore was he hired, that I should be afraid, and do so, and sin, and that they might have matter for an evil report, that they might reproach me.

^14My God, think thou upon Tobiah and Sanballat according to these their works, and on the prophetess Noadiah, and the rest of the prophets, that would have put me in fear.

^15So the wall was finished in the twenty and fifth day of the month Elul, in fifty and two days.

^16And it came to pass, that when all our enemies heard thereof, and all the heathen that were about us saw these things, they were much cast down in their own eyes: for they perceived that this work was wrought of our God.

^17Moreover in those days the nobles of Judah sent many letters unto Tobiah, and the letters of Tobiah came unto them.

^18For there were many in Judah sworn unto him, because he was the son in law of Shechaniah the son of Arah; and his son Johanan had taken the daughter of Meshullam the son of Berechiah.

^19Also they reported his good deeds before me, and uttered my words to him. And Tobiah sent letters to put me in fear.

VII

^1Now it came to pass, when the wall was built, and I had set up the doors, and the porters and the singers and the Levites were appointed,

^2That I gave my brother Hanani, and Hananiah the ruler of the palace, charge over Jerusalem: for he was a faithful man, and feared God above many.

^3And I said unto them, Let not the gates of Jerusalem be opened until the sun be hot; and while they stand by, let them shut the doors, and bar them: and appoint watches of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, every one in his watch, and every one to be over against his house.

^4Now the city was large and great: but the people were few therein, and the houses were not builded.

^5And my God put into mine heart to gather together the nobles, and the rulers, and the people, that they might be reckoned by genealogy. And I found a register of the genealogy of them which came up at the first, and found written therein,

^6These are the children of the province, that went up out of the captivity, of those that had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away, and came again to Jerusalem and to Judah, every one unto his city;

^7Who came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum, Baanah. The number, I say, of the men of the people of Israel was this;

^8The children of Parosh, two thousand an hundred seventy and two.

^9The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy and two.

^10The children of Arah, six hundred fifty and two.

^11The children of Pahathmoab, of the children of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand and eight hundred and eighteen.

^12The children of Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four.

^13The children of Zattu, eight hundred forty and five.

^14The children of Zaccai, seven hundred and threescore.

^15The children of Binnui, six hundred forty and eight.

^16The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty and eight.

^17The children of Azgad, two thousand three hundred twenty and two.

^18The children of Adonikam, six hundred threescore and seven.

^19The children of Bigvai, two thousand threescore and seven.

^20The children of Adin, six hundred fifty and five.

^21The children of Ater of Hezekiah, ninety and eight.

^22The children of Hashum, three hundred twenty and eight.

^23The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty and four.

^24The children of Hariph, an hundred and twelve.

^25The children of Gibeon, ninety and five.

^26The men of Bethlehem and Netophah, an hundred fourscore and eight.

^27The men of Anathoth, an hundred twenty and eight.

^28The men of Bethazmaveth, forty and two.

^29The men of Kirjathjearim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred forty and three.

^30The men of Ramah and Gaba, six hundred twenty and one.

^31The men of Michmas, an hundred and twenty and two.

^32The men of Bethel and Ai, an hundred twenty and three.

^33The men of the other Nebo, fifty and two.

^34The children of the other Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four.

^35The children of Harim, three hundred and twenty.

^36The children of Jericho, three hundred forty and five.

^37The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty and one.

^38The children of Senaah, three thousand nine hundred and thirty.

^39The priests: the children of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy and three.

^40The children of Immer, a thousand fifty and two.

^41The children of Pashur, a thousand two hundred forty and seven.

^42The children of Harim, a thousand and seventeen.

^43The Levites: the children of Jeshua, of Kadmiel, and of the children of Hodevah, seventy and four.

^44The singers: the children of Asaph, an hundred forty and eight.

^45The porters: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, an hundred thirty and eight.

^46The Nethinims: the children of Ziha, the children of Hashupha, the children of Tabbaoth,

^47The children of Keros, the children of Sia, the children of Padon,

^48The children of Lebana, the children of Hagaba, the children of Shalmai,

^49The children of Hanan, the children of Giddel, the children of Gahar,

^50The children of Reaiah, the children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda,

^51The children of Gazzam, the children of Uzza, the children of Phaseah,

^52The children of Besai, the children of Meunim, the children of Nephishesim,

^53The children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur,

^54The children of Bazlith, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha,

^55The children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Tamah,

^56The children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.

^57The children of Solomon’s servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Sophereth, the children of Perida,

^58The children of Jaala, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel,

^59The children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth of Zebaim, the children of Amon.

^60All the Nethinims, and the children of Solomon’s servants, were three hundred ninety and two.

^61And these were they which went up also from Telmelah, Telharesha, Cherub, Addon, and Immer: but they could not shew their father’s house, nor their seed, whether they were of Israel.

^62The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred forty and two.

^63And of the priests: the children of Habaiah, the children of Koz, the children of Barzillai, which took one of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite to wife, and was called after their name.

^64These sought their register among those that were reckoned by genealogy, but it was not found: therefore were they, as polluted, put from the priesthood.

^65And the Tirshatha said unto them, that they should not eat of the most holy things, till there stood up a priest with Urim and Thummim.

^66The whole congregation together was forty and two thousand three hundred and threescore,

^67Beside their manservants and their maidservants, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred thirty and seven: and they had two hundred forty and five singing men and singing women.

^68Their horses, seven hundred thirty and six: their mules, two hundred forty and five:

^69Their camels, four hundred thirty and five: six thousand seven hundred and twenty asses.

^70And some of the chief of the fathers gave unto the work. The Tirshatha gave to the treasure a thousand drams of gold, fifty basons, five hundred and thirty priests’ garments.

^71And some of the chief of the fathers gave to the treasure of the work twenty thousand drams of gold, and two thousand and two hundred pound of silver.

^72And that which the rest of the people gave was twenty thousand drams of gold, and two thousand pound of silver, and threescore and seven priests’ garments.

^73So the priests, and the Levites, and the porters, and the singers, and some of the people, and the Nethinims, and all Israel, dwelt in their cities; and when the seventh month came, the children of Israel were in their cities.

VIII

^1And all the people gathered themselves together as one man into the street that was before the water gate; and they spake unto Ezra the scribe to bring the book of the law of Moses, which the Lord had commanded to Israel.

^2And Ezra the priest brought the law before the congregation both of men and women, and all that could hear with understanding, upon the first day of the seventh month.

^3And he read therein before the street that was before the water gate from the morning until midday, before the men and the women, and those that could understand; and the ears of all the people were attentive unto the book of the law.

^4And Ezra the scribe stood upon a pulpit of wood, which they had made for the purpose; and beside him stood Mattithiah, and Shema, and Anaiah, and Urijah, and Hilkiah, and Maaseiah, on his right hand; and on his left hand, Pedaiah, and Mishael, and Malchiah, and Hashum, and Hashbadana, Zechariah, and Meshullam.

^5And Ezra opened the book in the sight of all the people; (for he was above all the people;) and when he opened it, all the people stood up:

^6And Ezra blessed the Lord, the great God. And all the people answered, Amen, Amen, with lifting up their hands: and they bowed their heads, and worshipped the Lord with their faces to the ground.

^7Also Jeshua, and Bani, and Sherebiah, Jamin, Akkub, Shabbethai, Hodijah, Maaseiah, Kelita, Azariah, Jozabad, Hanan, Pelaiah, and the Levites, caused the people to understand the law: and the people stood in their place.

^8So they read in the book in the law of God distinctly, and gave the sense, and caused them to understand the reading.

^9And Nehemiah, which is the Tirshatha, and Ezra the priest the scribe, and the Levites that taught the people, said unto all the people, This day is holy unto the Lord your God; mourn not, nor weep. For all the people wept, when they heard the words of the law.

^10Then he said unto them, Go your way, eat the fat, and drink the sweet, and send portions unto them for whom nothing is prepared: for this day is holy unto our Lord: neither be ye sorry; for the joy of the Lord is your strength.

^11So the Levites stilled all the people, saying, Hold your peace, for the day is holy; neither be ye grieved.

^12And all the people went their way to eat, and to drink, and to send portions, and to make great mirth, because they had understood the words that were declared unto them.

^13And on the second day were gathered together the chief of the fathers of all the people, the priests, and the Levites, unto Ezra the scribe, even to understand the words of the law.

^14And they found written in the law which the Lord had commanded by Moses, that the children of Israel should dwell in booths in the feast of the seventh month:

^15And that they should publish and proclaim in all their cities, and in Jerusalem, saying, Go forth unto the mount, and fetch olive branches, and pine branches, and myrtle branches, and palm branches, and branches of thick trees, to make booths, as it is written.

^16So the people went forth, and brought them, and made themselves booths, every one upon the roof of his house, and in their courts, and in the courts of the house of God, and in the street of the water gate, and in the street of the gate of Ephraim.

^17And all the congregation of them that were come again out of the captivity made booths, and sat under the booths: for since the days of Jeshua the son of Nun unto that day had not the children of Israel done so. And there was very great gladness.

^18Also day by day, from the first day unto the last day, he read in the book of the law of God. And they kept the feast seven days; and on the eighth day was a solemn assembly, according unto the manner.

IX

^1Now in the twenty and fourth day of this month the children of Israel were assembled with fasting, and with sackclothes, and earth upon them.

^2And the seed of Israel separated themselves from all strangers, and stood and confessed their sins, and the iniquities of their fathers.

^3And they stood up in their place, and read in the book of the law of the Lord their God one fourth part of the day; and another fourth part they confessed, and worshipped the Lord their God.

^4Then stood up upon the stairs, of the Levites, Jeshua, and Bani, Kadmiel, Shebaniah, Bunni, Sherebiah, Bani, and Chenani, and cried with a loud voice unto the Lord their God.

^5Then the Levites, Jeshua, and Kadmiel, Bani, Hashabniah, Sherebiah, Hodijah, Shebaniah, and Pethahiah, said, Stand up and bless the Lord your God for ever and ever: and blessed be thy glorious name, which is exalted above all blessing and praise.

^6Thou, even thou, art Lord alone; thou hast made heaven, the heaven of heavens, with all their host, the earth, and all things that are therein, the seas, and all that is therein, and thou preservest them all; and the host of heaven worshippeth thee.

^7Thou art the Lord the God, who didst choose Abram, and broughtest him forth out of Ur of the Chaldees, and gavest him the name of Abraham;

^8And foundest his heart faithful before thee, and madest a covenant with him to give the land of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Jebusites, and the Girgashites, to give it, I say, to his seed, and hast performed thy words; for thou art righteous:

^9And didst see the affliction of our fathers in Egypt, and heardest their cry by the Red sea;

^10And shewedst signs and wonders upon Pharaoh, and on all his servants, and on all the people of his land: for thou knewest that they dealt proudly against them. So didst thou get thee a name, as it is this day.

^11And thou didst divide the sea before them, so that they went through the midst of the sea on the dry land; and their persecutors thou threwest into the deeps, as a stone into the mighty waters.

^12Moreover thou leddest them in the day by a cloudy pillar; and in the night by a pillar of fire, to give them light in the way wherein they should go.

^13Thou camest down also upon mount Sinai, and spakest with them from heaven, and gavest them right judgments, and true laws, good statutes and commandments:

^14And madest known unto them thy holy sabbath, and commandedst them precepts, statutes, and laws, by the hand of Moses thy servant:

^15And gavest them bread from heaven for their hunger, and broughtest forth water for them out of the rock for their thirst, and promisedst them that they should go in to possess the land which thou hadst sworn to give them.

^16But they and our fathers dealt proudly, and hardened their necks, and hearkened not to thy commandments,

^17And refused to obey, neither were mindful of thy wonders that thou didst among them; but hardened their necks, and in their rebellion appointed a captain to return to their bondage: but thou art a God ready to pardon, gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and of great kindness, and forsookest them not.

^18Yea, when they had made them a molten calf, and said, This is thy God that brought thee up out of Egypt, and had wrought great provocations;

^19Yet thou in thy manifold mercies forsookest them not in the wilderness: the pillar of the cloud departed not from them by day, to lead them in the way; neither the pillar of fire by night, to shew them light, and the way wherein they should go.

^20Thou gavest also thy good spirit to instruct them, and withheldest not thy manna from their mouth, and gavest them water for their thirst.

^21Yea, forty years didst thou sustain them in the wilderness, so that they lacked nothing; their clothes waxed not old, and their feet swelled not.

^22Moreover thou gavest them kingdoms and nations, and didst divide them into corners: so they possessed the land of Sihon, and the land of the king of Heshbon, and the land of Og king of Bashan.

^23Their children also multipliedst thou as the stars of heaven, and broughtest them into the land, concerning which thou hadst promised to their fathers, that they should go in to possess it.

^24So the children went in and possessed the land, and thou subduedst before them the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, and gavest them into their hands, with their kings, and the people of the land, that they might do with them as they would.

^25And they took strong cities, and a fat land, and possessed houses full of all goods, wells digged, vineyards, and oliveyards, and fruit trees in abundance: so they did eat, and were filled, and became fat, and delighted themselves in thy great goodness.

^26Nevertheless they were disobedient, and rebelled against thee, and cast thy law behind their backs, and slew thy prophets which testified against them to turn them to thee, and they wrought great provocations.

^27Therefore thou deliveredst them into the hand of their enemies, who vexed them: and in the time of their trouble, when they cried unto thee, thou heardest them from heaven; and according to thy manifold mercies thou gavest them saviours, who saved them out of the hand of their enemies.

^28But after they had rest, they did evil again before thee: therefore leftest thou them in the land of their enemies, so that they had the dominion over them: yet when they returned, and cried unto thee, thou heardest them from heaven; and many times didst thou deliver them according to thy mercies;

^29And testifiedst against them, that thou mightest bring them again unto thy law: yet they dealt proudly, and hearkened not unto thy commandments, but sinned against thy judgments, (which if a man do, he shall live in them;) and withdrew the shoulder, and hardened their neck, and would not hear.

^30Yet many years didst thou forbear them, and testifiedst against them by thy spirit in thy prophets: yet would they not give ear: therefore gavest thou them into the hand of the people of the lands.

^31Nevertheless for thy great mercies’ sake thou didst not utterly consume them, nor forsake them; for thou art a gracious and merciful God.

^32Now therefore, our God, the great, the mighty, and the terrible God, who keepest covenant and mercy, let not all the trouble seem little before thee, that hath come upon us, on our kings, on our princes, and on our priests, and on our prophets, and on our fathers, and on all thy people, since the time of the kings of Assyria unto this day.

^33Howbeit thou art just in all that is brought upon us; for thou hast done right, but we have done wickedly:

^34Neither have our kings, our princes, our priests, nor our fathers, kept thy law, nor hearkened unto thy commandments and thy testimonies, wherewith thou didst testify against them.

^35For they have not served thee in their kingdom, and in thy great goodness that thou gavest them, and in the large and fat land which thou gavest before them, neither turned they from their wicked works.

^36Behold, we are servants this day, and for the land that thou gavest unto our fathers to eat the fruit thereof and the good thereof, behold, we are servants in it:

^37And it yieldeth much increase unto the kings whom thou hast set over us because of our sins: also they have dominion over our bodies, and over our cattle, at their pleasure, and we are in great distress.

^38And because of all this we make a sure covenant, and write it; and our princes, Levites, and priests, seal unto it.

X

^1Now those that sealed were, Nehemiah, the Tirshatha, the son of Hachaliah, and Zidkijah,

^2Seraiah, Azariah, Jeremiah,

^3Pashur, Amariah, Malchijah,

^4Hattush, Shebaniah, Malluch,

^5Harim, Meremoth, Obadiah,

^6Daniel, Ginnethon, Baruch,

^7Meshullam, Abijah, Mijamin,

^8Maaziah, Bilgai, Shemaiah: these were the priests.

^9And the Levites: both Jeshua the son of Azaniah, Binnui of the sons of Henadad, Kadmiel;

^10And their brethren, Shebaniah, Hodijah, Kelita, Pelaiah, Hanan,

^11Micha, Rehob, Hashabiah,

^12Zaccur, Sherebiah, Shebaniah,

^13Hodijah, Bani, Beninu.

^14The chief of the people; Parosh, Pahathmoab, Elam, Zatthu, Bani,

^15Bunni, Azgad, Bebai,

^16Adonijah, Bigvai, Adin,

^17Ater, Hizkijah, Azzur,

^18Hodijah, Hashum, Bezai,

^19Hariph, Anathoth, Nebai,

^20Magpiash, Meshullam, Hezir,

^21Meshezabeel, Zadok, Jaddua,

^22Pelatiah, Hanan, Anaiah,

^23Hoshea, Hananiah, Hashub,

^24Hallohesh, Pileha, Shobek,

^25Rehum, Hashabnah, Maaseiah,

^26And Ahijah, Hanan, Anan,

^27Malluch, Harim, Baanah.

^28And the rest of the people, the priests, the Levites, the porters, the singers, the Nethinims, and all they that had separated themselves from the people of the lands unto the law of God, their wives, their sons, and their daughters, every one having knowledge, and having understanding;

^29They clave to their brethren, their nobles, and entered into a curse, and into an oath, to walk in God’s law, which was given by Moses the servant of God, and to observe and do all the commandments of the Lord our Lord, and his judgments and his statutes;

^30And that we would not give our daughters unto the people of the land, not take their daughters for our sons:

^31And if the people of the land bring ware or any victuals on the sabbath day to sell, that we would not buy it of them on the sabbath, or on the holy day: and that we would leave the seventh year, and the exaction of every debt.

^32Also we made ordinances for us, to charge ourselves yearly with the third part of a shekel for the service of the house of our God;

^33For the shewbread, and for the continual meat offering, and for the continual burnt offering, of the sabbaths, of the new moons, for the set feasts, and for the holy things, and for the sin offerings to make an atonement for Israel, and for all the work of the house of our God.

^34And we cast the lots among the priests, the Levites, and the people, for the wood offering, to bring it into the house of our God, after the houses of our fathers, at times appointed year by year, to burn upon the altar of the Lord our God, as it is written in the law:

^35And to bring the firstfruits of our ground, and the firstfruits of all fruit of all trees, year by year, unto the house of the Lord:

^36Also the firstborn of our sons, and of our cattle, as it is written in the law, and the firstlings of our herds and of our flocks, to bring to the house of our God, unto the priests that minister in the house of our God:

^37And that we should bring the firstfruits of our dough, and our offerings, and the fruit of all manner of trees, of wine and of oil, unto the priests, to the chambers of the house of our God; and the tithes of our ground unto the Levites, that the same Levites might have the tithes in all the cities of our tillage.

^38And the priest the son of Aaron shall be with the Levites, when the Levites take tithes: and the Levites shall bring up the tithe of the tithes unto the house of our God, to the chambers, into the treasure house.

^39For the children of Israel and the children of Levi shall bring the offering of the corn, of the new wine, and the oil, unto the chambers, where are the vessels of the sanctuary, and the priests that minister, and the porters, and the singers: and we will not forsake the house of our God.

XI

^1And the rulers of the people dwelt at Jerusalem: the rest of the people also cast lots, to bring one of ten to dwell in Jerusalem the holy city, and nine parts to dwell in other cities.

^2And the people blessed all the men, that willingly offered themselves to dwell at Jerusalem.

^3Now these are the chief of the province that dwelt in Jerusalem: but in the cities of Judah dwelt every one in his possession in their cities, to wit, Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the Nethinims, and the children of Solomon’s servants.

^4And at Jerusalem dwelt certain of the children of Judah, and of the children of Benjamin. Of the children of Judah; Athaiah the son of Uzziah, the son of Zechariah, the son of Amariah, the son of Shephatiah, the son of Mahalaleel, of the children of Perez;

^5And Maaseiah the son of Baruch, the son of Colhozeh, the son of Hazaiah, the son of Adaiah, the son of Joiarib, the son of Zechariah, the son of Shiloni.

^6All the sons of Perez that dwelt at Jerusalem were four hundred threescore and eight valiant men.

^7And these are the sons of Benjamin; Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Joed, the son of Pedaiah, the son of Kolaiah, the son of Maaseiah, the son of Ithiel, the son of Jesaiah.

^8And after him Gabbai, Sallai, nine hundred twenty and eight.

^9And Joel the son of Zichri was their overseer: and Judah the son of Senuah was second over the city.

^10Of the priests: Jedaiah the son of Joiarib, Jachin.

^11Seraiah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, was the ruler of the house of God.

^12And their brethren that did the work of the house were eight hundred twenty and two: and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pelaliah, the son of Amzi, the son of Zechariah, the son of Pashur, the son of Malchiah.

^13And his brethren, chief of the fathers, two hundred forty and two: and Amashai the son of Azareel, the son of Ahasai, the son of Meshillemoth, the son of Immer,

^14And their brethren, mighty men of valour, an hundred twenty and eight: and their overseer was Zabdiel, the son of one of the great men.

^15Also of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hashub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Bunni;

^16And Shabbethai and Jozabad, of the chief of the Levites, had the oversight of the outward business of the house of God.

^17And Mattaniah the son of Micha, the son of Zabdi, the son of Asaph, was the principal to begin the thanksgiving in prayer: and Bakbukiah the second among his brethren, and Abda the son of Shammua, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun.

^18All the Levites in the holy city were two hundred fourscore and four.

^19Moreover the porters, Akkub, Talmon, and their brethren that kept the gates, were an hundred seventy and two.

^20And the residue of Israel, of the priests, and the Levites, were in all the cities of Judah, every one in his inheritance.

^21But the Nethinims dwelt in Ophel: and Ziha and Gispa were over the Nethinims.

^22The overseer also of the Levites at Jerusalem was Uzzi the son of Bani, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Micha. Of the sons of Asaph, the singers were over the business of the house of God.

^23For it was the king’s commandment concerning them, that a certain portion should be for the singers, due for every day.

^24And Pethahiah the son of Meshezabeel, of the children of Zerah the son of Judah, was at the king’s hand in all matters concerning the people.

^25And for the villages, with their fields, some of the children of Judah dwelt at Kirjatharba, and in the villages thereof, and at Dibon, and in the villages thereof, and at Jekabzeel, and in the villages thereof,

^26And at Jeshua, and at Moladah, and at Bethphelet,

^27And at Hazarshual, and at Beersheba, and in the villages thereof,

^28And at Ziklag, and at Mekonah, and in the villages thereof,

^29And at Enrimmon, and at Zareah, and at Jarmuth,

^30Zanoah, Adullam, and in their villages, at Lachish, and the fields thereof, at Azekah, and in the villages thereof. And they dwelt from Beersheba unto the valley of Hinnom.

^31The children also of Benjamin from Geba dwelt at Michmash, and Aija, and Bethel, and in their villages.

^32And at Anathoth, Nob, Ananiah,

^33Hazor, Ramah, Gittaim,

^34Hadid, Zeboim, Neballat,

^35Lod, and Ono, the valley of craftsmen.

^36And of the Levites were divisions in Judah, and in Benjamin.

XII

^1Now these are the priests and the Levites that went up with Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua: Seraiah, Jeremiah, Ezra,

^2Amariah, Malluch, Hattush,

^3Shechaniah, Rehum, Meremoth,

^4Iddo, Ginnetho, Abijah,

^5Miamin, Maadiah, Bilgah,

^6Shemaiah, and Joiarib, Jedaiah,

^7Sallu, Amok, Hilkiah, Jedaiah. These were the chief of the priests and of their brethren in the days of Jeshua.

^8Moreover the Levites: Jeshua, Binnui, Kadmiel, Sherebiah, Judah, and Mattaniah, which was over the thanksgiving, he and his brethren.

^9Also Bakbukiah and Unni, their brethren, were over against them in the watches.

^10And Jeshua begat Joiakim, Joiakim also begat Eliashib, and Eliashib begat Joiada,

^11And Joiada begat Jonathan, and Jonathan begat Jaddua.

^12And in the days of Joiakim were priests, the chief of the fathers: of Seraiah, Meraiah; of Jeremiah, Hananiah;

^13Of Ezra, Meshullam; of Amariah, Jehohanan;

^14Of Melicu, Jonathan; of Shebaniah, Joseph;

^15Of Harim, Adna; of Meraioth, Helkai;

^16Of Iddo, Zechariah; of Ginnethon, Meshullam;

^17Of Abijah, Zichri; of Miniamin, of Moadiah, Piltai:

^18Of Bilgah, Shammua; of Shemaiah, Jehonathan;

^19And of Joiarib, Mattenai; of Jedaiah, Uzzi;

^20Of Sallai, Kallai; of Amok, Eber;

^21Of Hilkiah, Hashabiah; of Jedaiah, Nethaneel.

^22The Levites in the days of Eliashib, Joiada, and Johanan, and Jaddua, were recorded chief of the fathers: also the priests, to the reign of Darius the Persian.

^23The sons of Levi, the chief of the fathers, were written in the book of the chronicles, even until the days of Johanan the son of Eliashib.

^24And the chief of the Levites: Hashabiah, Sherebiah, and Jeshua the son of Kadmiel, with their brethren over against them, to praise and to give thanks, according to the commandment of David the man of God, ward over against ward.

^25Mattaniah, and Bakbukiah, Obadiah, Meshullam, Talmon, Akkub, were porters keeping the ward at the thresholds of the gates.

^26These were in the days of Joiakim the son of Jeshua, the son of Jozadak, and in the days of Nehemiah the governor, and of Ezra the priest, the scribe.

^27And at the dedication of the wall of Jerusalem they sought the Levites out of all their places, to bring them to Jerusalem, to keep the dedication with gladness, both with thanksgivings, and with singing, with cymbals, psalteries, and with harps.

^28And the sons of the singers gathered themselves together, both out of the plain country round about Jerusalem, and from the villages of Netophathi;

^29Also from the house of Gilgal, and out of the fields of Geba and Azmaveth: for the singers had builded them villages round about Jerusalem.

^30And the priests and the Levites purified themselves, and purified the people, and the gates, and the wall.

^31Then I brought up the princes of Judah upon the wall, and appointed two great companies of them that gave thanks, whereof one went on the right hand upon the wall toward the dung gate:

^32And after them went Hoshaiah, and half of the princes of Judah,

^33And Azariah, Ezra, and Meshullam,

^34Judah, and Benjamin, and Shemaiah, and Jeremiah,

^35And certain of the priests’ sons with trumpets; namely, Zechariah the son of Jonathan, the son of Shemaiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Michaiah, the son of Zaccur, the son of Asaph:

^36And his brethren, Shemaiah, and Azarael, Milalai, Gilalai, Maai, Nethaneel, and Judah, Hanani, with the musical instruments of David the man of God, and Ezra the scribe before them.

^37And at the fountain gate, which was over against them, they went up by the stairs of the city of David, at the going up of the wall, above the house of David, even unto the water gate eastward.

^38And the other company of them that gave thanks went over against them, and I after them, and the half of the people upon the wall, from beyond the tower of the furnaces even unto the broad wall;

^39And from above the gate of Ephraim, and above the old gate, and above the fish gate, and the tower of Hananeel, and the tower of Meah, even unto the sheep gate: and they stood still in the prison gate.

^40So stood the two companies of them that gave thanks in the house of God, and I, and the half of the rulers with me:

^41And the priests; Eliakim, Maaseiah, Miniamin, Michaiah, Elioenai, Zechariah, and Hananiah, with trumpets;

^42And Maaseiah, and Shemaiah, and Eleazar, and Uzzi, and Jehohanan, and Malchijah, and Elam, and Ezer. And the singers sang loud, with Jezrahiah their overseer.

^43Also that day they offered great sacrifices, and rejoiced: for God had made them rejoice with great joy: the wives also and the children rejoiced: so that the joy of Jerusalem was heard even afar off.

^44And at that time were some appointed over the chambers for the treasures, for the offerings, for the firstfruits, and for the tithes, to gather into them out of the fields of the cities the portions of the law for the priests and Levites: for Judah rejoiced for the priests and for the Levites that waited.

^45And both the singers and the porters kept the ward of their God, and the ward of the purification, according to the commandment of David, and of Solomon his son.

^46For in the days of David and Asaph of old there were chief of the singers, and songs of praise and thanksgiving unto God.

^47And all Israel in the days of Zerubbabel, and in the days of Nehemiah, gave the portions of the singers and the porters, every day his portion: and they sanctified holy things unto the Levites; and the Levites sanctified them unto the children of Aaron.

XIII

^1On that day they read in the book of Moses in the audience of the people; and therein was found written, that the Ammonite and the Moabite should not come into the congregation of God for ever;

^2Because they met not the children of Israel with bread and with water, but hired Balaam against them, that he should curse them: howbeit our God turned the curse into a blessing.

^3Now it came to pass, when they had heard the law, that they separated from Israel all the mixed multitude.

^4And before this, Eliashib the priest, having the oversight of the chamber of the house of our God, was allied unto Tobiah:

^5And he had prepared for him a great chamber, where aforetime they laid the meat offerings, the frankincense, and the vessels, and the tithes of the corn, the new wine, and the oil, which was commanded to be given to the Levites, and the singers, and the porters; and the offerings of the priests.

^6But in all this time was not I at Jerusalem: for in the two and thirtieth year of Artaxerxes king of Babylon came I unto the king, and after certain days obtained I leave of the king:

^7And I came to Jerusalem, and understood of the evil that Eliashib did for Tobiah, in preparing him a chamber in the courts of the house of God.

^8And it grieved me sore: therefore I cast forth all the household stuff to Tobiah out of the chamber.

^9Then I commanded, and they cleansed the chambers: and thither brought I again the vessels of the house of God, with the meat offering and the frankincense.

^10And I perceived that the portions of the Levites had not been given them: for the Levites and the singers, that did the work, were fled every one to his field.

^11Then contended I with the rulers, and said, Why is the house of God forsaken? And I gathered them together, and set them in their place.

^12Then brought all Judah the tithe of the corn and the new wine and the oil unto the treasuries.

^13And I made treasurers over the treasuries, Shelemiah the priest, and Zadok the scribe, and of the Levites, Pedaiah: and next to them was Hanan the son of Zaccur, the son of Mattaniah: for they were counted faithful, and their office was to distribute unto their brethren.

^14Remember me, O my God, concerning this, and wipe not out my good deeds that I have done for the house of my God, and for the offices thereof.

^15In those days saw I in Judah some treading wine presses on the sabbath, and bringing in sheaves, and lading asses; as also wine, grapes, and figs, and all manner of burdens, which they brought into Jerusalem on the sabbath day: and I testified against them in the day wherein they sold victuals.

^16There dwelt men of Tyre also therein, which brought fish, and all manner of ware, and sold on the sabbath unto the children of Judah, and in Jerusalem.

^17Then I contended with the nobles of Judah, and said unto them, What evil thing is this that ye do, and profane the sabbath day?

^18Did not your fathers thus, and did not our God bring all this evil upon us, and upon this city? yet ye bring more wrath upon Israel by profaning the sabbath.

^19And it came to pass, that when the gates of Jerusalem began to be dark before the sabbath, I commanded that the gates should be shut, and charged that they should not be opened till after the sabbath: and some of my servants set I at the gates, that there should no burden be brought in on the sabbath day.

^20So the merchants and sellers of all kind of ware lodged without Jerusalem once or twice.

^21Then I testified against them, and said unto them, Why lodge ye about the wall? if ye do so again, I will lay hands on you. From that time forth came they no more on the sabbath.

^22And I commanded the Levites that they should cleanse themselves, and that they should come and keep the gates, to sanctify the sabbath day. Remember me, O my God, concerning this also, and spare me according to the greatness of thy mercy.

^23In those days also saw I Jews that had married wives of Ashdod, of Ammon, and of Moab:

^24And their children spake half in the speech of Ashdod, and could not speak in the Jews’ language, but according to the language of each people.

^25And I contended with them, and cursed them, and smote certain of them, and plucked off their hair, and made them swear by God, saying, Ye shall not give your daughters unto their sons, nor take their daughters unto your sons, or for yourselves.

^26Did not Solomon king of Israel sin by these things? yet among many nations was there no king like him, who was beloved of his God, and God made him king over all Israel: nevertheless even him did outlandish women cause to sin.

^27Shall we then hearken unto you to do all this great evil, to transgress against our God in marrying strange wives?

^28And one of the sons of Joiada, the son of Eliashib the high priest, was son in law to Sanballat the Horonite: therefore I chased him from me.

^29Remember them, O my God, because they have defiled the priesthood, and the covenant of the priesthood, and of the Levites.

^30Thus cleansed I them from all strangers, and appointed the wards of the priests and the Levites, every one in his business;

^31And for the wood offering, at times appointed, and for the firstfruits. Remember me, O my God, for good.

Job 1

1^1There was a man in the land of Uz, whose name was Job; and that man was perfect and upright, and one that feared God, and eschewed evil.

^2And there were born unto him seven sons and three daughters.

^3His substance also was seven thousand sheep, and three thousand camels, and five hundred yoke of oxen, and five hundred she asses, and a very great household; so that this man was the greatest of all the men of the east.

^4And his sons went and feasted in their houses, every one his day; and sent and called for their three sisters to eat and to drink with them.

^5And it was so, when the days of their feasting were gone about, that Job sent and sanctified them, and rose up early in the morning, and offered burnt offerings according to the number of them all: for Job said, It may be that my sons have sinned, and cursed God in their hearts. Thus did Job continually.

^6Now there was a day when the sons of God came to present themselves before the Lord, and Satan came also among them.

^7And the Lord said unto Satan, Whence comest thou? Then Satan answered the Lord, and said, From going to and fro in the earth, and from walking up and down in it.

^8And the Lord said unto Satan, Hast thou considered my servant Job, that there is none like him in the earth, a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God, and escheweth evil?

^9Then Satan answered the Lord, and said, Doth Job fear God for nought?

^10Hast not thou made an hedge about him, and about his house, and about all that he hath on every side? thou hast blessed the work of his hands, and his substance is increased in the land.

^11But put forth thine hand now, and touch all that he hath, and he will curse thee to thy face.

^12And the Lord said unto Satan, Behold, all that he hath is in thy power; only upon himself put not forth thine hand. So Satan went forth from the presence of the Lord.

^13And there was a day when his sons and his daughters were eating and drinking wine in their eldest brother’s house:

^14And there came a messenger unto Job, and said, The oxen were plowing, and the asses feeding beside them:

^15And the Sabeans fell upon them, and took them away; yea, they have slain the servants with the edge of the sword; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee.

^16While he was yet speaking, there came also another, and said, The fire of God is fallen from heaven, and hath burned up the sheep, and the servants, and consumed them; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee.

^17While he was yet speaking, there came also another, and said, The Chaldeans made out three bands, and fell upon the camels, and have carried them away, yea, and slain the servants with the edge of the sword; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee.

^18While he was yet speaking, there came also another, and said, Thy sons and thy daughters were eating and drinking wine in their eldest brother’s house:

^19And, behold, there came a great wind from the wilderness, and smote the four corners of the house, and it fell upon the young men, and they are dead; and I only am escaped alone to tell thee.

^20Then Job arose, and rent his mantle, and shaved his head, and fell down upon the ground, and worshipped,

^21And said, Naked came I out of my mother’s womb, and naked shall I return thither: the Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away; blessed be the name of the Lord.

^22In all this Job sinned not, nor charged God foolishly.

Job 2

2^1Again there was a day when the sons of God came to present themselves before the Lord, and Satan came also among them to present himself before the Lord.

^2And the Lord said unto Satan, From whence comest thou? And Satan answered the Lord, and said, From going to and fro in the earth, and from walking up and down in it.

^3And the Lord said unto Satan, Hast thou considered my servant Job, that there is none like him in the earth, a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God, and escheweth evil? and still he holdeth fast his integrity, although thou movedst me against him, to destroy him without cause.

^4And Satan answered the Lord, and said, Skin for skin, yea, all that a man hath will he give for his life.

^5But put forth thine hand now, and touch his bone and his flesh, and he will curse thee to thy face.

^6And the Lord said unto Satan, Behold, he is in thine hand; but save his life.

^7So went Satan forth from the presence of the Lord, and smote Job with sore boils from the sole of his foot unto his crown.

^8And he took him a potsherd to scrape himself withal; and he sat down among the ashes.

^9Then said his wife unto him, Dost thou still retain thine integrity? curse God, and die.

^10But he said unto her, Thou speakest as one of the foolish women speaketh. What? shall we receive good at the hand of God, and shall we not receive evil? In all this did not Job sin with his lips.

^11Now when Job’s three friends heard of all this evil that was come upon him, they came every one from his own place; Eliphaz the Temanite, and Bildad the Shuhite, and Zophar the Naamathite: for they had made an appointment together to come to mourn with him and to comfort him.

^12And when they lifted up their eyes afar off, and knew him not, they lifted up their voice, and wept; and they rent every one his mantle, and sprinkled dust upon their heads toward heaven.

^13So they sat down with him upon the ground seven days and seven nights, and none spake a word unto him: for they saw that his grief was very great.

Job 3

3^1After this opened Job his mouth, and cursed his day.

^2And Job spake, and said,

^3Let the day perish wherein I was born, and the night in which it was said, There is a man child conceived.

^4Let that day be darkness; let not God regard it from above, neither let the light shine upon it.

^5Let darkness and the shadow of death stain it; let a cloud dwell upon it; let the blackness of the day terrify it.

^6As for that night, let darkness seize upon it; let it not be joined unto the days of the year, let it not come into the number of the months.

^7Lo, let that night be solitary, let no joyful voice come therein.

^8Let them curse it that curse the day, who are ready to raise up their mourning.

^9Let the stars of the twilight thereof be dark; let it look for light, but have none; neither let it see the dawning of the day:

^10Because it shut not up the doors of my mother’s womb, nor hid sorrow from mine eyes.

^11Why died I not from the womb? why did I not give up the ghost when I came out of the belly?

^12Why did the knees prevent me? or why the breasts that I should suck?

^13For now should I have lain still and been quiet, I should have slept: then had I been at rest,

^14With kings and counsellors of the earth, which build desolate places for themselves;

^15Or with princes that had gold, who filled their houses with silver:

^16Or as an hidden untimely birth I had not been; as infants which never saw light.

^17There the wicked cease from troubling; and there the weary be at rest.

^18There the prisoners rest together; they hear not the voice of the oppressor.

^19The small and great are there; and the servant is free from his master.

^20Wherefore is light given to him that is in misery, and life unto the bitter in soul;

^21Which long for death, but it cometh not; and dig for it more than for hid treasures;

^22Which rejoice exceedingly, and are glad, when they can find the grave?

^23Why is light given to a man whose way is hid, and whom God hath hedged in?

^24For my sighing cometh before I eat, and my roarings are poured out like the waters.

^25For the thing which I greatly feared is come upon me, and that which I was afraid of is come unto me.

^26I was not in safety, neither had I rest, neither was I quiet; yet trouble came.

Job 4

4^1Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered and said,

^2If we assay to commune with thee, wilt thou be grieved? but who can withhold himself from speaking?

^3Behold, thou hast instructed many, and thou hast strengthened the weak hands.

^4Thy words have upholden him that was falling, and thou hast strengthened the feeble knees.

^5But now it is come upon thee, and thou faintest; it toucheth thee, and thou art troubled.

^6Is not this thy fear, thy confidence, thy hope, and the uprightness of thy ways?

^7Remember, I pray thee, who ever perished, being innocent? or where were the righteous cut off?

^8Even as I have seen, they that plow iniquity, and sow wickedness, reap the same.

^9By the blast of God they perish, and by the breath of his nostrils are they consumed.

^10The roaring of the lion, and the voice of the fierce lion, and the teeth of the young lions, are broken.

^11The old lion perisheth for lack of prey, and the stout lion’s whelps are scattered abroad.

^12Now a thing was secretly brought to me, and mine ear received a little thereof.

^13In thoughts from the visions of the night, when deep sleep falleth on men,

^14Fear came upon me, and trembling, which made all my bones to shake.

^15Then a spirit passed before my face; the hair of my flesh stood up:

^16It stood still, but I could not discern the form thereof: an image was before mine eyes, there was silence, and I heard a voice, saying,

^17Shall mortal man be more just than God? shall a man be more pure than his maker?

^18Behold, he put no trust in his servants; and his angels he charged with folly:

^19How much less in them that dwell in houses of clay, whose foundation is in the dust, which are crushed before the moth?

^20They are destroyed from morning to evening: they perish for ever without any regarding it.

^21Doth not their excellency which is in them go away? they die, even without wisdom.

Job 5

5^1Call now, if there be any that will answer thee; and to which of the saints wilt thou turn?

^2For wrath killeth the foolish man, and envy slayeth the silly one.

^3I have seen the foolish taking root: but suddenly I cursed his habitation.

^4His children are far from safety, and they are crushed in the gate, neither is there any to deliver them.

^5Whose harvest the hungry eateth up, and taketh it even out of the thorns, and the robber swalloweth up their substance.

^6Although affliction cometh not forth of the dust, neither doth trouble spring out of the ground;

^7Yet man is born unto trouble, as the sparks fly upward.

^8I would seek unto God, and unto God would I commit my cause:

^9Which doeth great things and unsearchable; marvellous things without number:

^10Who giveth rain upon the earth, and sendeth waters upon the fields:

^11To set up on high those that be low; that those which mourn may be exalted to safety.

^12He disappointeth the devices of the crafty, so that their hands cannot perform their enterprise.

^13He taketh the wise in their own craftiness: and the counsel of the froward is carried headlong.

^14They meet with darkness in the day time, and grope in the noonday as in the night.

^15But he saveth the poor from the sword, from their mouth, and from the hand of the mighty.

^16So the poor hath hope, and iniquity stoppeth her mouth.

^17Behold, happy is the man whom God correcteth: therefore despise not thou the chastening of the Almighty:

^18For he maketh sore, and bindeth up: he woundeth, and his hands make whole.

^19He shall deliver thee in six troubles: yea, in seven there shall no evil touch thee.

^20In famine he shall redeem thee from death: and in war from the power of the sword.

^21Thou shalt be hid from the scourge of the tongue: neither shalt thou be afraid of destruction when it cometh.

^22At destruction and famine thou shalt laugh: neither shalt thou be afraid of the beasts of the earth.

^23For thou shalt be in league with the stones of the field: and the beasts of the field shall be at peace with thee.

^24And thou shalt know that thy tabernacle shall be in peace; and thou shalt visit thy habitation, and shalt not sin.

^25Thou shalt know also that thy seed shall be great, and thine offspring as the grass of the earth.

^26Thou shalt come to thy grave in a full age, like as a shock of corn cometh in in his season.

^27Lo this, we have searched it, so it is; hear it, and know thou it for thy good.

Job 6

6^1But Job answered and said,

^2Oh that my grief were throughly weighed, and my calamity laid in the balances together!

^3For now it would be heavier than the sand of the sea: therefore my words are swallowed up.

^4For the arrows of the Almighty are within me, the poison whereof drinketh up my spirit: the terrors of God do set themselves in array against me.

^5Doth the wild ass bray when he hath grass? or loweth the ox over his fodder?

^6Can that which is unsavoury be eaten without salt? or is there any taste in the white of an egg?

^7The things that my soul refused to touch are as my sorrowful meat.

^8Oh that I might have my request; and that God would grant me the thing that I long for!

^9Even that it would please God to destroy me; that he would let loose his hand, and cut me off!

^10Then should I yet have comfort; yea, I would harden myself in sorrow: let him not spare; for I have not concealed the words of the Holy One.

^11What is my strength, that I should hope? and what is mine end, that I should prolong my life?

^12Is my strength the strength of stones? or is my flesh of brass?

^13Is not my help in me? and is wisdom driven quite from me?

^14To him that is afflicted pity should be shewed from his friend; but he forsaketh the fear of the Almighty.

^15My brethren have dealt deceitfully as a brook, and as the stream of brooks they pass away;

^16Which are blackish by reason of the ice, and wherein the snow is hid:

^17What time they wax warm, they vanish: when it is hot, they are consumed out of their place.

^18The paths of their way are turned aside; they go to nothing, and perish.

^19The troops of Tema looked, the companies of Sheba waited for them.

^20They were confounded because they had hoped; they came thither, and were ashamed.

^21For now ye are nothing; ye see my casting down, and are afraid.

^22Did I say, Bring unto me? or, Give a reward for me of your substance?

^23Or, Deliver me from the enemy’s hand? or, Redeem me from the hand of the mighty?

^24Teach me, and I will hold my tongue: and cause me to understand wherein I have erred.

^25How forcible are right words! but what doth your arguing reprove?

^26Do ye imagine to reprove words, and the speeches of one that is desperate, which are as wind?

^27Yea, ye overwhelm the fatherless, and ye dig a pit for your friend.

^28Now therefore be content, look upon me; for it is evident unto you if I lie.

^29Return, I pray you, let it not be iniquity; yea, return again, my righteousness is in it.

^30Is there iniquity in my tongue? cannot my taste discern perverse things?

Job 7

7^1Is there not an appointed time to man upon earth? are not his days also like the days of an hireling?

^2As a servant earnestly desireth the shadow, and as an hireling looketh for the reward of his work:

^3So am I made to possess months of vanity, and wearisome nights are appointed to me.

^4When I lie down, I say, When shall I arise, and the night be gone? and I am full of tossings to and fro unto the dawning of the day.

^5My flesh is clothed with worms and clods of dust; my skin is broken, and become loathsome.

^6My days are swifter than a weaver’s shuttle, and are spent without hope.

^7O remember that my life is wind: mine eye shall no more see good.

^8The eye of him that hath seen me shall see me no more: thine eyes are upon me, and I am not.

^9As the cloud is consumed and vanisheth away: so he that goeth down to the grave shall come up no more.

^10He shall return no more to his house, neither shall his place know him any more.

^11Therefore I will not refrain my mouth; I will speak in the anguish of my spirit; I will complain in the bitterness of my soul.

^12Am I a sea, or a whale, that thou settest a watch over me?

^13When I say, My bed shall comfort me, my couch shall ease my complaints;

^14Then thou scarest me with dreams, and terrifiest me through visions:

^15So that my soul chooseth strangling, and death rather than my life.

^16I loathe it; I would not live alway: let me alone; for my days are vanity.

^17What is man, that thou shouldest magnify him? and that thou shouldest set thine heart upon him?

^18And that thou shouldest visit him every morning, and try him every moment?

^19How long wilt thou not depart from me, nor let me alone till I swallow down my spittle?

^20I have sinned; what shall I do unto thee, O thou preserver of men? why hast thou set me as a mark against thee, so that I am a burden to myself?

^21And why dost thou not pardon my transgression, and take away my iniquity? for now shall I sleep in the dust; and thou shalt seek me in the morning, but I shall not be.

Job 8

8^1Then answered Bildad the Shuhite, and said,

^2How long wilt thou speak these things? and how long shall the words of thy mouth be like a strong wind?

^3Doth God pervert judgment? or doth the Almighty pervert justice?

^4If thy children have sinned against him, and he have cast them away for their transgression;

^5If thou wouldest seek unto God betimes, and make thy supplication to the Almighty;

^6If thou wert pure and upright; surely now he would awake for thee, and make the habitation of thy righteousness prosperous.

^7Though thy beginning was small, yet thy latter end should greatly increase.

^8For enquire, I pray thee, of the former age, and prepare thyself to the search of their fathers:

^9(For we are but of yesterday, and know nothing, because our days upon earth are a shadow:)

^10Shall not they teach thee, and tell thee, and utter words out of their heart?

^11Can the rush grow up without mire? can the flag grow without water?

^12Whilst it is yet in his greenness, and not cut down, it withereth before any other herb.

^13So are the paths of all that forget God; and the hypocrite’s hope shall perish:

^14Whose hope shall be cut off, and whose trust shall be a spider’s web.

^15He shall lean upon his house, but it shall not stand: he shall hold it fast, but it shall not endure.

^16He is green before the sun, and his branch shooteth forth in his garden.

^17His roots are wrapped about the heap, and seeth the place of stones.

^18If he destroy him from his place, then it shall deny him, saying, I have not seen thee.

^19Behold, this is the joy of his way, and out of the earth shall others grow.

^20Behold, God will not cast away a perfect man, neither will he help the evil doers:

^21Till he fill thy mouth with laughing, and thy lips with rejoicing.

^22They that hate thee shall be clothed with shame; and the dwelling place of the wicked shall come to nought.

Job 9

9^1Then Job answered and said,

^2I know it is so of a truth: but how should man be just with God?

^3If he will contend with him, he cannot answer him one of a thousand.

^4He is wise in heart, and mighty in strength: who hath hardened himself against him, and hath prospered?

^5Which removeth the mountains, and they know not: which overturneth them in his anger.

^6Which shaketh the earth out of her place, and the pillars thereof tremble.

^7Which commandeth the sun, and it riseth not; and sealeth up the stars.

^8Which alone spreadeth out the heavens, and treadeth upon the waves of the sea.

^9Which maketh Arcturus, Orion, and Pleiades, and the chambers of the south.

^10Which doeth great things past finding out; yea, and wonders without number.

^11Lo, he goeth by me, and I see him not: he passeth on also, but I perceive him not.

^12Behold, he taketh away, who can hinder him? who will say unto him, What doest thou?

^13If God will not withdraw his anger, the proud helpers do stoop under him.

^14How much less shall I answer him, and choose out my words to reason with him?

^15Whom, though I were righteous, yet would I not answer, but I would make supplication to my judge.

^16If I had called, and he had answered me; yet would I not believe that he had hearkened unto my voice.

^17For he breaketh me with a tempest, and multiplieth my wounds without cause.

^18He will not suffer me to take my breath, but filleth me with bitterness.

^19If I speak of strength, lo, he is strong: and if of judgment, who shall set me a time to plead?

^20If I justify myself, mine own mouth shall condemn me: if I say, I am perfect, it shall also prove me perverse.

^21Though I were perfect, yet would I not know my soul: I would despise my life.

^22This is one thing, therefore I said it, He destroyeth the perfect and the wicked.

^23If the scourge slay suddenly, he will laugh at the trial of the innocent.

^24The earth is given into the hand of the wicked: he covereth the faces of the judges thereof; if not, where, and who is he?

^25Now my days are swifter than a post: they flee away, they see no good.

^26They are passed away as the swift ships: as the eagle that hasteth to the prey.

^27If I say, I will forget my complaint, I will leave off my heaviness, and comfort myself:

^28I am afraid of all my sorrows, I know that thou wilt not hold me innocent.

^29If I be wicked, why then labour I in vain?

^30If I wash myself with snow water, and make my hands never so clean;

^31Yet shalt thou plunge me in the ditch, and mine own clothes shall abhor me.

^32For he is not a man, as I am, that I should answer him, and we should come together in judgment.

^33Neither is there any daysman betwixt us, that might lay his hand upon us both.

^34Let him take his rod away from me, and let not his fear terrify me:

^35Then would I speak, and not fear him; but it is not so with me.

Job 10

10^1My soul is weary of my life; I will leave my complaint upon myself; I will speak in the bitterness of my soul.

^2I will say unto God, Do not condemn me; shew me wherefore thou contendest with me.

^3Is it good unto thee that thou shouldest oppress, that thou shouldest despise the work of thine hands, and shine upon the counsel of the wicked?

^4Hast thou eyes of flesh? or seest thou as man seeth?

^5Are thy days as the days of man? are thy years as man’s days,

^6That thou enquirest after mine iniquity, and searchest after my sin?

^7Thou knowest that I am not wicked; and there is none that can deliver out of thine hand.

^8Thine hands have made me and fashioned me together round about; yet thou dost destroy me.

^9Remember, I beseech thee, that thou hast made me as the clay; and wilt thou bring me into dust again?

^10Hast thou not poured me out as milk, and curdled me like cheese?

^11Thou hast clothed me with skin and flesh, and hast fenced me with bones and sinews.

^12Thou hast granted me life and favour, and thy visitation hath preserved my spirit.

^13And these things hast thou hid in thine heart: I know that this is with thee.

^14If I sin, then thou markest me, and thou wilt not acquit me from mine iniquity.

^15If I be wicked, woe unto me; and if I be righteous, yet will I not lift up my head. I am full of confusion; therefore see thou mine affliction;

^16For it increaseth. Thou huntest me as a fierce lion: and again thou shewest thyself marvellous upon me.

^17Thou renewest thy witnesses against me, and increasest thine indignation upon me; changes and war are against me.

^18Wherefore then hast thou brought me forth out of the womb? Oh that I had given up the ghost, and no eye had seen me!

^19I should have been as though I had not been; I should have been carried from the womb to the grave.

^20Are not my days few? cease then, and let me alone, that I may take comfort a little,

^21Before I go whence I shall not return, even to the land of darkness and the shadow of death;

^22A land of darkness, as darkness itself; and of the shadow of death, without any order, and where the light is as darkness.

Job 11

11^1Then answered Zophar the Naamathite, and said,

^2Should not the multitude of words be answered? and should a man full of talk be justified?

^3Should thy lies make men hold their peace? and when thou mockest, shall no man make thee ashamed?

^4For thou hast said, My doctrine is pure, and I am clean in thine eyes.

^5But oh that God would speak, and open his lips against thee;

^6And that he would shew thee the secrets of wisdom, that they are double to that which is! Know therefore that God exacteth of thee less than thine iniquity deserveth.

^7Canst thou by searching find out God? canst thou find out the Almighty unto perfection?

^8It is as high as heaven; what canst thou do? deeper than hell; what canst thou know?

^9The measure thereof is longer than the earth, and broader than the sea.

^10If he cut off, and shut up, or gather together, then who can hinder him?

^11For he knoweth vain men: he seeth wickedness also; will he not then consider it?

^12For vain men would be wise, though man be born like a wild ass’s colt.

^13If thou prepare thine heart, and stretch out thine hands toward him;

^14If iniquity be in thine hand, put it far away, and let not wickedness dwell in thy tabernacles.

^15For then shalt thou lift up thy face without spot; yea, thou shalt be stedfast, and shalt not fear:

^16Because thou shalt forget thy misery, and remember it as waters that pass away:

^17And thine age shall be clearer than the noonday: thou shalt shine forth, thou shalt be as the morning.

^18And thou shalt be secure, because there is hope; yea, thou shalt dig about thee, and thou shalt take thy rest in safety.

^19Also thou shalt lie down, and none shall make thee afraid; yea, many shall make suit unto thee.

^20But the eyes of the wicked shall fail, and they shall not escape, and their hope shall be as the giving up of the ghost.

Job 12

12^1And Job answered and said,

^2No doubt but ye are the people, and wisdom shall die with you.

^3But I have understanding as well as you; I am not inferior to you: yea, who knoweth not such things as these?

^4I am as one mocked of his neighbour, who calleth upon God, and he answereth him: the just upright man is laughed to scorn.

^5He that is ready to slip with his feet is as a lamp despised in the thought of him that is at ease.

^6The tabernacles of robbers prosper, and they that provoke God are secure; into whose hand God bringeth abundantly.

^7But ask now the beasts, and they shall teach thee; and the fowls of the air, and they shall tell thee:

^8Or speak to the earth, and it shall teach thee: and the fishes of the sea shall declare unto thee.

^9Who knoweth not in all these that the hand of the Lord hath wrought this?

^10In whose hand is the soul of every living thing, and the breath of all mankind.

^11Doth not the ear try words? and the mouth taste his meat?

^12With the ancient is wisdom; and in length of days understanding.

^13With him is wisdom and strength, he hath counsel and understanding.

^14Behold, he breaketh down, and it cannot be built again: he shutteth up a man, and there can be no opening.

^15Behold, he withholdeth the waters, and they dry up: also he sendeth them out, and they overturn the earth.

^16With him is strength and wisdom: the deceived and the deceiver are his.

^17He leadeth counsellors away spoiled, and maketh the judges fools.

^18He looseth the bond of kings, and girdeth their loins with a girdle.

^19He leadeth princes away spoiled, and overthroweth the mighty.

^20He removeth away the speech of the trusty, and taketh away the understanding of the aged.

^21He poureth contempt upon princes, and weakeneth the strength of the mighty.

^22He discovereth deep things out of darkness, and bringeth out to light the shadow of death.

^23He increaseth the nations, and destroyeth them: he enlargeth the nations, and straiteneth them again.

^24He taketh away the heart of the chief of the people of the earth, and causeth them to wander in a wilderness where there is no way.

^25They grope in the dark without light, and he maketh them to stagger like a drunken man.

Job 13

13^1Lo, mine eye hath seen all this, mine ear hath heard and understood it.

^2What ye know, the same do I know also: I am not inferior unto you.

^3Surely I would speak to the Almighty, and I desire to reason with God.

^4But ye are forgers of lies, ye are all physicians of no value.

^5O that ye would altogether hold your peace! and it should be your wisdom.

^6Hear now my reasoning, and hearken to the pleadings of my lips.

^7Will ye speak wickedly for God? and talk deceitfully for him?

^8Will ye accept his person? will ye contend for God?

^9Is it good that he should search you out? or as one man mocketh another, do ye so mock him?

^10He will surely reprove you, if ye do secretly accept persons.

^11Shall not his excellency make you afraid? and his dread fall upon you?

^12Your remembrances are like unto ashes, your bodies to bodies of clay.

^13Hold your peace, let me alone, that I may speak, and let come on me what will.

^14Wherefore do I take my flesh in my teeth, and put my life in mine hand?

^15Though he slay me, yet will I trust in him: but I will maintain mine own ways before him.

^16He also shall be my salvation: for an hypocrite shall not come before him.

^17Hear diligently my speech, and my declaration with your ears.

^18Behold now, I have ordered my cause; I know that I shall be justified.

^19Who is he that will plead with me? for now, if I hold my tongue, I shall give up the ghost.

^20Only do not two things unto me: then will I not hide myself from thee.

^21Withdraw thine hand far from me: and let not thy dread make me afraid.

^22Then call thou, and I will answer: or let me speak, and answer thou me.

^23How many are mine iniquities and sins? make me to know my transgression and my sin.

^24Wherefore hidest thou thy face, and holdest me for thine enemy?

^25Wilt thou break a leaf driven to and fro? and wilt thou pursue the dry stubble?

^26For thou writest bitter things against me, and makest me to possess the iniquities of my youth.

^27Thou puttest my feet also in the stocks, and lookest narrowly unto all my paths; thou settest a print upon the heels of my feet.

^28And he, as a rotten thing, consumeth, as a garment that is moth eaten.

Job 14

14^1Man that is born of a woman is of few days and full of trouble.

^2He cometh forth like a flower, and is cut down: he fleeth also as a shadow, and continueth not.

^3And doth thou open thine eyes upon such an one, and bringest me into judgment with thee?

^4Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean? not one.

^5Seeing his days are determined, the number of his months are with thee, thou hast appointed his bounds that he cannot pass;

^6Turn from him, that he may rest, till he shall accomplish, as an hireling, his day.

^7For there is hope of a tree, if it be cut down, that it will sprout again, and that the tender branch thereof will not cease.

^8Though the root thereof wax old in the earth, and the stock thereof die in the ground;

^9Yet through the scent of water it will bud, and bring forth boughs like a plant.

^10But man dieth, and wasteth away: yea, man giveth up the ghost, and where is he?

^11As the waters fail from the sea, and the flood decayeth and drieth up:

^12So man lieth down, and riseth not: till the heavens be no more, they shall not awake, nor be raised out of their sleep.

^13O that thou wouldest hide me in the grave, that thou wouldest keep me secret, until thy wrath be past, that thou wouldest appoint me a set time, and remember me!

^14If a man die, shall he live again? all the days of my appointed time will I wait, till my change come.

^15Thou shalt call, and I will answer thee: thou wilt have a desire to the work of thine hands.

^16For now thou numberest my steps: dost thou not watch over my sin?

^17My transgression is sealed up in a bag, and thou sewest up mine iniquity.

^18And surely the mountains falling cometh to nought, and the rock is removed out of his place.

^19The waters wear the stones: thou washest away the things which grow out of the dust of the earth; and thou destroyest the hope of man.

^20Thou prevailest for ever against him, and he passeth: thou changest his countenance, and sendest him away.

^21His sons come to honour, and he knoweth it not; and they are brought low, but he perceiveth it not of them.

^22But his flesh upon him shall have pain, and his soul within him shall mourn.

Job 15

15^1Then answered Eliphaz the Temanite, and said,

^2Should a wise man utter vain knowledge, and fill his belly with the east wind?

^3Should he reason with unprofitable talk? or with speeches wherewith he can do no good?

^4Yea, thou castest off fear, and restrainest prayer before God.

^5For thy mouth uttereth thine iniquity, and thou choosest the tongue of the crafty.

^6Thine own mouth condemneth thee, and not I: yea, thine own lips testify against thee.

^7Art thou the first man that was born? or wast thou made before the hills?

^8Hast thou heard the secret of God? and dost thou restrain wisdom to thyself?

^9What knowest thou, that we know not? what understandest thou, which is not in us?

^10With us are both the grayheaded and very aged men, much elder than thy father.

^11Are the consolations of God small with thee? is there any secret thing with thee?

^12Why doth thine heart carry thee away? and what do thy eyes wink at,

^13That thou turnest thy spirit against God, and lettest such words go out of thy mouth?

^14What is man, that he should be clean? and he which is born of a woman, that he should be righteous?

^15Behold, he putteth no trust in his saints; yea, the heavens are not clean in his sight.

^16How much more abominable and filthy is man, which drinketh iniquity like water?

^17I will shew thee, hear me; and that which I have seen I will declare;

^18Which wise men have told from their fathers, and have not hid it:

^19Unto whom alone the earth was given, and no stranger passed among them.

^20The wicked man travaileth with pain all his days, and the number of years is hidden to the oppressor.

^21A dreadful sound is in his ears: in prosperity the destroyer shall come upon him.

^22He believeth not that he shall return out of darkness, and he is waited for of the sword.

^23He wandereth abroad for bread, saying, Where is it? he knoweth that the day of darkness is ready at his hand.

^24Trouble and anguish shall make him afraid; they shall prevail against him, as a king ready to the battle.

^25For he stretcheth out his hand against God, and strengtheneth himself against the Almighty.

^26He runneth upon him, even on his neck, upon the thick bosses of his bucklers:

^27Because he covereth his face with his fatness, and maketh collops of fat on his flanks.

^28And he dwelleth in desolate cities, and in houses which no man inhabiteth, which are ready to become heaps.

^29He shall not be rich, neither shall his substance continue, neither shall he prolong the perfection thereof upon the earth.

^30He shall not depart out of darkness; the flame shall dry up his branches, and by the breath of his mouth shall he go away.

^31Let not him that is deceived trust in vanity: for vanity shall be his recompence.

^32It shall be accomplished before his time, and his branch shall not be green.

^33He shall shake off his unripe grape as the vine, and shall cast off his flower as the olive.

^34For the congregation of hypocrites shall be desolate, and fire shall consume the tabernacles of bribery.

^35They conceive mischief, and bring forth vanity, and their belly prepareth deceit.

Job 16

16^1Then Job answered and said,

^2I have heard many such things: miserable comforters are ye all.

^3Shall vain words have an end? or what emboldeneth thee that thou answerest?

^4I also could speak as ye do: if your soul were in my soul’s stead, I could heap up words against you, and shake mine head at you.

^5But I would strengthen you with my mouth, and the moving of my lips should asswage your grief.

^6Though I speak, my grief is not asswaged: and though I forbear, what am I eased?

^7But now he hath made me weary: thou hast made desolate all my company.

^8And thou hast filled me with wrinkles, which is a witness against me: and my leanness rising up in me beareth witness to my face.

^9He teareth me in his wrath, who hateth me: he gnasheth upon me with his teeth; mine enemy sharpeneth his eyes upon me.

^10They have gaped upon me with their mouth; they have smitten me upon the cheek reproachfully; they have gathered themselves together against me.

^11God hath delivered me to the ungodly, and turned me over into the hands of the wicked.

^12I was at ease, but he hath broken me asunder: he hath also taken me by my neck, and shaken me to pieces, and set me up for his mark.

^13His archers compass me round about, he cleaveth my reins asunder, and doth not spare; he poureth out my gall upon the ground.

^14He breaketh me with breach upon breach, he runneth upon me like a giant.

^15I have sewed sackcloth upon my skin, and defiled my horn in the dust.

^16My face is foul with weeping, and on my eyelids is the shadow of death;

^17Not for any injustice in mine hands: also my prayer is pure.

^18O earth, cover not thou my blood, and let my cry have no place.

^19Also now, behold, my witness is in heaven, and my record is on high.

^20My friends scorn me: but mine eye poureth out tears unto God.

^21O that one might plead for a man with God, as a man pleadeth for his neighbour!

^22When a few years are come, then I shall go the way whence I shall not return.

Job 17

17^1My breath is corrupt, my days are extinct, the graves are ready for me.

^2Are there not mockers with me? and doth not mine eye continue in their provocation?

^3Lay down now, put me in a surety with thee; who is he that will strike hands with me?

^4For thou hast hid their heart from understanding: therefore shalt thou not exalt them.

^5He that speaketh flattery to his friends, even the eyes of his children shall fail.

^6He hath made me also a byword of the people; and aforetime I was as a tabret.

^7Mine eye also is dim by reason of sorrow, and all my members are as a shadow.

^8Upright men shall be astonied at this, and the innocent shall stir up himself against the hypocrite.

^9The righteous also shall hold on his way, and he that hath clean hands shall be stronger and stronger.

^10But as for you all, do ye return, and come now: for I cannot find one wise man among you.

^11My days are past, my purposes are broken off, even the thoughts of my heart.

^12They change the night into day: the light is short because of darkness.

^13If I wait, the grave is mine house: I have made my bed in the darkness.

^14I have said to corruption, Thou art my father: to the worm, Thou art my mother, and my sister.

^15And where is now my hope? as for my hope, who shall see it?

^16They shall go down to the bars of the pit, when our rest together is in the dust.

Job 18

18^1Then answered Bildad the Shuhite, and said,

^2How long will it be ere ye make an end of words? mark, and afterwards we will speak.

^3Wherefore are we counted as beasts, and reputed vile in your sight?

^4He teareth himself in his anger: shall the earth be forsaken for thee? and shall the rock be removed out of his place?

^5Yea, the light of the wicked shall be put out, and the spark of his fire shall not shine.

^6The light shall be dark in his tabernacle, and his candle shall be put out with him.

^7The steps of his strength shall be straitened, and his own counsel shall cast him down.

^8For he is cast into a net by his own feet, and he walketh upon a snare.

^9The gin shall take him by the heel, and the robber shall prevail against him.

^10The snare is laid for him in the ground, and a trap for him in the way.

^11Terrors shall make him afraid on every side, and shall drive him to his feet.

^12His strength shall be hungerbitten, and destruction shall be ready at his side.

^13It shall devour the strength of his skin: even the firstborn of death shall devour his strength.

^14His confidence shall be rooted out of his tabernacle, and it shall bring him to the king of terrors.

^15It shall dwell in his tabernacle, because it is none of his: brimstone shall be scattered upon his habitation.

^16His roots shall be dried up beneath, and above shall his branch be cut off.

^17His remembrance shall perish from the earth, and he shall have no name in the street.

^18He shall be driven from light into darkness, and chased out of the world.

^19He shall neither have son nor nephew among his people, nor any remaining in his dwellings.

^20They that come after him shall be astonied at his day, as they that went before were affrighted.

^21Surely such are the dwellings of the wicked, and this is the place of him that knoweth not God.

Job 19

19^1Then Job answered and said,

^2How long will ye vex my soul, and break me in pieces with words?

^3These ten times have ye reproached me: ye are not ashamed that ye make yourselves strange to me.

^4And be it indeed that I have erred, mine error remaineth with myself.

^5If indeed ye will magnify yourselves against me, and plead against me my reproach:

^6Know now that God hath overthrown me, and hath compassed me with his net.

^7Behold, I cry out of wrong, but I am not heard: I cry aloud, but there is no judgment.

^8He hath fenced up my way that I cannot pass, and he hath set darkness in my paths.

^9He hath stripped me of my glory, and taken the crown from my head.

^10He hath destroyed me on every side, and I am gone: and mine hope hath he removed like a tree.

^11He hath also kindled his wrath against me, and he counteth me unto him as one of his enemies.

^12His troops come together, and raise up their way against me, and encamp round about my tabernacle.

^13He hath put my brethren far from me, and mine acquaintance are verily estranged from me.

^14My kinsfolk have failed, and my familiar friends have forgotten me.

^15They that dwell in mine house, and my maids, count me for a stranger: I am an alien in their sight.

^16I called my servant, and he gave me no answer; I intreated him with my mouth.

^17My breath is strange to my wife, though I intreated for the children’s sake of mine own body.

^18Yea, young children despised me; I arose, and they spake against me.

^19All my inward friends abhorred me: and they whom I loved are turned against me.

^20My bone cleaveth to my skin and to my flesh, and I am escaped with the skin of my teeth.

^21Have pity upon me, have pity upon me, O ye my friends; for the hand of God hath touched me.

^22Why do ye persecute me as God, and are not satisfied with my flesh?

^23Oh that my words were now written! oh that they were printed in a book!

^24That they were graven with an iron pen and lead in the rock for ever!

^25For I know that my redeemer liveth, and that he shall stand at the latter day upon the earth:

^26And though after my skin worms destroy this body, yet in my flesh shall I see God:

^27Whom I shall see for myself, and mine eyes shall behold, and not another; though my reins be consumed within me.

^28But ye should say, Why persecute we him, seeing the root of the matter is found in me?

^29Be ye afraid of the sword: for wrath bringeth the punishments of the sword, that ye may know there is a judgment.

Job 20

20^1Then answered Zophar the Naamathite, and said,

^2Therefore do my thoughts cause me to answer, and for this I make haste.

^3I have heard the check of my reproach, and the spirit of my understanding causeth me to answer.

^4Knowest thou not this of old, since man was placed upon earth,

^5That the triumphing of the wicked is short, and the joy of the hypocrite but for a moment?

^6Though his excellency mount up to the heavens, and his head reach unto the clouds;

^7Yet he shall perish for ever like his own dung: they which have seen him shall say, Where is he?

^8He shall fly away as a dream, and shall not be found: yea, he shall be chased away as a vision of the night.

^9The eye also which saw him shall see him no more; neither shall his place any more behold him.

^10His children shall seek to please the poor, and his hands shall restore their goods.

^11His bones are full of the sin of his youth, which shall lie down with him in the dust.

^12Though wickedness be sweet in his mouth, though he hide it under his tongue;

^13Though he spare it, and forsake it not; but keep it still within his mouth:

^14Yet his meat in his bowels is turned, it is the gall of asps within him.

^15He hath swallowed down riches, and he shall vomit them up again: God shall cast them out of his belly.

^16He shall suck the poison of asps: the viper’s tongue shall slay him.

^17He shall not see the rivers, the floods, the brooks of honey and butter.

^18That which he laboured for shall he restore, and shall not swallow it down: according to his substance shall the restitution be, and he shall not rejoice therein.

^19Because he hath oppressed and hath forsaken the poor; because he hath violently taken away an house which he builded not;

^20Surely he shall not feel quietness in his belly, he shall not save of that which he desired.

^21There shall none of his meat be left; therefore shall no man look for his goods.

^22In the fulness of his sufficiency he shall be in straits: every hand of the wicked shall come upon him.

^23When he is about to fill his belly, God shall cast the fury of his wrath upon him, and shall rain it upon him while he is eating.

^24He shall flee from the iron weapon, and the bow of steel shall strike him through.

^25It is drawn, and cometh out of the body; yea, the glittering sword cometh out of his gall: terrors are upon him.

^26All darkness shall be hid in his secret places: a fire not blown shall consume him; it shall go ill with him that is left in his tabernacle.

^27The heaven shall reveal his iniquity; and the earth shall rise up against him.

^28The increase of his house shall depart, and his goods shall flow away in the day of his wrath.

^29This is the portion of a wicked man from God, and the heritage appointed unto him by God.

Job 21

21^1But Job answered and said,

^2Hear diligently my speech, and let this be your consolations.

^3Suffer me that I may speak; and after that I have spoken, mock on.

^4As for me, is my complaint to man? and if it were so, why should not my spirit be troubled?

^5Mark me, and be astonished, and lay your hand upon your mouth.

^6Even when I remember I am afraid, and trembling taketh hold on my flesh.

^7Wherefore do the wicked live, become old, yea, are mighty in power?

^8Their seed is established in their sight with them, and their offspring before their eyes.

^9Their houses are safe from fear, neither is the rod of God upon them.

^10Their bull gendereth, and faileth not; their cow calveth, and casteth not her calf.

^11They send forth their little ones like a flock, and their children dance.

^12They take the timbrel and harp, and rejoice at the sound of the organ.

^13They spend their days in wealth, and in a moment go down to the grave.

^14Therefore they say unto God, Depart from us; for we desire not the knowledge of thy ways.

^15What is the Almighty, that we should serve him? and what profit should we have, if we pray unto him?

^16Lo, their good is not in their hand: the counsel of the wicked is far from me.

^17How oft is the candle of the wicked put out! and how oft cometh their destruction upon them! God distributeth sorrows in his anger.

^18They are as stubble before the wind, and as chaff that the storm carrieth away.

^19God layeth up his iniquity for his children: he rewardeth him, and he shall know it.

^20His eyes shall see his destruction, and he shall drink of the wrath of the Almighty.

^21For what pleasure hath he in his house after him, when the number of his months is cut off in the midst?

^22Shall any teach God knowledge? seeing he judgeth those that are high.

^23One dieth in his full strength, being wholly at ease and quiet.

^24His breasts are full of milk, and his bones are moistened with marrow.

^25And another dieth in the bitterness of his soul, and never eateth with pleasure.

^26They shall lie down alike in the dust, and the worms shall cover them.

^27Behold, I know your thoughts, and the devices which ye wrongfully imagine against me.

^28For ye say, Where is the house of the prince? and where are the dwelling places of the wicked?

^29Have ye not asked them that go by the way? and do ye not know their tokens,

^30That the wicked is reserved to the day of destruction? they shall be brought forth to the day of wrath.

^31Who shall declare his way to his face? and who shall repay him what he hath done?

^32Yet shall he be brought to the grave, and shall remain in the tomb.

^33The clods of the valley shall be sweet unto him, and every man shall draw after him, as there are innumerable before him.

^34How then comfort ye me in vain, seeing in your answers there remaineth falsehood?

Job 22

22^1Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered and said,

^2Can a man be profitable unto God, as he that is wise may be profitable unto himself?

^3Is it any pleasure to the Almighty, that thou art righteous? or is it gain to him, that thou makest thy ways perfect?

^4Will he reprove thee for fear of thee? will he enter with thee into judgment?

^5Is not thy wickedness great? and thine iniquities infinite?

^6For thou hast taken a pledge from thy brother for nought, and stripped the naked of their clothing.

^7Thou hast not given water to the weary to drink, and thou hast withholden bread from the hungry.

^8But as for the mighty man, he had the earth; and the honourable man dwelt in it.

^9Thou hast sent widows away empty, and the arms of the fatherless have been broken.

^10Therefore snares are round about thee, and sudden fear troubleth thee;

^11Or darkness, that thou canst not see; and abundance of waters cover thee.

^12Is not God in the height of heaven? and behold the height of the stars, how high they are!

^13And thou sayest, How doth God know? can he judge through the dark cloud?

^14Thick clouds are a covering to him, that he seeth not; and he walketh in the circuit of heaven.

^15Hast thou marked the old way which wicked men have trodden?

^16Which were cut down out of time, whose foundation was overflown with a flood:

^17Which said unto God, Depart from us: and what can the Almighty do for them?

^18Yet he filled their houses with good things: but the counsel of the wicked is far from me.

^19The righteous see it, and are glad: and the innocent laugh them to scorn.

^20Whereas our substance is not cut down, but the remnant of them the fire consumeth.

^21Acquaint now thyself with him, and be at peace: thereby good shall come unto thee.

^22Receive, I pray thee, the law from his mouth, and lay up his words in thine heart.

^23If thou return to the Almighty, thou shalt be built up, thou shalt put away iniquity far from thy tabernacles.

^24Then shalt thou lay up gold as dust, and the gold of Ophir as the stones of the brooks.

^25Yea, the Almighty shall be thy defence, and thou shalt have plenty of silver.

^26For then shalt thou have thy delight in the Almighty, and shalt lift up thy face unto God.

^27Thou shalt make thy prayer unto him, and he shall hear thee, and thou shalt pay thy vows.

^28Thou shalt also decree a thing, and it shall be established unto thee: and the light shall shine upon thy ways.

^29When men are cast down, then thou shalt say, There is lifting up; and he shall save the humble person.

^30He shall deliver the island of the innocent: and it is delivered by the pureness of thine hands.

Job 23

23^1Then Job answered and said,

^2Even to day is my complaint bitter: my stroke is heavier than my groaning.

^3Oh that I knew where I might find him! that I might come even to his seat!

^4I would order my cause before him, and fill my mouth with arguments.

^5I would know the words which he would answer me, and understand what he would say unto me.

^6Will he plead against me with his great power? No; but he would put strength in me.

^7There the righteous might dispute with him; so should I be delivered for ever from my judge.

^8Behold, I go forward, but he is not there; and backward, but I cannot perceive him:

^9On the left hand, where he doth work, but I cannot behold him: he hideth himself on the right hand, that I cannot see him:

^10But he knoweth the way that I take: when he hath tried me, I shall come forth as gold.

^11My foot hath held his steps, his way have I kept, and not declined.

^12Neither have I gone back from the commandment of his lips; I have esteemed the words of his mouth more than my necessary food.

^13But he is in one mind, and who can turn him? and what his soul desireth, even that he doeth.

^14For he performeth the thing that is appointed for me: and many such things are with him.

^15Therefore am I troubled at his presence: when I consider, I am afraid of him.

^16For God maketh my heart soft, and the Almighty troubleth me:

^17Because I was not cut off before the darkness, neither hath he covered the darkness from my face.

Job 24

24^1Why, seeing times are not hidden from the Almighty, do they that know him not see his days?

^2Some remove the landmarks; they violently take away flocks, and feed thereof.

^3They drive away the ass of the fatherless, they take the widow’s ox for a pledge.

^4They turn the needy out of the way: the poor of the earth hide themselves together.

^5Behold, as wild asses in the desert, go they forth to their work; rising betimes for a prey: the wilderness yieldeth food for them and for their children.

^6They reap every one his corn in the field: and they gather the vintage of the wicked.

^7They cause the naked to lodge without clothing, that they have no covering in the cold.

^8They are wet with the showers of the mountains, and embrace the rock for want of a shelter.

^9They pluck the fatherless from the breast, and take a pledge of the poor.

^10They cause him to go naked without clothing, and they take away the sheaf from the hungry;

^11Which make oil within their walls, and tread their winepresses, and suffer thirst.

^12Men groan from out of the city, and the soul of the wounded crieth out: yet God layeth not folly to them.

^13They are of those that rebel against the light; they know not the ways thereof, nor abide in the paths thereof.

^14The murderer rising with the light killeth the poor and needy, and in the night is as a thief.

^15The eye also of the adulterer waiteth for the twilight, saying, No eye shall see me: and disguiseth his face.

^16In the dark they dig through houses, which they had marked for themselves in the daytime: they know not the light.

^17For the morning is to them even as the shadow of death: if one know them, they are in the terrors of the shadow of death.

^18He is swift as the waters; their portion is cursed in the earth: he beholdeth not the way of the vineyards.

^19Drought and heat consume the snow waters: so doth the grave those which have sinned.

^20The womb shall forget him; the worm shall feed sweetly on him; he shall be no more remembered; and wickedness shall be broken as a tree.

^21He evil entreateth the barren that beareth not: and doeth not good to the widow.

^22He draweth also the mighty with his power: he riseth up, and no man is sure of life.

^23Though it be given him to be in safety, whereon he resteth; yet his eyes are upon their ways.

^24They are exalted for a little while, but are gone and brought low; they are taken out of the way as all other, and cut off as the tops of the ears of corn.

^25And if it be not so now, who will make me a liar, and make my speech nothing worth?

Job 25

25^1Then answered Bildad the Shuhite, and said,

^2Dominion and fear are with him, he maketh peace in his high places.

^3Is there any number of his armies? and upon whom doth not his light arise?

^4How then can man be justified with God? or how can he be clean that is born of a woman?

^5Behold even to the moon, and it shineth not; yea, the stars are not pure in his sight.

^6How much less man, that is a worm? and the son of man, which is a worm?

Job 26

26^1But Job answered and said,

^2How hast thou helped him that is without power? how savest thou the arm that hath no strength?

^3How hast thou counselled him that hath no wisdom? and how hast thou plentifully declared the thing as it is?

^4To whom hast thou uttered words? and whose spirit came from thee?

^5Dead things are formed from under the waters, and the inhabitants thereof.

^6Hell is naked before him, and destruction hath no covering.

^7He stretcheth out the north over the empty place, and hangeth the earth upon nothing.

^8He bindeth up the waters in his thick clouds; and the cloud is not rent under them.

^9He holdeth back the face of his throne, and spreadeth his cloud upon it.

^10He hath compassed the waters with bounds, until the day and night come to an end.

^11The pillars of heaven tremble and are astonished at his reproof.

^12He divideth the sea with his power, and by his understanding he smiteth through the proud.

^13By his spirit he hath garnished the heavens; his hand hath formed the crooked serpent.

^14Lo, these are parts of his ways: but how little a portion is heard of him? but the thunder of his power who can understand?

Job 27

27^1Moreover Job continued his parable, and said,

^2As God liveth, who hath taken away my judgment; and the Almighty, who hath vexed my soul;

^3All the while my breath is in me, and the spirit of God is in my nostrils;

^4My lips shall not speak wickedness, nor my tongue utter deceit.

^5God forbid that I should justify you: till I die I will not remove mine integrity from me.

^6My righteousness I hold fast, and will not let it go: my heart shall not reproach me so long as I live.

^7Let mine enemy be as the wicked, and he that riseth up against me as the unrighteous.

^8For what is the hope of the hypocrite, though he hath gained, when God taketh away his soul?

^9Will God hear his cry when trouble cometh upon him?

^10Will he delight himself in the Almighty? will he always call upon God?

^11I will teach you by the hand of God: that which is with the Almighty will I not conceal.

^12Behold, all ye yourselves have seen it; why then are ye thus altogether vain?

^13This is the portion of a wicked man with God, and the heritage of oppressors, which they shall receive of the Almighty.

^14If his children be multiplied, it is for the sword: and his offspring shall not be satisfied with bread.

^15Those that remain of him shall be buried in death: and his widows shall not weep.

^16Though he heap up silver as the dust, and prepare raiment as the clay;

^17He may prepare it, but the just shall put it on, and the innocent shall divide the silver.

^18He buildeth his house as a moth, and as a booth that the keeper maketh.

^19The rich man shall lie down, but he shall not be gathered: he openeth his eyes, and he is not.

^20Terrors take hold on him as waters, a tempest stealeth him away in the night.

^21The east wind carrieth him away, and he departeth: and as a storm hurleth him out of his place.

^22For God shall cast upon him, and not spare: he would fain flee out of his hand.

^23Men shall clap their hands at him, and shall hiss him out of his place.

Job 28

28^1Surely there is a vein for the silver, and a place for gold where they fine it.

^2Iron is taken out of the earth, and brass is molten out of the stone.

^3He setteth an end to darkness, and searcheth out all perfection: the stones of darkness, and the shadow of death.

^4The flood breaketh out from the inhabitant; even the waters forgotten of the foot: they are dried up, they are gone away from men.

^5As for the earth, out of it cometh bread: and under it is turned up as it were fire.

^6The stones of it are the place of sapphires: and it hath dust of gold.

^7There is a path which no fowl knoweth, and which the vulture’s eye hath not seen:

^8The lion’s whelps have not trodden it, nor the fierce lion passed by it.

^9He putteth forth his hand upon the rock; he overturneth the mountains by the roots.

^10He cutteth out rivers among the rocks; and his eye seeth every precious thing.

^11He bindeth the floods from overflowing; and the thing that is hid bringeth he forth to light.

^12But where shall wisdom be found? and where is the place of understanding?

^13Man knoweth not the price thereof; neither is it found in the land of the living.

^14The depth saith, It is not in me: and the sea saith, It is not with me.

^15It cannot be gotten for gold, neither shall silver be weighed for the price thereof.

^16It cannot be valued with the gold of Ophir, with the precious onyx, or the sapphire.

^17The gold and the crystal cannot equal it: and the exchange of it shall not be for jewels of fine gold.

^18No mention shall be made of coral, or of pearls: for the price of wisdom is above rubies.

^19The topaz of Ethiopia shall not equal it, neither shall it be valued with pure gold.

^20Whence then cometh wisdom? and where is the place of understanding?

^21Seeing it is hid from the eyes of all living, and kept close from the fowls of the air.

^22Destruction and death say, We have heard the fame thereof with our ears.

^23God understandeth the way thereof, and he knoweth the place thereof.

^24For he looketh to the ends of the earth, and seeth under the whole heaven;

^25To make the weight for the winds; and he weigheth the waters by measure.

^26When he made a decree for the rain, and a way for the lightning of the thunder:

^27Then did he see it, and declare it; he prepared it, yea, and searched it out.

^28And unto man he said, Behold, the fear of the Lord, that is wisdom; and to depart from evil is understanding.

Job 29

29^1Moreover Job continued his parable, and said,

^2Oh that I were as in months past, as in the days when God preserved me;

^3When his candle shined upon my head, and when by his light I walked through darkness;

^4As I was in the days of my youth, when the secret of God was upon my tabernacle;

^5When the Almighty was yet with me, when my children were about me;

^6When I washed my steps with butter, and the rock poured me out rivers of oil;

^7When I went out to the gate through the city, when I prepared my seat in the street!

^8The young men saw me, and hid themselves: and the aged arose, and stood up.

^9The princes refrained talking, and laid their hand on their mouth.

^10The nobles held their peace, and their tongue cleaved to the roof of their mouth.

^11When the ear heard me, then it blessed me; and when the eye saw me, it gave witness to me:

^12Because I delivered the poor that cried, and the fatherless, and him that had none to help him.

^13The blessing of him that was ready to perish came upon me: and I caused the widow’s heart to sing for joy.

^14I put on righteousness, and it clothed me: my judgment was as a robe and a diadem.

^15I was eyes to the blind, and feet was I to the lame.

^16I was a father to the poor: and the cause which I knew not I searched out.

^17And I brake the jaws of the wicked, and plucked the spoil out of his teeth.

^18Then I said, I shall die in my nest, and I shall multiply my days as the sand.

^19My root was spread out by the waters, and the dew lay all night upon my branch.

^20My glory was fresh in me, and my bow was renewed in my hand.

^21Unto me men gave ear, and waited, and kept silence at my counsel.

^22After my words they spake not again; and my speech dropped upon them.

^23And they waited for me as for the rain; and they opened their mouth wide as for the latter rain.

^24If I laughed on them, they believed it not; and the light of my countenance they cast not down.

^25I chose out their way, and sat chief, and dwelt as a king in the army, as one that comforteth the mourners.

Job 30

30^1But now they that are younger than I have me in derision, whose fathers I would have disdained to have set with the dogs of my flock.

^2Yea, whereto might the strength of their hands profit me, in whom old age was perished?

^3For want and famine they were solitary; fleeing into the wilderness in former time desolate and waste.

^4Who cut up mallows by the bushes, and juniper roots for their meat.

^5They were driven forth from among men, (they cried after them as after a thief;)

^6To dwell in the cliffs of the valleys, in caves of the earth, and in the rocks.

^7Among the bushes they brayed; under the nettles they were gathered together.

^8They were children of fools, yea, children of base men: they were viler than the earth.

^9And now am I their song, yea, I am their byword.

^10They abhor me, they flee far from me, and spare not to spit in my face.

^11Because he hath loosed my cord, and afflicted me, they have also let loose the bridle before me.

^12Upon my right hand rise the youth; they push away my feet, and they raise up against me the ways of their destruction.

^13They mar my path, they set forward my calamity, they have no helper.

^14They came upon me as a wide breaking in of waters: in the desolation they rolled themselves upon me.

^15Terrors are turned upon me: they pursue my soul as the wind: and my welfare passeth away as a cloud.

^16And now my soul is poured out upon me; the days of affliction have taken hold upon me.

^17My bones are pierced in me in the night season: and my sinews take no rest.

^18By the great force of my disease is my garment changed: it bindeth me about as the collar of my coat.

^19He hath cast me into the mire, and I am become like dust and ashes.

^20I cry unto thee, and thou dost not hear me: I stand up, and thou regardest me not.

^21Thou art become cruel to me: with thy strong hand thou opposest thyself against me.

^22Thou liftest me up to the wind; thou causest me to ride upon it, and dissolvest my substance.

^23For I know that thou wilt bring me to death, and to the house appointed for all living.

^24Howbeit he will not stretch out his hand to the grave, though they cry in his destruction.

^25Did not I weep for him that was in trouble? was not my soul grieved for the poor?

^26When I looked for good, then evil came unto me: and when I waited for light, there came darkness.

^27My bowels boiled, and rested not: the days of affliction prevented me.

^28I went mourning without the sun: I stood up, and I cried in the congregation.

^29I am a brother to dragons, and a companion to owls.

^30My skin is black upon me, and my bones are burned with heat.

^31My harp also is turned to mourning, and my organ into the voice of them that weep.

Job 31

31^1I made a covenant with mine eyes; why then should I think upon a maid?

^2For what portion of God is there from above? and what inheritance of the Almighty from on high?

^3Is not destruction to the wicked? and a strange punishment to the workers of iniquity?

^4Doth not he see my ways, and count all my steps?

^5If I have walked with vanity, or if my foot hath hasted to deceit;

^6Let me be weighed in an even balance that God may know mine integrity.

^7If my step hath turned out of the way, and mine heart walked after mine eyes, and if any blot hath cleaved to mine hands;

^8Then let me sow, and let another eat; yea, let my offspring be rooted out.

^9If mine heart have been deceived by a woman, or if I have laid wait at my neighbour’s door;

^10Then let my wife grind unto another, and let others bow down upon her.

^11For this is an heinous crime; yea, it is an iniquity to be punished by the judges.

^12For it is a fire that consumeth to destruction, and would root out all mine increase.

^13If I did despise the cause of my manservant or of my maidservant, when they contended with me;

^14What then shall I do when God riseth up? and when he visiteth, what shall I answer him?

^15Did not he that made me in the womb make him? and did not one fashion us in the womb?

^16If I have withheld the poor from their desire, or have caused the eyes of the widow to fail;

^17Or have eaten my morsel myself alone, and the fatherless hath not eaten thereof;

^18(For from my youth he was brought up with me, as with a father, and I have guided her from my mother’s womb;)

^19If I have seen any perish for want of clothing, or any poor without covering;

^20If his loins have not blessed me, and if he were not warmed with the fleece of my sheep;

^21If I have lifted up my hand against the fatherless, when I saw my help in the gate:

^22Then let mine arm fall from my shoulder blade, and mine arm be broken from the bone.

^23For destruction from God was a terror to me, and by reason of his highness I could not endure.

^24If I have made gold my hope, or have said to the fine gold, Thou art my confidence;

^25If I rejoice because my wealth was great, and because mine hand had gotten much;

^26If I beheld the sun when it shined, or the moon walking in brightness;

^27And my heart hath been secretly enticed, or my mouth hath kissed my hand:

^28This also were an iniquity to be punished by the judge: for I should have denied the God that is above.

^29If I rejoice at the destruction of him that hated me, or lifted up myself when evil found him:

^30Neither have I suffered my mouth to sin by wishing a curse to his soul.

^31If the men of my tabernacle said not, Oh that we had of his flesh! we cannot be satisfied.

^32The stranger did not lodge in the street: but I opened my doors to the traveller.

^33If I covered my transgressions as Adam, by hiding mine iniquity in my bosom:

^34Did I fear a great multitude, or did the contempt of families terrify me, that I kept silence, and went not out of the door?

^35Oh that one would hear me! behold, my desire is, that the Almighty would answer me, and that mine adversary had written a book.

^36Surely I would take it upon my shoulder, and bind it as a crown to me.

^37I would declare unto him the number of my steps; as a prince would I go near unto him.

^38If my land cry against me, or that the furrows likewise thereof complain;

^39If I have eaten the fruits thereof without money, or have caused the owners thereof to lose their life:

^40Let thistles grow instead of wheat, and cockle instead of barley. The words of Job are ended.

Job 32

32^1So these three men ceased to answer Job, because he was righteous in his own eyes.

^2Then was kindled the wrath of Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite, of the kindred of Ram: against Job was his wrath kindled, because he justified himself rather than God.

^3Also against his three friends was his wrath kindled, because they had found no answer, and yet had condemned Job.

^4Now Elihu had waited till Job had spoken, because they were elder than he.

^5When Elihu saw that there was no answer in the mouth of these three men, then his wrath was kindled.

^6And Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite answered and said, I am young, and ye are very old; wherefore I was afraid, and durst not shew you mine opinion.

^7I said, Days should speak, and multitude of years should teach wisdom.

^8But there is a spirit in man: and the inspiration of the Almighty giveth them understanding.

^9Great men are not always wise: neither do the aged understand judgment.

^10Therefore I said, Hearken to me; I also will shew mine opinion.

^11Behold, I waited for your words; I gave ear to your reasons, whilst ye searched out what to say.

^12Yea, I attended unto you, and, behold, there was none of you that convinced Job, or that answered his words:

^13Lest ye should say, We have found out wisdom: God thrusteth him down, not man.

^14Now he hath not directed his words against me: neither will I answer him with your speeches.

^15They were amazed, they answered no more: they left off speaking.

^16When I had waited, (for they spake not, but stood still, and answered no more;)

^17I said, I will answer also my part, I also will shew mine opinion.

^18For I am full of matter, the spirit within me constraineth me.

^19Behold, my belly is as wine which hath no vent; it is ready to burst like new bottles.

^20I will speak, that I may be refreshed: I will open my lips and answer.

^21Let me not, I pray you, accept any man’s person, neither let me give flattering titles unto man.

^22For I know not to give flattering titles; in so doing my maker would soon take me away.

Job 33

33^1Wherefore, Job, I pray thee, hear my speeches, and hearken to all my words.

^2Behold, now I have opened my mouth, my tongue hath spoken in my mouth.

^3My words shall be of the uprightness of my heart: and my lips shall utter knowledge clearly.

^4The spirit of God hath made me, and the breath of the Almighty hath given me life.

^5If thou canst answer me, set thy words in order before me, stand up.

^6Behold, I am according to thy wish in God’s stead: I also am formed out of the clay.

^7Behold, my terror shall not make thee afraid, neither shall my hand be heavy upon thee.

^8Surely thou hast spoken in mine hearing, and I have heard the voice of thy words, saying,

^9I am clean without transgression, I am innocent; neither is there iniquity in me.

^10Behold, he findeth occasions against me, he counteth me for his enemy,

^11He putteth my feet in the stocks, he marketh all my paths.

^12Behold, in this thou art not just: I will answer thee, that God is greater than man.

^13Why dost thou strive against him? for he giveth not account of any of his matters.

^14For God speaketh once, yea twice, yet man perceiveth it not.

^15In a dream, in a vision of the night, when deep sleep falleth upon men, in slumberings upon the bed;

^16Then he openeth the ears of men, and sealeth their instruction,

^17That he may withdraw man from his purpose, and hide pride from man.

^18He keepeth back his soul from the pit, and his life from perishing by the sword.

^19He is chastened also with pain upon his bed, and the multitude of his bones with strong pain:

^20So that his life abhorreth bread, and his soul dainty meat.

^21His flesh is consumed away, that it cannot be seen; and his bones that were not seen stick out.

^22Yea, his soul draweth near unto the grave, and his life to the destroyers.

^23If there be a messenger with him, an interpreter, one among a thousand, to shew unto man his uprightness:

^24Then he is gracious unto him, and saith, Deliver him from going down to the pit: I have found a ransom.

^25His flesh shall be fresher than a child’s: he shall return to the days of his youth:

^26He shall pray unto God, and he will be favourable unto him: and he shall see his face with joy: for he will render unto man his righteousness.

^27He looketh upon men, and if any say, I have sinned, and perverted that which was right, and it profited me not;

^28He will deliver his soul from going into the pit, and his life shall see the light.

^29Lo, all these things worketh God oftentimes with man,

^30To bring back his soul from the pit, to be enlightened with the light of the living.

^31Mark well, O Job, hearken unto me: hold thy peace, and I will speak.

^32If thou hast anything to say, answer me: speak, for I desire to justify thee.

^33If not, hearken unto me: hold thy peace, and I shall teach thee wisdom.

Job 34

34^1Furthermore Elihu answered and said,

^2Hear my words, O ye wise men; and give ear unto me, ye that have knowledge.

^3For the ear trieth words, as the mouth tasteth meat.

^4Let us choose to us judgment: let us know among ourselves what is good.

^5For Job hath said, I am righteous: and God hath taken away my judgment.

^6Should I lie against my right? my wound is incurable without transgression.

^7What man is like Job, who drinketh up scorning like water?

^8Which goeth in company with the workers of iniquity, and walketh with wicked men.

^9For he hath said, It profiteth a man nothing that he should delight himself with God.

^10Therefore hearken unto me ye men of understanding: far be it from God, that he should do wickedness; and from the Almighty, that he should commit iniquity.

^11For the work of a man shall he render unto him, and cause every man to find according to his ways.

^12Yea, surely God will not do wickedly, neither will the Almighty pervert judgment.

^13Who hath given him a charge over the earth? or who hath disposed the whole world?

^14If he set his heart upon man, if he gather unto himself his spirit and his breath;

^15All flesh shall perish together, and man shall turn again unto dust.

^16If now thou hast understanding, hear this: hearken to the voice of my words.

^17Shall even he that hateth right govern? and wilt thou condemn him that is most just?

^18Is it fit to say to a king, Thou art wicked? and to princes, Ye are ungodly?

^19How much less to him that accepteth not the persons of princes, nor regardeth the rich more than the poor? for they all are the work of his hands.

^20In a moment shall they die, and the people shall be troubled at midnight, and pass away: and the mighty shall be taken away without hand.

^21For his eyes are upon the ways of man, and he seeth all his goings.

^22There is no darkness, nor shadow of death, where the workers of iniquity may hide themselves.

^23For he will not lay upon man more than right; that he should enter into judgment with God.

^24He shall break in pieces mighty men without number, and set others in their stead.

^25Therefore he knoweth their works, and he overturneth them in the night, so that they are destroyed.

^26He striketh them as wicked men in the open sight of others;

^27Because they turned back from him, and would not consider any of his ways:

^28So that they cause the cry of the poor to come unto him, and he heareth the cry of the afflicted.

^29When he giveth quietness, who then can make trouble? and when he hideth his face, who then can behold him? whether it be done against a nation, or against a man only:

^30That the hypocrite reign not, lest the people be ensnared.

^31Surely it is meet to be said unto God, I have borne chastisement, I will not offend any more:

^32That which I see not teach thou me: if I have done iniquity, I will do no more.

^33Should it be according to thy mind? he will recompense it, whether thou refuse, or whether thou choose; and not I: therefore speak what thou knowest.

^34Let men of understanding tell me, and let a wise man hearken unto me.

^35Job hath spoken without knowledge, and his words were without wisdom.

^36My desire is that Job may be tried unto the end because of his answers for wicked men.

^37For he addeth rebellion unto his sin, he clappeth his hands among us, and multiplieth his words against God.

Job 35

35^1Elihu spake moreover, and said,

^2Thinkest thou this to be right, that thou saidst, My righteousness is more than God’s?

^3For thou saidst, What advantage will it be unto thee? and, What profit shall I have, if I be cleansed from my sin?

^4I will answer thee, and thy companions with thee.

^5Look unto the heavens, and see; and behold the clouds which are higher than thou.

^6If thou sinnest, what doest thou against him? or if thy transgressions be multiplied, what doest thou unto him?

^7If thou be righteous, what givest thou him? or what receiveth he of thine hand?

^8Thy wickedness may hurt a man as thou art; and thy righteousness may profit the son of man.

^9By reason of the multitude of oppressions they make the oppressed to cry: they cry out by reason of the arm of the mighty.

^10But none saith, Where is God my maker, who giveth songs in the night;

^11Who teacheth us more than the beasts of the earth, and maketh us wiser than the fowls of heaven?

^12There they cry, but none giveth answer, because of the pride of evil men.

^13Surely God will not hear vanity, neither will the Almighty regard it.

^14Although thou sayest thou shalt not see him, yet judgment is before him; therefore trust thou in him.

^15But now, because it is not so, he hath visited in his anger; yet he knoweth it not in great extremity:

^16Therefore doth Job open his mouth in vain; he multiplieth words without knowledge.

Job 36

36^1Elihu also proceeded, and said,

^2Suffer me a little, and I will shew thee that I have yet to speak on God’s behalf.

^3I will fetch my knowledge from afar, and will ascribe righteousness to my Maker.

^4For truly my words shall not be false: he that is perfect in knowledge is with thee.

^5Behold, God is mighty, and despiseth not any: he is mighty in strength and wisdom.

^6He preserveth not the life of the wicked: but giveth right to the poor.

^7He withdraweth not his eyes from the righteous: but with kings are they on the throne; yea, he doth establish them for ever, and they are exalted.

^8And if they be bound in fetters, and be holden in cords of affliction;

^9Then he sheweth them their work, and their transgressions that they have exceeded.

^10He openeth also their ear to discipline, and commandeth that they return from iniquity.

^11If they obey and serve him, they shall spend their days in prosperity, and their years in pleasures.

^12But if they obey not, they shall perish by the sword, and they shall die without knowledge.

^13But the hypocrites in heart heap up wrath: they cry not when he bindeth them.

^14They die in youth, and their life is among the unclean.

^15He delivereth the poor in his affliction, and openeth their ears in oppression.

^16Even so would he have removed thee out of the strait into a broad place, where there is no straitness; and that which should be set on thy table should be full of fatness.

^17But thou hast fulfilled the judgment of the wicked: judgment and justice take hold on thee.

^18Because there is wrath, beware lest he take thee away with his stroke: then a great ransom cannot deliver thee.

^19Will he esteem thy riches? no, not gold, nor all the forces of strength.

^20Desire not the night, when people are cut off in their place.

^21Take heed, regard not iniquity: for this hast thou chosen rather than affliction.

^22Behold, God exalteth by his power: who teacheth like him?

^23Who hath enjoined him his way? or who can say, Thou hast wrought iniquity?

^24Remember that thou magnify his work, which men behold.

^25Every man may see it; man may behold it afar off.

^26Behold, God is great, and we know him not, neither can the number of his years be searched out.

^27For he maketh small the drops of water: they pour down rain according to the vapour thereof:

^28Which the clouds do drop and distil upon man abundantly.

^29Also can any understand the spreadings of the clouds, or the noise of his tabernacle?

^30Behold, he spreadeth his light upon it, and covereth the bottom of the sea.

^31For by them judgeth he the people; he giveth meat in abundance.

^32With clouds he covereth the light; and commandeth it not to shine by the cloud that cometh betwixt.

^33The noise thereof sheweth concerning it, the cattle also concerning the vapour.

Job 37

37^1At this also my heart trembleth, and is moved out of his place.

^2Hear attentively the noise of his voice, and the sound that goeth out of his mouth.

^3He directeth it under the whole heaven, and his lightning unto the ends of the earth.

^4After it a voice roareth: he thundereth with the voice of his excellency; and he will not stay them when his voice is heard.

^5God thundereth marvellously with his voice; great things doeth he, which we cannot comprehend.

^6For he saith to the snow, Be thou on the earth; likewise to the small rain, and to the great rain of his strength.

^7He sealeth up the hand of every man; that all men may know his work.

^8Then the beasts go into dens, and remain in their places.

^9Out of the south cometh the whirlwind: and cold out of the north.

^10By the breath of God frost is given: and the breadth of the waters is straitened.

^11Also by watering he wearieth the thick cloud: he scattereth his bright cloud:

^12And it is turned round about by his counsels: that they may do whatsoever he commandeth them upon the face of the world in the earth.

^13He causeth it to come, whether for correction, or for his land, or for mercy.

^14Hearken unto this, O Job: stand still, and consider the wondrous works of God.

^15Dost thou know when God disposed them, and caused the light of his cloud to shine?

^16Dost thou know the balancings of the clouds, the wondrous works of him which is perfect in knowledge?

^17How thy garments are warm, when he quieteth the earth by the south wind?

^18Hast thou with him spread out the sky, which is strong, and as a molten looking glass?

^19Teach us what we shall say unto him; for we cannot order our speech by reason of darkness.

^20Shall it be told him that I speak? if a man speak, surely he shall be swallowed up.

^21And now men see not the bright light which is in the clouds: but the wind passeth, and cleanseth them.

^22Fair weather cometh out of the north: with God is terrible majesty.

^23Touching the Almighty, we cannot find him out: he is excellent in power, and in judgment, and in plenty of justice: he will not afflict.

^24Men do therefore fear him: he respecteth not any that are wise of heart.

Job 38

38^1Then the Lord answered Job out of the whirlwind, and said,

^2Who is this that darkeneth counsel by words without knowledge?

^3Gird up now thy loins like a man; for I will demand of thee, and answer thou me.

^4Where wast thou when I laid the foundations of the earth? declare, if thou hast understanding.

^5Who hath laid the measures thereof, if thou knowest? or who hath stretched the line upon it?

^6Whereupon are the foundations thereof fastened? or who laid the corner stone thereof;

^7When the morning stars sang together, and all the sons of God shouted for joy?

^8Or who shut up the sea with doors, when it brake forth, as if it had issued out of the womb?

^9When I made the cloud the garment thereof, and thick darkness a swaddlingband for it,

^10And brake up for it my decreed place, and set bars and doors,

^11And said, Hitherto shalt thou come, but no further: and here shall thy proud waves be stayed?

^12Hast thou commanded the morning since thy days; and caused the dayspring to know his place;

^13That it might take hold of the ends of the earth, that the wicked might be shaken out of it?

^14It is turned as clay to the seal; and they stand as a garment.

^15And from the wicked their light is withholden, and the high arm shall be broken.

^16Hast thou entered into the springs of the sea? or hast thou walked in the search of the depth?

^17Have the gates of death been opened unto thee? or hast thou seen the doors of the shadow of death?

^18Hast thou perceived the breadth of the earth? declare if thou knowest it all.

^19Where is the way where light dwelleth? and as for darkness, where is the place thereof,

^20That thou shouldest take it to the bound thereof, and that thou shouldest know the paths to the house thereof?

^21Knowest thou it, because thou wast then born? or because the number of thy days is great?

^22Hast thou entered into the treasures of the snow? or hast thou seen the treasures of the hail,

^23Which I have reserved against the time of trouble, against the day of battle and war?

^24By what way is the light parted, which scattereth the east wind upon the earth?

^25Who hath divided a watercourse for the overflowing of waters, or a way for the lightning of thunder;

^26To cause it to rain on the earth, where no man is; on the wilderness, wherein there is no man;

^27To satisfy the desolate and waste ground; and to cause the bud of the tender herb to spring forth?

^28Hath the rain a father? or who hath begotten the drops of dew?

^29Out of whose womb came the ice? and the hoary frost of heaven, who hath gendered it?

^30The waters are hid as with a stone, and the face of the deep is frozen.

^31Canst thou bind the sweet influences of Pleiades, or loose the bands of Orion?

^32Canst thou bring forth Mazzaroth in his season? or canst thou guide Arcturus with his sons?

^33Knowest thou the ordinances of heaven? canst thou set the dominion thereof in the earth?

^34Canst thou lift up thy voice to the clouds, that abundance of waters may cover thee?

^35Canst thou send lightnings, that they may go and say unto thee, Here we are?

^36Who hath put wisdom in the inward parts? or who hath given understanding to the heart?

^37Who can number the clouds in wisdom? or who can stay the bottles of heaven,

^38When the dust groweth into hardness, and the clods cleave fast together?

^39Wilt thou hunt the prey for the lion? or fill the appetite of the young lions,

^40When they couch in their dens, and abide in the covert to lie in wait?

^41Who provideth for the raven his food? when his young ones cry unto God, they wander for lack of meat.

Job 39

39^1Knowest thou the time when the wild goats of the rock bring forth? or canst thou mark when the hinds do calve?

^2Canst thou number the months that they fulfil? or knowest thou the time when they bring forth?

^3They bow themselves, they bring forth their young ones, they cast out their sorrows.

^4Their young ones are in good liking, they grow up with corn; they go forth, and return not unto them.

^5Who hath sent out the wild ass free? or who hath loosed the bands of the wild ass?

^6Whose house I have made the wilderness, and the barren land his dwellings.

^7He scorneth the multitude of the city, neither regardeth he the crying of the driver.

^8The range of the mountains is his pasture, and he searcheth after every green thing.

^9Will the unicorn be willing to serve thee, or abide by thy crib?

^10Canst thou bind the unicorn with his band in the furrow? or will he harrow the valleys after thee?

^11Wilt thou trust him, because his strength is great? or wilt thou leave thy labour to him?

^12Wilt thou believe him, that he will bring home thy seed, and gather it into thy barn?

^13Gavest thou the goodly wings unto the peacocks? or wings and feathers unto the ostrich?

^14Which leaveth her eggs in the earth, and warmeth them in dust,

^15And forgetteth that the foot may crush them, or that the wild beast may break them.

^16She is hardened against her young ones, as though they were not her’s: her labour is in vain without fear;

^17Because God hath deprived her of wisdom, neither hath he imparted to her understanding.

^18What time she lifteth up herself on high, she scorneth the horse and his rider.

^19Hast thou given the horse strength? hast thou clothed his neck with thunder?

^20Canst thou make him afraid as a grasshopper? the glory of his nostrils is terrible.

^21He paweth in the valley, and rejoiceth in his strength: he goeth on to meet the armed men.

^22He mocketh at fear, and is not affrighted; neither turneth he back from the sword.

^23The quiver rattleth against him, the glittering spear and the shield.

^24He swalloweth the ground with fierceness and rage: neither believeth he that it is the sound of the trumpet.

^25He saith among the trumpets, Ha, ha; and he smelleth the battle afar off, the thunder of the captains, and the shouting.

^26Doth the hawk fly by thy wisdom, and stretch her wings toward the south?

^27Doth the eagle mount up at thy command, and make her nest on high?

^28She dwelleth and abideth on the rock, upon the crag of the rock, and the strong place.

^29From thence she seeketh the prey, and her eyes behold afar off.

^30Her young ones also suck up blood: and where the slain are, there is she.

Job 40

40^1Moreover the Lord answered Job, and said,

^2Shall he that contendeth with the Almighty instruct him? he that reproveth God, let him answer it.

^3Then Job answered the Lord, and said,

^4Behold, I am vile; what shall I answer thee? I will lay mine hand upon my mouth.

^5Once have I spoken; but I will not answer: yea, twice; but I will proceed no further.

^6Then answered the Lord unto Job out of the whirlwind, and said,

^7Gird up thy loins now like a man: I will demand of thee, and declare thou unto me.

^8Wilt thou also disannul my judgment? wilt thou condemn me, that thou mayest be righteous?

^9Hast thou an arm like God? or canst thou thunder with a voice like him?

^10Deck thyself now with majesty and excellency; and array thyself with glory and beauty.

^11Cast abroad the rage of thy wrath: and behold every one that is proud, and abase him.

^12Look on every one that is proud, and bring him low; and tread down the wicked in their place.

^13Hide them in the dust together; and bind their faces in secret.

^14Then will I also confess unto thee that thine own right hand can save thee.

^15Behold now behemoth, which I made with thee; he eateth grass as an ox.

^16Lo now, his strength is in his loins, and his force is in the navel of his belly.

^17He moveth his tail like a cedar: the sinews of his stones are wrapped together.

^18His bones are as strong pieces of brass; his bones are like bars of iron.

^19He is the chief of the ways of God: he that made him can make his sword to approach unto him.

^20Surely the mountains bring him forth food, where all the beasts of the field play.

^21He lieth under the shady trees, in the covert of the reed, and fens.

^22The shady trees cover him with their shadow; the willows of the brook compass him about.

^23Behold, he drinketh up a river, and hasteth not: he trusteth that he can draw up Jordan into his mouth.

^24He taketh it with his eyes: his nose pierceth through snares.

Job 41

41^1Canst thou draw out leviathan with an hook? or his tongue with a cord which thou lettest down?

^2Canst thou put an hook into his nose? or bore his jaw through with a thorn?

^3Will he make many supplications unto thee? will he speak soft words unto thee?

^4Will he make a covenant with thee? wilt thou take him for a servant for ever?

^5Wilt thou play with him as with a bird? or wilt thou bind him for thy maidens?

^6Shall the companions make a banquet of him? shall they part him among the merchants?

^7Canst thou fill his skin with barbed irons? or his head with fish spears?

^8Lay thine hand upon him, remember the battle, do no more.

^9Behold, the hope of him is in vain: shall not one be cast down even at the sight of him?

^10None is so fierce that dare stir him up: who then is able to stand before me?

^11Who hath prevented me, that I should repay him? whatsoever is under the whole heaven is mine.

^12I will not conceal his parts, nor his power, nor his comely proportion.

^13Who can discover the face of his garment? or who can come to him with his double bridle?

^14Who can open the doors of his face? his teeth are terrible round about.

^15His scales are his pride, shut up together as with a close seal.

^16One is so near to another, that no air can come between them.

^17They are joined one to another, they stick together, that they cannot be sundered.

^18By his neesings a light doth shine, and his eyes are like the eyelids of the morning.

^19Out of his mouth go burning lamps, and sparks of fire leap out.

^20Out of his nostrils goeth smoke, as out of a seething pot or caldron.

^21His breath kindleth coals, and a flame goeth out of his mouth.

^22In his neck remaineth strength, and sorrow is turned into joy before him.

^23The flakes of his flesh are joined together: they are firm in themselves; they cannot be moved.

^24His heart is as firm as a stone; yea, as hard as a piece of the nether millstone.

^25When he raiseth up himself, the mighty are afraid: by reason of breakings they purify themselves.

^26The sword of him that layeth at him cannot hold: the spear, the dart, nor the habergeon.

^27He esteemeth iron as straw, and brass as rotten wood.

^28The arrow cannot make him flee: slingstones are turned with him into stubble.

^29Darts are counted as stubble: he laugheth at the shaking of a spear.

^30Sharp stones are under him: he spreadeth sharp pointed things upon the mire.

^31He maketh the deep to boil like a pot: he maketh the sea like a pot of ointment.

^32He maketh a path to shine after him; one would think the deep to be hoary.

^33Upon earth there is not his like, who is made without fear.

^34He beholdeth all high things: he is a king over all the children of pride.

Job 42

42^1Then Job answered the Lord, and said,

^2I know that thou canst do every thing, and that no thought can be withholden from thee.

^3Who is he that hideth counsel without knowledge? therefore have I uttered that I understood not; things too wonderful for me, which I knew not.

^4Hear, I beseech thee, and I will speak: I will demand of thee, and declare thou unto me.

^5I have heard of thee by the hearing of the ear: but now mine eye seeth thee.

^6Wherefore I abhor myself, and repent in dust and ashes.

^7And it was so, that after the Lord had spoken these words unto Job, the Lord said to Eliphaz the Temanite, My wrath is kindled against thee, and against thy two friends: for ye have not spoken of me the thing that is right, as my servant Job hath.

^8Therefore take unto you now seven bullocks and seven rams, and go to my servant Job, and offer up for yourselves a burnt offering; and my servant Job shall pray for you: for him will I accept: lest I deal with you after your folly, in that ye have not spoken of me the thing which is right, like my servant Job.

^9So Eliphaz the Temanite and Bildad the Shuhite and Zophar the Naamathite went, and did according as the Lord commanded them: the Lord also accepted Job.

^10And the Lord turned the captivity of Job, when he prayed for his friends: also the Lord gave Job twice as much as he had before.

^11Then came there unto him all his brethren, and all his sisters, and all they that had been of his acquaintance before, and did eat bread with him in his house: and they bemoaned him, and comforted him over all the evil that the Lord had brought upon him: every man also gave him a piece of money, and every one an earring of gold.

^12So the Lord blessed the latter end of Job more than his beginning: for he had fourteen thousand sheep, and six thousand camels, and a thousand yoke of oxen, and a thousand she asses.

^13He had also seven sons and three daughters.

^14And he called the name of the first, Jemima; and the name of the second, Kezia; and the name of the third, Kerenhappuch.

^15And in all the land were no women found so fair as the daughters of Job: and their father gave them inheritance among their brethren.

^16After this lived Job an hundred and forty years, and saw his sons, and his sons’ sons, even four generations.

^17So Job died, being old and full of days.